<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phonetics-phonology interface on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Phonetics-phonology interface on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Жизненный цикл морфонологических процессов в русском языке</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</guid>
      <description>Характерное свойство динамических подходов к русской фонологии и морфонологии — как выполненных в духе порождающих фонологических теорий, так и (пост)структуралистских — обширное использование правил, обязательно применяемых в определенном порядке. Обоснование этого порядка — важнейшая задача для теоретического осмысления фактов русского языка, без решения которой динамические подходы являются по сути нефальсифицируемыми: в отсутствие четких ограничений на количество правил и порядок их применения любое чередование можно подвергнуть сколь угодно абстрактному анализу с произвольным количеством правил.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There is no problem of /v/ in Russian phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</guid>
      <description>The dual behaviour of /v/ has been a notorious crux in Russian phonology since at least Jakobson (1956). The basic problem is that /v/ fails to trigger voicing assimilation, like sonorants, but undergoes both assimilation to following obstruents and final devoicing, like obstruents.
The commonest solution in the literature is representational: [v] is treated as a sonorant, either an underlying /w/ (Lightner 1972, Hayes 1984, Kiparsky 1985) or some labial non-glide (Coats &amp;amp; Harshenin 1971, Padgett 2002).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
      <description>‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A substance-free framework for phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-book/</guid>
      <description>The book is a revised and updated version of parts of my PhD thesis. From the publisher&amp;rsquo;s blurb:
 What is the relationship between phonetics and phonology? Are phonological features innate and universal, and do they have fixed phonetic correlates? These questions have recently received renewed prominence in theoretical debates, and this book explores them from a modular, substance-free perspective.
This in-depth analysis of Breton serves not only to introduce previously underused data into the theoretical landscape but also to demonstrate the viability of a modular framework for phonology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making sense of consonant palatalization vowel backness in Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</guid>
      <description>Despite its status as a minority language, Modern Irish has a rich body of phonetic and phonological descriptions, based on (near-)native fieldworker knowledge and traditional auditory methods. In this paper, we draw on a range of up-to-date instrumental and quantitative methods in order to verify and expand the traditional findings regarding the nature and status of the interaction between consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish.
According to the descriptive literature, there are several types of consonant-to-vowel coarticulation in Modern Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short vowel allophones in Modern Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/tionol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/tionol/</guid>
      <description>We present the results of a study of the acoustic properties of short vowels in Modern Irish, building on data from all three major dialect groupings. It is well known that short vowels in Irish are realized as back or front depending on the palatalization of the surrounding consonants (thus liom [u] but linn [i]). In addition, traditional descriptions also recognize that vowels can also have a number of distinct allophones whose distribution also depends on surrounding consonants: for instance, De Bhaldraithe (1945) describes four distinct varieties of [a] in Cois Fhairrge Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems of phonemicization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/clc9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/clc9/</guid>
      <description>We address a long-standing issue in the phonology of Modern Irish: the phonological status of the distinction between front and back short vowels. We argue that the approach inherent in most theoretical work on the topic, which privileges traditional &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; criteria such as predictability of distribution, misses important generalizations and cannot be sustained. Instead, we suggest that front and back (non-low) vowels in Irish are best thought of as phonologically &amp;lsquo;distinctive&amp;rsquo;, but not (significantly) &amp;lsquo;contrastive&amp;rsquo; units.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels: phonology and/or coarticulation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents much the same material as our presentation at OCP13</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel backness and palatalization in Irish and Scottish Gaelic: A study in rule scattering</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</guid>
      <description>We present the results of an acoustic study of the interaction of consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels. Previous descriptions of Irish (but usually not of Scottish Gaelic) often describe the distribution of front vs. back nonlow vowels as predictable (allophonic). This makes Irish a potential example of a vertical vowel system. However, the sources are mostly impressionistic, and also tend to underplay the extent of variation within and across lexical items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonetic (non-)explanation in historical phonology: Duration, harmony, and dissimilation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</guid>
      <description>We consider the value of phonetically based explanations for phonological change by tracing the phonologization paths of durational asymmetries between vowels. The literature on phonetic motivations for phonological change identifies relative shortness of one vowel with respect to another as an important precursor to vowel reduction, which, in turn, may feed hypercorrection of the reduced vowel to give rise to vowel harmony phenomena. We examine such a case from Nivkh in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free and not so free</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</guid>
      <description>I offer an analysis of &amp;lsquo;length&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;tenseness&amp;rsquo; found in an acoustic study of eight speakers. The results confirm the existence of a categorical pattern whereby the quality of long mid vowels in penults depends on the phonological height of the following vowel (Awbery 1984, Wmffre 2003). One speaker shows a distribution of tenseness that categorically tracks length in penults, much as described in the literature and shown for monosyllables by Mayr &amp;amp; Davies (2011).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantity-quality interactions in Welsh vowels</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</guid>
      <description>I present the results of a phonetic study of the relationship between vowel quality and vowel quantity. The results confirm that the descriptions are correct in setting up a categorical distinction between two varieties of long mid vowels (tense [eː oː] and lax [ɛː ɔː]) in South-West Welsh. This system plausibly arose as the enhancement of a pattern where there is no quality distinctions between short and long vowels, with continuous variation in height in both prosodic contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Length and tenseness across Welsh dialects</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the First Conference on Linguistic Diversity in Wales at the National Library of Wales in Aberystwyth.
This talk is about the interaction of vowel quantity and quality in different dialects of Welsh. According to existing descriptions, Welsh is a bit like English in that its short vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; in quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ ə]) and its long vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; ([iː uː eː oː]).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress and consonant length in Welsh revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</guid>
      <description>I</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The [ATR]/laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</guid>
      <description>I offer a preliminary analysis of the phenomenon of calediad (&amp;lsquo;provection&amp;rsquo;) in South-Eastern Welsh, whereby &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (lenis) stops become &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; after a stressed vowel. I argue that since vowels before lenis stops are generally long &amp;mdash; and, given the phonology of South Welsh &amp;mdash; tense, provection is an example of vowel-consonant interaction, where the same feature is used for the tense/lax contrast in vowels and laryngeal contrast in consonants. I interpret this as supporting emergent feature theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</guid>
      <description>Here, I propose an analysis of the interacting between final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian (and other related varieties of northern Italy). Historically, stressed vowels lengthen before voiced obstruents, but this is opacified by final devoicing. I capitalize on phonetic studies showing final devoicing in the language to be incomplete and argue that the process is not in fact opaque: devoicing does not involve neutralization but instead the creation of a third, laryngealy unspecified class of obstruents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started here. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian palatalization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</guid>
      <description>In this talk we argue that the traditional view of vowel-driven palatalization in Russian is inadequate, at least for two reasons. First, it relies on a six-vowel interpretation of the Russian inventory that is not adequate from a phonetic perspective. Second, and more importantly, it undergenerates the range of alternations found in Modern Standard Russian. Instead, we argue that palatalization must be driven by a floating feature attached to the left edge of suffixes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fonetikk versus fonologi</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</guid>
      <description>Dette er det fyrste føredraget i prosjektet om russisk vokalreduksjon. Sluttversjonen kan ein finne i denne artikkelen.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>