<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Phonetics Phonology Interface in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="http://anghyflawn.github.io/img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 21:35:23 GMT</updated>



<item>
<title>Teachings</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Presentations</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Pavel Iosad</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>North Germanic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/north-germanic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/north-germanic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Laryngeal Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Norwegian preaspiration in traditional and modern sources</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/fgls/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/fgls/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I survey traditional descriptions of Norwegian dialects
with particular attention to their discussion of voiceless stop
preaspiration, and conclude that it is highly probable preaspiration has
been consistently under-reported in these sources. As surveyed in detail
by Pétur Helgason (2002), preaspiration in Norwegian has been reported
most prominently for northern Gudbrandsdalen (Ross 1907; Horne 1917),
Rogaland (Oftedal 1947; Wolter 1965), and for Senja by Iversen (1913).
To Helgason’s list should be added Vestvågøya (Elstad 1982) and contact
varieties in Northern Norway (Jahr 2008). Other varieties, by
implication, lack preaspiration, and it is usually treated as
characteristic of most mainland North Germanic varieties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I survey the results of recent empirical studies. Pétur Helgason
(2002) has shown that preaspiration is widespread in mainland
varieties; in particular, he has demonstrated that it is pervasive,
albeit variable, in Central Standard Swedish. Preaspiration has also
been shown to exist in Trøndelag (Moxness 1998; van Dommelen 1998; van
Dommelen, Holm &amp;amp; Koreman 2011; Ringen &amp;amp; van Dommelen 2013), Dalane
(Tengesdal 2015), and Oslo (Allen 2016). Finally, I briefly present
the results of my own instrumental study demonstrating the
pervasiveness of preaspiration in speakers from both Rogaland and
Northern Norway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argue that this situation is less likely to be due to language change,
and more likely to reflect fieldworkers’ lack of expectation to find
preaspiration: for instance, Elstad (1982) notes preaspiration for
Vestvågøya where Christiansen (1933) does not mention it for the
neighbouring island of Gimsøya; Tengesdal (2015) directly contradicts
Oftedal’s (1947) impressionistic claims — even though the same author
correctly identified preaspiration in Scottish Gaelic (Oftedal 1956). I
compare these findings to the recent discussion by Kristoffersen (2016)
of the late discovery of the lack of tonal contrasts in rural dialects
around Bergen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Current Issues in Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/current-issues-in-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/current-issues-in-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This advanced course introduces students to a variety of live research issues in phonological theory. I teach this course with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/heinz-giegerich&#34;&gt;Heinz Giegerich&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt;. Check back nearer the time for a list of topics I will cover.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2e/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2e/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is (optionally) a part of the pre-Honours sequence in the Linguistics undergraduate degree (but can of course be taken as an outside course). In &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I am responsible for the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Indo-European language family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in the phonology of European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-Indo-European languages of Europe (Basque; Finno-Ugric)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I am acting as the course organizer for LEL2D. I am also responsible for the entire phonology block.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course (co-taught with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt;) we consider a variety of issues connected to phonological change. Throughout the course, we address questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we reconstruct the phonology of past language states?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What types of phonological changes are attested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can synchronic phonological theory assist us in the study of historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn about the human language faculty by studying historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I will cover the following topics (subject to change with extreme prejudice):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanisms and types of phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical phonology and phonological representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>News</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 21:44:31 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teaching</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 21:44:31 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In the second semester of &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I am teaching &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc10046.htm&#34;&gt;Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt; (Honours/MSc), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc10089.htm&#34;&gt;Current Issues in Phonology&lt;/a&gt; (Honours/MSc), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc08020.htm&#34;&gt;LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours; I am also the course organizer), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc08021.htm&#34;&gt;LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxcelt08019.htm&#34;&gt;Linguistics and the Gaelic Language&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Pilot</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/pilot/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 21:41:13 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/pilot/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I have been awarded funding from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ppls.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;School of Philosophy, Psychology and Language Sciences&lt;/a&gt; Pilot Project Fund to initiate work on a database of Gaelic dialect forms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Fgls</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/fgls/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 21:39:32 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/fgls/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I will present &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/fgls/&#34;&gt;Norwegian preaspiration in traditional and modern sources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.conferences.cahss.ed.ac.uk/germanic-language-studies/&#34;&gt;13th Forum for Germanic Language Studies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Esohph</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/esohph/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/esohph/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offered two presentations at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/symposium-on-historical-phonology/&#34;&gt;Third Edinburgh Symposium on Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on pre-sonorant voicing and language contact in the fringe session on laryngeal phonology and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/&#34;&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt; on the history of Brythonic tense and lax vowels in the main session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Welsh</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/welsh/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/breton/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Towards a history of the tenseness contrast in Brythonic vowels</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Modern Welsh is similar to many modern Germanic languages such as English, German and Dutch in showing an association between &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; vowel quality and phonological length. Specifically, long vowels tend to be tense in quality and short vowels tend to be lax, with concomitant alternations. As in the Germanic case, there is some disagreement in the literature on whether quality or quantity (or both) is phonologically relevant in Modern Welsh. In this paper I aim to add to this debate via an overview of the diatopic variation in the relationship between vowel quantity and quality in Welsh and more broadly in the Brythonic languages. I argue that tense/lax quality is likely to be diachronically secondary with respect to quantity, being derivable from prosodic contexts &amp;mdash; primarily vowel length and syllable structure. One of the notable consequences of this is that even when tense/lax quality has been phonologized (as in, for instance, south-western dialects of Welsh), it is still partly conditioned by quantity and syllable structure; conversely, the distribution of quantity is not significantly determined by vowel quality, which supports the contention that quantity is synchronically active in Welsh phonology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support this case for a secondary development of tense/lax quality, I offer a reconstruction of its rise that starts with a tensing of word-final stressed vowels, perhaps initially only restricted to high vowels. This later undergoes rule generalization  to embrace both non-high vowels (as in most dialects with tense [e: oː]) and to syllable-final rather than word-final position (as in South Welsh dialects, where long vowels are allowed in penultimate stressed syllables). I show that intermediate stages of this development are attested across modern Welsh dialects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argue that the Brythonic languages present an interesting test case for theories that attempt to connect the &amp;lsquo;transphonologization&amp;rsquo; of quantity as quality with the rise of vowel shifts: despite the long/short vowels undergoing a tense/lax split, much as in many Germanic languages, the Brythonic system neither became prone to vowel shifting (as in the case of English) nor underwent a further split where the new qualities fit into a new quantity system (as in many North Germanic varieties).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Pre-sonorant voicing and language contact</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I draw attention to the fact that whilst pre-sonorant voicing of &lt;em&gt;fricatives&lt;/em&gt; across a word boundary appears to be fairly widely spread (at least in Europe), pre-sonorant voicing of &lt;em&gt;all obstruents&lt;/em&gt; appears to cluster in areas where &amp;lsquo;aspirating&amp;rsquo; languages are in contact with &amp;lsquo;voice&amp;rsquo; languages: the languages involved are Breton (Celtic/Gallo-Romance), Franconian/Netherlandic (e.g. Limburg Dutch, Luxembourgish), Western Polish and Slovak (Slavic/Germanic).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Blogs</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Language is only as divisive as you make it</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2017/language-divisive-as-you-make-it/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 09:50:48 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2017/language-divisive-as-you-make-it/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;It gives me no pleasure but the recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/language-is-an-important-but-divisive-force-k5prqm9ff&#34;&gt;opinion&lt;/a&gt; in The Times by the highly respected journalist Magnus Linklater really deserves a response. In a handy 899 words, it shows all the blind spots of a majority establishment that simply does not see what the deal is with minority languages. I can see where this position is coming from (Russia is not the most progressive country for awareness of its minority languages among the majority population), but really, one expects better &amp;mdash; not just as far as the policy  proposals go (we can surely disagree on that) but even in terms of basic journalism. The piece is full of inaccuracies that may not matter much for the central point, but boy do they get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it would be desperately sad to lose such an important part of our
heritage. I remember summer holidays in Ullapool and Mallaig, where
the herring were being packed in barrels by women who spoke to each
other entirely in Gaelic - as pure as you could get. The herring are
long gone. I hope the Gaelic survives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well that&amp;rsquo;s awfully nice. But note that we&amp;rsquo;re already slipping into the trope of non-modernity. Not only is Gaelic associated primarily with a traditional industry but it is also described as &amp;lsquo;pure&amp;rsquo;. When was the last time you heard someone&amp;rsquo;s English described as &amp;lsquo;pure&amp;rsquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t let&amp;rsquo;s pretend, however, that it is our second language. For
all the street signs, station names and border posts translated
laboriously into Gaelic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another trope. &amp;lsquo;All&amp;rsquo; the street signs? &amp;lsquo;Laboriously&amp;rsquo; translated? This makes it sound like some sort of heroic enterprise whereby there are forests of signs going up all over Scotland. In Edinburgh, I am aware of precisely zero bilingual street signs. The number of &amp;lsquo;border posts&amp;rsquo; can&amp;rsquo;t possibly be that large. Nor, in the grand scheme of things, is the cost of renewing some station signs (lots of them, incidentally, in the Highlands).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or the £30 million spent annually on promoting it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah yes, let&amp;rsquo;s put a price on it. How much on promoting English? How much of this money is spent on education and would therefore be spent in the English-medium education system anyway? We&amp;rsquo;re not told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we are no more a bilingual nation than Cornwall or the Isle of Man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose at least someone in Cornwall or the Isle of Man might take exception to that, but we can let that pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to reverse that decline, the 2005 Gaelic Language Act,
which gave Gaelic formal recognition in Scotland, laid down that it
should command &amp;ldquo;equal respect&amp;rdquo; with English but stopped well short
of insisting on its use&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, &amp;lsquo;equal respect&amp;rsquo; is a largely symbolic policy with not much in the way of real teeth to enforce it if it is not complied with. This is 100% true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just take a look at Catalonia, where since the early 1980s the
&amp;ldquo;immersion&amp;rdquo; system in schools has transformed Catalan from an
archaic Latin-based tongue, once suppressed by Franco, into the
official language of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is so confused one doesn&amp;rsquo;t know where to start. Immersion education has, in principle, nothing to do with &amp;lsquo;official&amp;rsquo; status. Immersion is meant to produce more speakers &amp;mdash; this is what we do in Scotland without Gaelic being the &amp;lsquo;official language of the nation&amp;rsquo;. The rhetorical contrast between &amp;lsquo;archaic Latin-based tongue&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;official&amp;rsquo; language of the nation makes no sense. Why bring in &amp;lsquo;Latin-based&amp;rsquo; at all &amp;mdash; after all the majority language in the Catalan situation is the equally &amp;lsquo;Latin-based&amp;rsquo; Spanish. And note the non-modernity trope again &amp;mdash; how is Catalan &amp;lsquo;archaic&amp;rsquo;? (On the scale of how much it has changed from Latin it is roughly at the same stage as Spanish, somewhere in the middle between Sardinian and French, but it&amp;rsquo;s still difficult to see what this has to do with anything.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence it has become a divisive force. For those who want to stay part of Spain, it is the language of nationalism and separation; for those who back independence, it is simply the expression of who they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we come to the nub and the ground zero of projection. Here&amp;rsquo;s the thing: people speak a language because it&amp;rsquo;s central to who they are, or who they want to be, and there is absolutely no logical necessity that it should align to constitutional preferences. There are Spanish-speaking nationalists, and there are Catalan-speaking unionists. Minority languages are not spoken to spite the unionist majority. To say that Catalan was made divisive by immersion education feeding young nationalists, in the same breath as noting it was suppressed by Franco, honestly beggars belief. To blame the people who fought for the right to be educated, and live their lives through their own language, a right that was denied to them, for being divisive, betrays an unwillingness to step away from the majority&amp;rsquo;s view of minorities as a needy nuisance. It would be equally naive, of course, to say that the Catalan language question is completely politics-free, but here we are putting the blame squarely on the minority and not on a state with previous form for less enlightened attitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pressure to preserve a language is, of course, a strong one. There are those who argue that unless Gaelic is given official status it will be lost. They point to Wales, where the Welsh Language Measure of 2011 made it de jure the language of the state - the only part of the UK where English is not the principal language of government. Even here, however, the percentage of those speaking Welsh has dropped below the 20 per cent level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that is the point. The reason the Welsh Language Measure was introduced was that previous Welsh Language Acts, whilst fairly successful in many respects, particularly within education, the arts and the official sphere, were not sufficient to build many robust Welsh-language arenas, for instance in the private sector. This is exactly why Wales has moved to a language commissioner model, whose intent is to make sure Welsh-language provision can be expanded beyond areas directly funded by the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaelic, by contrast, has been in decline for far longer, and has
never been truly the language of the establishment; the writer Allan
Massie argues that the last king of Scotland to have spoken Gaelic
was James IV in the 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is telling that Allan Massie (with all due respect), and not, say,
Charles Withers is the principal authority on the history of Gaelic,
but the important thing rhetorically is that again the case for Gaelic
is connected to the pre-modern past. Literally no-one serious is
basing proposals for a stronger Gaelic policy on how long it survived
as the language of the Scottish court. The reason stronger statutory
protection for Gaelic is needed is that it represents best practice in
building sustainable minority language communities, not that James IV
spoke it. This is a straw man and a continuation of unfortunate
framing of the language as irrelevant in the modern age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking to elevate its status would, therefore, be to reverse a
 centuries-long trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;trend&amp;rsquo; being, of course, often the result of quite deliberate
government policy. But let&amp;rsquo;s not mention government policy, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finland, once part of the Swedish empire, framed its laws in
Swedish, and Finns spoke it as the national language, even after
their country was annexed by Russia in 1809.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not obvious what it means that the Finns &amp;lsquo;spoke it as the
national language&amp;rsquo;. Yes, educated citizens of the Grand Duchy of
Finland routinely read, wrote and spoke Swedish, but Finnish was also
there, wasn&amp;rsquo;t it? The words &amp;lsquo;national language&amp;rsquo; are doing a lot of
work here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, after independence in 1917, the Finnish language, whose
origins go back to the Magyar empire of the middle ages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is so wrong it&amp;rsquo;s good. Yes, Finnish is (distantly) related to
Hungarian but the Magyar settlement of Pannonia has absolutely nothing
to do with Finland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and which was once used mainly in rural areas, gradually gained the
ascendancy and today, on the centenary of independence, has become
the language of the majority with barely 5 per cent speaking Swedish
for preference. Even here, however, language has its tensions. Try
going into a shop in rural Finland and speaking Swedish: you may get
a dusty response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority in Finland always spoke Finnish &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s just that the
elite stopped being exclusively Swedish-speaking. (Also, I wonder if
the &amp;lsquo;dusty&amp;rsquo; response has to do with people&amp;rsquo;s command of a language
they learn at school but don&amp;rsquo;t use much, rather than divisive
nationalist politics?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How then can Gaelic be saved? Probably by making it a vital part of
our education system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what Ireland and Wales and many other places have been
doing. And we know that it&amp;rsquo;s very important, but we also &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that
it&amp;rsquo;s not enough. Education is vital, but providing a sphere for the
language beyond the school is more vital still. This is exactly why
Wales has been trying to push for a more assertive language policy.
This is why when you visit Catalonia or the Basque Country and see the
bilingual (trilingual, even) signs literally everywhere and not just
on the odd railway station, you see just how much stronger their
language policies are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the unchanged Scottish state system flatlining at best, those
schools teaching Gaelic are often better resourced,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no evidence for this. Certainly, none is given. Generally,
this seems to be a meme among opponents of Gaelic-medium education.
(In Edinburgh, this seems to be fuelled by the fact that GME at
secondary level is offered at the desirable James Gillespie&amp;rsquo;s High
School &amp;mdash; largely by virtue of the fact that before the opening of
the dedicated school the Gaelic-medium primary unit was at Tollcross
Primary, which feeds into JGHS, meaning that&amp;rsquo;s where the expertise
is.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;give pupils the extra dimension of a second language and provide
greater stimulation than the relatively unchallenging Curriculum for
Excellence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without getting into a scrap over education policy, which is something
I&amp;rsquo;m not competent to do, Gaelic-medium education in Scotland offers
the Curriculum for Excellence, except it&amp;rsquo;s in Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gaelic they have been taught may indeed have been &amp;ldquo;broken&amp;rdquo; by
modern jargon, but those who have learnt it will have become
familiar with the lilting quality and romantic poetry of a language
once spoken by the bards and a part of culture that enriched
Scotland&amp;rsquo;s life and heritage. Better by far to have absorbed a
language at source than that the state should try to force it onto
the statute books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once again the pre-modern framing. Do you ever hear Coleridge and Milton referred to as a justification for the massive support the government gives to English, by teaching it at schools, supporting the arts, funding a broadcaster? No. Do you ever hear that we should all be learning English because it&amp;rsquo;s the language of international commerce? That&amp;rsquo;s preposterous. English is taught and supported because it is the language of its speakers, and that is justification enough. So why is it not enough for Gaelic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most perniciously, the sweet words about &amp;lsquo;lilting quality&amp;rsquo; and bards are just an excuse to say &amp;lsquo;the burden of reviving the language is on the speakers&amp;rsquo;. It is on them to come through the school and keep using their Gaelic, as we keep it off the statute books. &amp;lsquo;We&amp;rsquo;, the majority, don&amp;rsquo;t need to do anything, need suffer no inconvenience, not even the indignity of seeing a railway station sign. How are people meant to keep using their Gaelic outside of their own circle when the state offers no protection, no support for it? We&amp;rsquo;re not told. And when the small numbers of speakers give up, dwindle further in the monolingual sea of the modern nation-state, we shrug our shoulders and say &amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo;s a centuries-long trend; should&amp;rsquo;ve taken better care of it, really&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can, and should, do better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>History of Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 15:02:16 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I have a uploaded a draft version of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/history-of-phonology/&#34;&gt;paper on phonology in the Soviet Union&lt;/a&gt; for the forthcoming &lt;em&gt;Oxford History of Phonology&lt;/em&gt;. Comments welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Univariate Statistics and Methodology Using R</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/univariate-stats/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/univariate-stats/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is an introductory postgraduate course in statistics and statistical methodology offered to all PG students in the School. This year I am co-teaching this course with &lt;a href=&#34;www.ed.ac.uk/profile/martin-corley&#34;&gt;Dr Martin Corley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to a range of important topics in (generative) phonological theory and to phonological data analysis. On the theoretical side, we cover the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of phonological theory: contrast, phonemes, allophones, alternations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivations, underlying representations, rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process interaction and rule ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suprasegmental phonology: syllable structure, stress, tone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced feature theory: feature geometry, unary features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explanation in phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, there is a strong emphasis on building data analysis and problem solving skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is also offered for MSc students (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc11148.htm&#34;&gt;LASC11148&lt;/a&gt;). It is suitable for postgraduate students who have had some previous exposure to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this course, students will be able to progress to advanced study of phonological theory. In &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, we are offering both LASC10089 Current Issues in Phonology and LASC10046 Historical Phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Writings</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>History of Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonology in the Soviet Union</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This invited contribution to a collection on the history of phonology explores the history of phonological studies in the USSR. I offer a short history of phonology in Russia and the USSR before the formation of the two main theoretical currents (the &amp;lsquo;Leningrad&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Moscow&amp;rsquo; schools), and emphasize both their mutual common roots and their closeness to other structuralist frameworks, in particular Prague phonology. I discuss the differences between the two schools both in their approach to the phoneme and in their analysis of morphophonological alternations. Throughout, the focus is on the ways in which a focus on Russian shaped the directions of phonological thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>dias</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/dias/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/dias/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented some fledgling work on the history of the tense/lax distinction and quality in Brythonic vowels at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dias.ie/2017/05/17/symposium-new-approaches-to-brittonic-historical-linguistics/&#34;&gt;New Approaches to Brittonic Historical Linguistics&lt;/a&gt; symposium at the Dublin Institute of Advanced Studies. Get the slides and handout &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/dias/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/celtic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/celtic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Bridging the gap</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/dias/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/dias/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I focus on reconstructing the development of vowel quality distinctions
in Brythonic and their connection with the history of vowel quantity
between the establishment of the ‘standard’ Brythonic penultimate-stress
system and the present day. In the received picture of Modern Welsh
phonology, ‘tense’ quality of non-low vowels ([i u e o]) is strongly
associated with length and, conversely, ‘lax’ quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ]) is
associated with shortness, at least in contrastive, i.e.stressed,
position. The history of this pattern, however, remains understudied.
Some important questions that remain to be addressed are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When and how did contrastive length in penultimate syllables
(characteristic of South Welsh, Cornish and most of Breton) become
established? Is it original (and thus preserved following the stress
shift), or does it represent a secondary lengthening of vowels that
had been shortened in unstressed position? What is the position of
North Welsh with its exclusively short vowels in stressed penults
(cf. Wmffre 2003)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Similarly, does the tense/lax quality of vowels in Welsh reflect
tense/lax quality before the stress shift, or does it represent a
secondary readjustment? What is the relationship between the pattern
in stressed penultimates and in final unstressed syllables (where at
least high vowels seem to show an original length conditioning, at
least in Welsh)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is the complementary pattern of vowel and consonant length in
penultimate syllables, which is practically universal in Brythonic,
original, as implied by e.g.the classic account by Falc’hun (1951),
or is it a secondary development following stress shift?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discuss the problems raised for these issues by traditional sources,
notably the focus on taxonomic phonemic transcription and the frequent
sidelining of consonant duration. I outline what kinds of studies are
needed to mitigate these problems. I also draw attention to some
evidence for the existence of dialects in Mid Wales that may lack a
tenseness distinction in at least some stressed syllables, and discuss
whether such systems can be accepted as evidence for the historically
secondary status of tenseness in penultimate stressed syllables.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Senior Tutor</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/senior-tutor/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2017 16:19:06 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/senior-tutor/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;From 1 August 2017 I am the Senior Tutor in the School of Philosophy, Psychology and Language Sciences. Please use &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ppls.senior.tutor@ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;ppls.senior.tutor@ed.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt; for any queries related to that role.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>tphs paper</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/tphs-paper/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/tphs-paper/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My paper &lt;em&gt;Welsh svarabhakti as stem allomorphy&lt;/em&gt; has appeared in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philsoc.org.uk/transactions.asp&#34;&gt;Transactions of the Philological Society&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Download the draft version &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or the official version &lt;a href=&#34;https://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1467-968X.12085&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonology Morphology Interface</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonology-morphology-interface/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonology-morphology-interface/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Welsh svarabhakti as stem allomorphy</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper develops the analysis in &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/&#34;&gt;this presentation&lt;/a&gt;. I offer an analysis of Welsh epenthesis, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (&lt;em&gt;pwdr&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]) and deletion in such clusters in polysyllables (&lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has previously been argued that both processes can be analysed in a single phonological grammar. I show that this is not tenable for South Welsh dialects, and propose an analysis in terms of part-of-speech-specific allomorphy, formalized as lexical storage of POS-characterized stems rather than roots.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>25mfm</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/25mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/25mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;em&gt;Microvariation in laryngeal realism: Preaspiration in North Germanic&lt;/em&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/mfm/25mfm.html&#34;&gt;25th Manchester Phonology Meeting&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/25mfm/&#34;&gt;Get the slides and handout here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Substance Free Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/substance-free-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/substance-free-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Microvariation in laryngeal realism</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/25mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/25mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I consider the range of microvariation in the expression of laryngeal contrast, focusing on (voiceless) preaspiration in North Germanic. On the basis of an acoustic study, I suggest that both the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization have been under-reported in existing descriptions. This, in turn, has important consequences for our understanding of the phonology of laryngeal contrast. Specifically, I argue that the observed variation in laryngeal phenomena is incompatible with a version of &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; that produces inferences about phonological specifications on the basis of phonetic implementation; instead, I advocate a more abstract approach that gives primacy to phonological behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed by Pétur Helgason (2002), whilst preaspiration and sonorant devoicing before stops in Insular North Germanic have long been recognized by the scholarship, their distribution and behaviour in mainland varieties have been less well understood. In the case of Norwegian, for example, traditional descriptions designate preaspiration as characteristic of Jæren and Gudbrandsdalen, with only passing references for other dialects. However, Pétur Helgason has shown preaspiration to be pervasive in other North Germanic varieties. More recently preaspiration has also been described for the Norwegian of Trøndelag. Moreover, it appears possible that this picture may be partially due to under-reporting in traditional auditory descriptions: thus, Tengesdal (2015), in an instrumental study, shows that Oftedal&amp;rsquo;s (1947) claim that preaspiration of fortis stops is absent in Dalane Norwegian is likely incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I report a comparative acoustic study of preaspiration in two regions of Norway: the south-west, parts of which (Jæren, parts of Dalane) are traditionally considered preaspirating areas, and the north, where preaspiration has not been consistently described before. I show that preaspiration is  attested in (at least some) northern dialects, at rates not dissimilar to those in the west. More importantly, the data show a more granular diversity than is implied by broad dialectal labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This microvariation in the expression of laryngeal contrast is important for our understanding of the relationship between phonological specification and phonetic substance. In particular, I suggest that the precise phonetic interpretation of a distinction between (say) fortis and lenis stops can be much more diverse than can be provided for by a theory deriving these differences from phonological specification, such as some versions of laryngeal realism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further argument in favour of the primacy of phonological behaviour is provided by [ʁ]-devoicing in south-western dialects. I argue that is both phonetically categorical (in contrast to lateral and nasal devoicing) and phonological, being triggered only by |fortis| stops. Crucially, lenis stops do not trigger any sonorant devoicing, even gradiently, despite being categorically voiceless (rather than &amp;lsquo;passively voiced&amp;rsquo;) themselves. This coarse-grained phonological behaviour is consistent with a substance-free privative analysis where obstruents are specified as |fortis| vs. ∅, but not with one that attempts to capture the phonetic behaviour of lenis stops in phonological representations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The government has a plan for Gaelic, and you won&#39;t believe what it is</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2017/dastardly-plan-gaelic/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2017/dastardly-plan-gaelic/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;An important dimension that&amp;rsquo;s often missing from the debates about whether it&amp;rsquo;s worthwhile to support Gaelic or promote Scots in Scotland is &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; one would do such a thing in the first place. In today&amp;rsquo;s feverish political environment these things slide all too often into outright constitutional mudslinging or at least a debate that foregrounds the essential Scottishness of the country&amp;rsquo;s languages, either as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thenational.scot/comment/14871672.Wee_Ginger_Dug__A_Gaelic_map_isn___t____Gaelic_imperialism_____it___s_a_restorative_act_for_the_language_which_created_Scotland&#34;&gt;good thing&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scotsman.com/news/opinion/comment-gaelic-signs-a-spurious-vanity-project-for-snp-1-4442999&#34;&gt;bad thing&lt;/a&gt;. Scott Hames has &lt;a href=&#34;http://bellacaledonia.org.uk/2016/02/19/not-nationality-but-language&#34;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; about this approach being unhelpful, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2016/gaelic-belongs-to-all/&#34;&gt;I agree&lt;/a&gt;. But if this is not about nationality, &lt;em&gt;why indeed&lt;/em&gt; would one put up Gaelic signs in the Borders or push for more recognition of Scots?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several misconceptions are widespread among both opponents and supporters of minority language promotion. For instance, the introduction of Gaelic or Scots into schools is often framed as an attempt by the government to &amp;lsquo;teach [alternatively, indoctrinate] the children to speak&amp;rsquo; the minority language &amp;mdash; ominously, at the expense of Standard English? The infamous Gaelic signs (the number of which in all of the Lowlands probably runs, let&amp;rsquo;s face it, into the low three figures) are seen as an attempt to stake a claim on territory for Gaelic, presumably on the basis of it having been spoken in the area historically; this often tends to provoke a backlash along the lines of &amp;lsquo;why don&amp;rsquo;t we promote Welsh then &amp;mdash; isn&amp;rsquo;t it the closest living relative of the historical language of Lowland Scotland?&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@theiaincameron/gaelic-road-signs-f14235b2984b&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a typical example.  This latter argument, of course, is only true if the purpose of Gaelic signs is to promote Gaelic for these historical reasons &amp;mdash; which supporters of the language are often wont to support, pointing to the very real Gaelic heritage of much of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ideas, whether espoused by well-wishers or detractors of minority languages, suffer from a failure to invert the majority&amp;rsquo;s perspective. Those who do not identify as members of the linguistic minority tend to see language policy as largely aimed at &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;, rather than catering for the needs and desires of the minority speakers themselves. Hence the frequent trope of the language being &amp;lsquo;pushed down our throats&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;subsidies&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;catering to the needs of the minority at the expense of the majority&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the problem: the kind of visible gestures that raise the most public ire are, in fact, just that: gestures. It is preposterous to think that having a &amp;lsquo;Burns week&amp;rsquo; at school or a bunch of English lessons attempting to write a poem in Scots (it&amp;rsquo;s always a poem, of course) is sufficient to guide pupils&amp;rsquo; linguistic behaviour outside class. The way people end up speaking depends on the speech first of their caregivers, then of their peers, perhaps particularly in adolescence, and also on their attitude to the different in- and out-groups they are members of.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A lesson or two in written Scots will no more turn a child with a middle-class accent into a speaker of broad Scots than many years of schooling eradicate non-standard varieties in working-class communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, a couple of signs at a railway station or the introduction of Gaelic into local council branding will not indoctrinate children into speaking Gaelic, and I strongly suspect they will not be able to somehow push children into having a stronger Scottish identity than they otherwise would have. Such token gestures are utterly ineffectual at the aims that they are commonly seen to have. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for an actually effective policy tool, look at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/naidheachdan/39791058&#34;&gt;LEACAG project&lt;/a&gt; currently conducted by several Scottish universities working towards a reference grammar of Gaelic, with funding from Bòrd na Gàidhlig. Yet it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be the target of quite so much ire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do it then? It starts making sense if you look at it from the perspective of someone who &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; (or aspires to be) a speaker of a minority language or a non-standard variety. This is part of &lt;em&gt;prestige planning&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; measures that improve the perceived status of the minority language in the broader society and building democratic consent for further policy initiatives in that area. In this respect, involving the language in &amp;lsquo;official&amp;rsquo; uses such as signage or school teaching is a signal both to the minority language users themselves and to the society at large that minority and non-standard varieties are valued and respected, and not an irrelevance or an inconvenience to be dismissed. That is an important part of promoting the languages: speakers&amp;rsquo; attitudes to their language are partly, of course, personal, but also shaped to a large extent by the broader societal attitudes &amp;mdash; can we really always expect a person growing up in an environment for few signs of appreciation for the way they speak to have a positive attitude to it themselves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the problem with the often-made argument that Scotland-wide promotion of Gaelic is a waste of resources and funding should be concentrated in areas where it has a stronger claim to being a &amp;lsquo;regional&amp;rsquo; language (in practice, the Highlands &amp;mdash; not even perhaps all of it &amp;mdash; and Islands). But look at it from the perspective of a speaker or user of Gaelic. The intent of the current policy is to signal to them: &amp;lsquo;we value your language because of who you are &amp;mdash; one of us &amp;mdash; not because of where you live&amp;rsquo;. A &amp;lsquo;regional&amp;rsquo; policy says: &amp;lsquo;we&amp;rsquo;ll allow you weirdos to have your fun where there&amp;rsquo;s enough of you around, but please don&amp;rsquo;t come here inconveniencing us, the numerical majority who actually matter&amp;rsquo;. This is, in some ways, quite an insidious argument that makes a &amp;lsquo;democratic&amp;rsquo; appeal to the will of the majority against the interests of the minority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b08q3ln9&#34;&gt;this programme&lt;/a&gt; recently broadcast on BBC Alba. It&amp;rsquo;s on Gaelic in Aberdeen, showing how people with backgrounds from both the north-east and elsewhere keep the flag flying. All too often they hear people say &amp;lsquo;but it was never spoken here&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;it is being imposed&amp;rsquo;. And yet they have lived in the north-east for years, sometimes, as some of those interviewed, all their lives &amp;mdash; they are living proof that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; spoken. How do you tell such a person that their language is an imposition and an inconvenience? This sort of argument betrays a fundamental lack of empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true even when the argument is couched in the language of &amp;lsquo;I have nothing against it, but it should stand on its own two feet&amp;rsquo;. It is majority communities that have the luxury of being confident their culture and language aren&amp;rsquo;t going away, because they already have the support structure and the social scaffolding that ensures their culture and language remain in it. Building and maintaining these structures requires the kind of time and effort that very few people have to spare. Telling them to get on with it and stop being so damn visible shows the very same lack of empathy for these circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Parenthetically, the programme, quite well done and produced, is largely preaching to the choir when it&amp;rsquo;s on BBC Alba. An establishment really keen on promoting and imposing Gaelic would be showing it, probably in English, on prime-time BBC One. As noted, if the SNP or whoever are intent on pushing the language down everybody&amp;rsquo;s throats, they are doing a pretty rubbish job of it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a cultural, heritage argument to be made for the promotion of Gaelic &amp;mdash; one that can be legitimately appealed to if we want to decide on, say, the appropriate level of support for &amp;lsquo;immigrant&amp;rsquo; minority languages that have a &amp;lsquo;home base&amp;rsquo; outside of Scotland. But it is by no means a central plank of Gaelic-language policy. Minority language policy should focus on protecting the rights of speakers, and the rights of speakers are best served with a coherent programme of language planning. This includes prestige planning that aims to build consent for the protection of speakers&amp;rsquo; rights everywhere &amp;mdash; not just in designated areas where they are tolerated, but wherever they choose to live. People who think others shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have these rights are of course entitled to their opinion, but it would be great if they argued their case on that basis, not referring to an imagined nationalist plot or bungled heritage programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS- If you want to put yourself into the shoes of a minority language speaker Who Has Had Enough, I highly recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://storify.com/nwdls/on-being-a-rude-welsh-speaker&#34;&gt;this tweetstorm by @Madeley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Incidentally, some of the groundbreaking research in this area was conducted in the significantly Scots-speaking community of Buckie in the north-east of Scotland.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>phonology paper</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/phonology-paper/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 10:15:15 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/phonology-paper/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My paper &lt;em&gt;The phonologization of redundancy: Length and quality in Welsh vowels&lt;/em&gt; has appeared in the latest issue of &lt;em&gt;Phonology&lt;/em&gt;. See the published version &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0952675717000057&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or the author manuscript &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonetics Phonology Interface</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Papers</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/papers/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/papers/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Feature Theory</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/feature-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/feature-theory/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Contrast in Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/contrast-in-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/contrast-in-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification. I focus on the requirement for featural specifications to obey the Contrastivist Hypothesis, which denies that redundant features can be involved in phonological computation, in the context of a framework with emergent features. I suggest that the Contrastivist Hypothesis acts as a useful check for emergent-feature theories, whilst independent phonologization criteria provide contrastivist approaches with a more solid conceptual underpinning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also download the R notebook with the graphics and scripts from the paper and the data itself &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org//10.17605/OSF.IO/HD3BZ&#34;&gt;here at Open Science Framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>book</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/book/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 21:30:16 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/book/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My book &lt;em&gt;A substance-free framework for phonology: An analysis of the Breton dialect of Bothoa&lt;/em&gt; is now out with Edinburgh University Press. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-book/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Initial Consonant Mutations</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/initial-consonant-mutations/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/initial-consonant-mutations/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>obo</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/obo/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/obo/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My annotated bibliography of works related to Celtic initial consonant mutations has appeared in &lt;em&gt;Oxford Bibliographies Online&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/OBO/9780199772810-0146&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The table of contents is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/mutations-bibliography/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic mutations</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/mutations-bibliography/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/mutations-bibliography/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is an annotated and commented bibliography of works related to the initial consonant mutations of Celtic languages, available by subscription via &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/OBO/9780199772810-0146&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oxford Bibliographies Online&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Here is the table of contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General overviews

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Descriptions of individual languages

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Welsh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breton&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scottish Gaelic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manx&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ancient Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General bibliographic resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The phonology of mutations

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structuralist approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rule-based phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonlinear phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimality Theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The syntax of mutation

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The triggering of mutation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Direct object mutation in Welsh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mutations and morphology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mutations and interfaces

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mutations and other components of grammar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Language variation and change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mutation in &amp;lsquo;non-traditional&amp;rsquo; varieties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acquisition and psycholinguistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diachrony of mutations

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The origins of mutations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The historical development of mutations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typological comparison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the published version does not have an acknowledgements facility, I would like to thank here two anonymous reviewers, Peadar Ó Muircheartaigh, Máire Ní Chiosáin, and Christopher Lewin for valuable criticisms and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Variation in North Germanic preaspiration</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I consider the extent of cross-dialectal variation in the expression of laryngeal contrast within North Germanic, with a focus on (voiceless) preaspiration, and suggest that the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization across the North Germanic area have been significantly under-reported in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed by Pétur Helgason (2002), whilst preaspiration and sonorant devoicing in Insular Nordic have long been recognized by the scholarship, their distribution and behaviour in mainland varieties have been less well understood. Traditional descriptions designate preaspiration as characteristic of varieties in Jæren  and Gudbrandsdalen, with only passing references for other dialects such as that of Senja. In Sweden, preaspiration had been noted in Härjedalen and parts of Dalarna, as well as in dialects of the Baltic Sea islands (Gräsö, Åland and Åboland). However, as Pétur Helgason (2002) has shown, preaspiration is pervasive in other varieties, notably Central Standard Swedish. More recently preaspiration has also been studied in detail in Trøndelag Norwegian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Pétur Helgason (2002) makes an important distinction between ‘normative’ and ‘non-normative’ preaspiration, and highlights some differences in the patterning of preaspiration between dialects, the degree of internal variation in the behaviour of preaspiration so far appears relatively small. This is in striking contrast to the significant variability observed in Scottish Gaelic preaspiration despite the comparable, if not smaller, time depth. For now, it is not clear whether this lack of variation may simply be due to under-reporting in traditional auditory descriptions. Tengesdal (2015), in an instrumental study, has shown Oftedal’s (1947) claim that preaspiration of fortis stops is absent in south-east Jæren (Bjerkreim/Dalane) to likely have been incorrect. Preaspiration in ‘non-preaspirating’ areas is also evidenced in the Nordic Dialect Corpus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I present a comparative acoustic study of preaspiration in two regions of Norway: Jæren, traditionally considered a preaspirating area, and Northern Norway, where preaspiration has not been consistently described before. I show that preaspiration is in fact prevalent in (some) northern dialects, at rates not dissimilar to those in the west. However, there are also important differences in patterning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documenting the diversity of ways in which laryngeal contrast is realized even in closely related varieties is important for our understanding of the relationship between phonological specification and phonetic substance. I argue that the study of microvariation in laryngeal contrast supports a substance-free view of that relationship, in that even relatively abstract substance-bound approaches such as laryngeal realism  underpredict the fine-grained behaviour of features such as preaspiration. At the same time laryngeal realism and substance-free approaches both readily account for asymmetries in phonological behaviour between fortis and lenis stops. For instance, they predict that Western Norwegian voiceless lenes should be inert in assimilation despite being categorically voiceless phonetically, which I show to be correct in the case of [ʁ]-devoicing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
