<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Scottish Gaelic in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="http://anghyflawn.github.io//img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/scottish-gaelic/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 20:44:46 BST</updated>











<item>
<title>Right at the left edge: Initial consonant mutations in the world’s languages</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/rara-rarissima/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/rara-rarissima/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk was an attempt at documenting initial consonant mutations in as wide a range of languages as possible, together with an attempt at a typology. It formed the basis for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/rara/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; published in the proceedings of the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Brythonic ‘second lenition’ revisited</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I evaluate the arguments for two competing reconstructions regarding the laryngeal phonology of Proto-Brythonic. I defend the &amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo; interpretation which underplays the role of a &amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo; contrast and instead relies on two separate lenition processes (due to authors such as David Greene and Patrick Sims-Williams), against the &amp;lsquo;classical&amp;rsquo; one due to Kenneth Jackson and defended by John Koch and Graham Isaac, which emphasizes the rôle of aspiration in Proto-Brythonic &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; stops. In many respects this talk does not really represent my current thinking, but some of the arguments seem to me to retain some value.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Лексикализованные вершины в валлийском синтаксисе</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I attempt to extend Nigel Duffield&amp;rsquo;s idea of &amp;lsquo;lexicalized heads&amp;rsquo; playing a rôle in the triggering of initial mutations, originally proposed for Irish, to Welsh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>How good is the internal evidence for multiple-level phonological computation? A view from Russian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Relying in part on the analysis of palatalization offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I argue that Russian does not provide strong &lt;em&gt;phonology-internal&lt;/em&gt; evidence for level ordering, contra suggestions by authors such as Morris Halle and Jerzy Rubach. A more focused argument to the same effect is offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A bad case of excessive computation</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I use the analysis of palatalization in Modern Standard Russian offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to argue that these data do not provide a watertight argument for multilevel phonological computation, and that phonological analysis must be combined with a theory of ordering (such as Stratal OT) if the hypothesis of parallel computation is to be challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in the north of Italy</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk presents in detail the analysis of Friulian also given at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/&#34;&gt;18th mfm&lt;/a&gt; and later published &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Explaning licensing mismatches in Welsh</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I propose a new analysis of so-called &amp;lsquo;vowel mutation&amp;rsquo; in Welsh, whereby final syllables (both stressed and unstressed) only allow a reduced inventory (by disallowing [ə]). I argue that these final syllables are specified with something like a suprasegmental feature that triggers a feature co-occurrence effect, and that there is no need for recourse to a mechanism of metrical prominence akin to that borne by stressed syllables (as previously suggested in the literature). (A fuller version of the analysis can be found in the thesis.) The argument also stresses the need for a distinction between metrical headship and prominence features such as stress (see also &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I consider the nature of the so-called &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic and argue that the contrast is one of metrical structure rather than lexical tone, at least diachronically, and probably also synchronically. This means that they can be reconstructed with an internal origin, and no recourse to contact with North Germanic is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to account for their appearance. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; has the analysis in detail, and the historical argument is expounded in some detail in later talks &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/&#34;&gt;Toronto presentation&lt;/a&gt; and to a certain extent my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/&#34;&gt;talk from the 6th CLC&lt;/a&gt;). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration. I argue that the tight connection between phonological contrast and phonetic representation proposed by laryngeal realism isn&amp;rsquo;t correct in any case, so this mismatch is not a major problem for the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Deconstructing mutation in Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer the analysis of Breton initial mutations found in my thesis. I argue that there is no such thing as a unified &amp;lsquo;mutation&amp;rsquo; mechanism: instead, this labels covers a variety of processes with different places in the overall grammar. The article-length version of the argument is &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-mutation/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A unified account of the behaviour of high vowels in Bothoa Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer an analysis of gliding in Bothoa Breton, as presented in the thesis. I argue that high vowels (especially [i]) either become glides or coalesce with a preceding consonant, in order to avoid hiatus. However, this pattern is disrupted if the high vowel becomes a nucleus at an earlier stage in the cyclic derivation. This provides an argument for stratal models of phonology-morphology interactions, and a strong argument &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; Output-Output Correspondence, because some of the exceptional non-gliding cases cannot be explained by reference to a free-standing form with transparent non-gliding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here, I propose an analysis of the interacting between final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian (and other related varieties of northern Italy). Historically, stressed vowels lengthen before voiced obstruents, but this is opacified by final devoicing. I capitalize on phonetic studies showing final devoicing in the language to be incomplete and argue that the process is not in fact opaque: devoicing does not involve neutralization but instead the creation of a third, laryngealy unspecified class of obstruents. I also observe that the distribution of moraicity in Friulian presents a challenge to accepted theories of weight assignment, and propose an analysis that relies on language-specific featural representations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>In defence of Richness of the Base</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I briefly present the analysis of mora assignment to consonants in South Welsh. The pattern can be analysed by appeal to the form of the inputs (i.e. with a massive number of accidental gaps, which is undesirable), or by positing a constraint schema with undesirable consequences for factorial typology. I suggest that the latter solution is preferable theoretically, although it may be premature to choose it for that reason alone.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>









<item>
<title>The phonological endgame</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I present an analysis of Welsh &amp;lsquo;svarabhakti&amp;rsquo;, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (&lt;em&gt;pwdr&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]). This pattern is said to coexist with a pattern of deleting consonants in such clusters in polysyllables (&lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has been argued that the two differing outcomes can be reconciled by appeal to a single constraint on the form of feet. I show that this analysis is not tenable for South Welsh, and propose that deletion (as in &lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt;) is not part of the phonological grammar (at least in South Welsh).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Initial consonant mutation and information flow in Mende</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/ocp5/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/ocp5/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I reanalyse the pattern of initial consonant mutation in Mende by arguing that the so-called &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade, usually assumed to be the derive one, is the default case morphosyntactically, and thus that the consonant mutation mechanism must derive the &amp;lsquo;strong&amp;rsquo; rather than the &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade. This is problematic for autosegmental, or probably any purely phonological, accounts of mutation, since the relationship between the weak and strong grades is one-to-many, so I suggest the choice between the two grades is made outside of phonology, with direct reference to the morphosyntax.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Liquids and spirants</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here, I consider some cases of fricatives phonologically patterning with liquids, and argue that this phenomenon is merely the extension of the well-known cross-linguistic diversity in the representation of the former. I interpret this as providing support for substance-free representations with a non-trivial phonology-phonetics mapping. I provide a concrete analysis of initial mutations involving sonorants in Scottish Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Liquids and spirants</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here, I consider some cases of fricatives phonologically patterning with liquids, and argue that this phenomenon is merely the extension of the well-known cross-linguistic diversity in the representation of the former. I interpret this as providing support for substance-free representations with a non-trivial phonology-phonetics mapping. I provide a concrete analysis of initial mutations involving sonorants in Scottish Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>All that glistens is not gold</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I argue that purely phonological (e.g. autosegmental) approaches to initial consonant mutations in languages such as Fula and Irish are insufficient to account for the facts fully. In many ways this does not represent my current thinking on these matters, as can be established by looking, for instance, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-mutation/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Too many levels, too few solutions</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/16mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/16mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk is largely of historic interest, superseded in particular by &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt;, also at the mfm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Fonetikk versus fonologi</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Dette er det fyrste føredraget i prosjektet om russisk vokalreduksjon. Sluttversjonen kan ein finne i &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/&#34;&gt;denne artikkelen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>







<item>
<title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>













<item>
<title>Лексикализованные вершины в валлийском синтаксисе</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I attempt to extend Nigel Duffield&amp;rsquo;s idea of &amp;lsquo;lexicalized heads&amp;rsquo; playing a rôle in the triggering of initial mutations, originally proposed for Irish, to Welsh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Glottal stop insertion in Scottish Gaelic and contrastive syllabification</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Gaelic dialects, mostly in Argyll, show a process of glottal stop epenthesis in stressed light syllables. This has been analysed as a stress-to-weight effect, and I review the evidence to show that this analysis is likely correct, and also that glottal stop insertion is a live phonological process rather than a lexicalized artefact of history. If this is correct, Argyll Gaelic shows an example of lexical storage of syllable structure, sometimes argued to be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge&lt;/em&gt; talk&lt;/a&gt; to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving &lt;em&gt;segments&lt;/em&gt;, but instead &lt;em&gt;features&lt;/em&gt; attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The [ATR]/laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer a preliminary analysis of the phenomenon of &lt;em&gt;calediad&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;lsquo;provection&amp;rsquo;) in South-Eastern Welsh, whereby &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (lenis) stops become &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; after a stressed vowel. I argue that since vowels before lenis stops are generally long &amp;mdash; and, given the phonology of South Welsh &amp;mdash; tense, provection is an example of vowel-consonant interaction, where the same feature is used for the tense/lax contrast in vowels and laryngeal contrast in consonants. I interpret this as supporting emergent feature theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory (in Russian)</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/phonological-theory-hse/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/phonological-theory-hse/</guid>
<description>

&lt;p&gt;Приглашенный мини-курс «Фонологическая теория», Москва, ГУ-ВШЭ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;В настоящем курсе рассматриваются важнейшие вопросы фонологической теории в ее генеративном варианте. Курс состоит из пяти лекций:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;лекция-1-архитектура-фонологической-теории:c045439eba0f66e41cba4f58ececd1bb&#34;&gt;Лекция 1: Архитектура фонологической теории&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/phon-theory-hse/hse-handout-01.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;материалы&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Тема первой лекции — устройство фонологической теории, место фонологии в теории грамматики и мотивация динамического (генеративного) подхода. В рамках современной теории фонологический модуль представляется как механизм, соотносящий фонологические объекты (множества сегментов, признаков, граничных символов и т.п.), предоставленные словарем, с другими фонологическими объектами, которые описываются в терминах того же алфавита, что и «входные данные», и интерпретируются фонетическим компонентом. В этой лекции рассматриваются мотивация такого подхода, которая связана в первую очередь с его успехом в описании (мор)фонологических чередований, и его преимущества перед одноуровневым описанием, характерным для традиционных фонематических теорий.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;лекция-2-морфонологические-чередования-и-порядок-правил:c045439eba0f66e41cba4f58ececd1bb&#34;&gt;Лекция 2: Морфонологические чередования и порядок правил&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/phon-theory-hse/hse-handout-02.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;материалы&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Во второй лекции мы рассмотрим некоторые типы чередований, которые могут быть изящно описаны в рамках многоуровневой теории. Особое внимание будет уделено «неавтоматическим» чередованиям, условия для которых плохо описываются без привлечения данных о промежуточных представлениях (т.е. о формах соответствующих слов, неидентичных их поверхностным представлениям). Будет рассмотрена типология порядка правил (питающий, блокирующий, контрпитающий и контрблокирующий порядки) и проблема непрозрачности.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;лекция-3-проблема-абстрактности-вопрос-о-естественности-взаимодействие-фонологии-и-морфологии:c045439eba0f66e41cba4f58ececd1bb&#34;&gt;Лекция 3: Проблема абстрактности, вопрос о «естественности», взаимодействие фонологии и морфологии&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/phon-theory-hse/hse-handout-03.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;материалы&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Многоуровневый подход в фонологии предполагает возможность существования достаточно абстрактных представлений на глубинных уровнях, которые сводятся к более «реалистичным» с помощью сложных систем фонологических правил. Тема третьей лекции — различные подходы к разрешению противоречия между (достаточно мощными) формальными возможностями теории и типологически наблюдаемым преобладанием систем, традиционно называемых «естественными» или «немаркированными». Мы рассмотрим несколько возможных ограничений на глубину дериваций, типы правил и порядок их применения (естественная фонология, условие обязательности чередования, строгая цикличность); особое внимание будет уделено лексической фонологии — наиболее разработанной морфонологической концепции.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;лекция-4-теория-представлений:c045439eba0f66e41cba4f58ececd1bb&#34;&gt;Лекция 4: Теория представлений&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/phon-theory-hse/hse-handout-04.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;материалы&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Тема четвертой лекции — различные подходы к уточнению признаковой теории, в первую очередь вопрос о привативности фонологических признаков, признаковой геометрии и неполной спецификации. Как известно, еще Трубецкой в «Основах фонологии» предлагал различать эквиполентные (и градуальные) оппозиции, предполагающие возможность двух (или более) значений признака, и привативные, для которых существенно лишь наличие либо отсутствие признака. Мы рассмотрим типологические данные, говорящие в пользу привативности по крайней мере некоторых признаков, и обсудим вопрос о том, может ли фонологическая теория вовсе обойтись без бинарных признаков. Существование привативных признаков также предполагает возможность отсутствия фонологической спецификации по некоторым параметрам: мы рассмотрим несколько теоретических подходов к такой неполной спецификации. Наконец, теория признаковой геометрии постулирует существование древовидной структуры составляющих «внутри» сегмента: в этой лекции мы обсудим некоторые преимущества такого подхода.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;лекция-5-ограничения-в-фонологии-теория-оптимальности:c045439eba0f66e41cba4f58ececd1bb&#34;&gt;Лекция 5: Ограничения в фонологии, теория оптимальности&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/phon-theory-hse/hse-handout-05.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;материалы&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Традиционную фонологическую теорию можно назвать «ориентированной на входные данные»: действие правил определяется состоянием системы до их запуска. Одно из следствий такого подхода: невозможность адекватного описания так называемых «заговоров», когда некая поверхностная структура избегается за счет применения формально не связанных друг с другом правил. В этой лекции мы обсудим вопрос о необходимости дополнить правила ограничениями, регулирующими применение правил, и недостатки такого гибридного подхода. В рамках лекции также будет дано введение в теорию оптимальности — подход, полностью отказывающийся от правил и оперирующий одними лишь ограничениями.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Getting ESS and AUCTeX to play nicely with knitr</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2014/getting-ess-and-auctex-to-play-nicely-with-knitr/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2014/getting-ess-and-auctex-to-play-nicely-with-knitr/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Although my job title is &amp;lsquo;Lecturer in Theoretical Phonology&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.ed.ac.uk/portal/en/persons/pavel-iosad(976edf38-f950-4179-a032-a6cea4b31b3b.html&#34;&gt;no, really&lt;/a&gt;), I&amp;rsquo;ve been getting into more empirical work. I went on a data collection trip to South Wales in February to work with Welsh, and only early this week we had two great days collecting Gaelic data in North Argyll – not an area &lt;em&gt;readily&lt;/em&gt; associated with Gaelic these days, but in fact we found quite a few very good speakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this post isn&amp;rsquo;t about that. Having collected the data and processed some of it, I have also been getting to grips with &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; doing statistical analysis (as opposed to working through textbooks), which these days inevitably means &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-project.org.&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m giving a couple of talks in Wales next week (&lt;a href=&#34;http://privatewww.essex.ac.uk/~wss/wss-21.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://amrywiaeth.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) with some of the results, so the time had come for me to think about getting my data into my presentations (and eventually papers). Being a LaTeX user, after some poking about I settled on &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name/knitr&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt; as the way to get stuff out of R and into LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the R wizards I know use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rstudio.com&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;, which is a very good IDE for R, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t come close to the power of Emacs with AUCTeX for LaTeX writing. So far I have found &lt;a href=&#34;http://ess.r-studio.org&#34;&gt;ESS&lt;/a&gt; to be perfectly adequare for my R needs. ESS also supports knitting &lt;code&gt;.Rnw&lt;/code&gt; files out of the box via &lt;code&gt;M-n r&lt;/code&gt;. Its default weaving engine, however, is Sweave. After some poking about, here&amp;rsquo;s how to get ESS and AUCTeX to play nicely with knitr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two components. One is to make knitr the default engine when tangling outside AUCTeX. This is easily achieved via &lt;code&gt;(setq ess-swv-processor &#39;knitr)&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;/code&gt;, but this only allows you to use knitr as the default when you tangle via &lt;code&gt;M-n T&lt;/code&gt;. What this doesn&amp;rsquo;t automate is running LaTeX on the product of the knitting: you have to switch to the &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file manually and run stuff from there, but this runs the risk of making edits to the &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file instead of the &lt;code&gt;.Rnw&lt;/code&gt;. ESS also has a &lt;code&gt;latex&lt;/code&gt; tangling option (&lt;code&gt;M-n l&lt;/code&gt;), but this just runs &lt;code&gt;latex&lt;/code&gt; from the shell, without any of the AUCTeX customizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ESS also has the option to plug into AUCTeX, making relevant commands available to the user via &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt;. This is much handier, but unfortunately the functions which add these commands are hardcoded to use Sweave from the shell rather than &lt;code&gt;ess-swv-run-in-R&lt;/code&gt;, which is sensitive to the value of &lt;code&gt;ess-swv-processor&lt;/code&gt;. So here&amp;rsquo;s what you need in order to get knitr to run into AUCTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-elisp&#34;&gt;;; somewhere after (require &#39;ess-site)
(setq ess-swv-plug-into-AUCTeX-p t)

(defun ess-swv-add-TeX-commands ()
  &amp;quot;Add commands to AUCTeX&#39;s \\[TeX-command-list].&amp;quot;
  (unless (and (featurep &#39;tex-site) (featurep &#39;tex))
    (error &amp;quot;AUCTeX does not seem to be loaded&amp;quot;))
  (add-to-list &#39;TeX-command-list
               &#39;(&amp;quot;Knit&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Rscript -e \&amp;quot;library(knitr); knit(&#39;%t&#39;)\&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
                 TeX-run-command nil (latex-mode) :help
                 &amp;quot;Run Knitr&amp;quot;) t)
  (add-to-list &#39;TeX-command-list
               &#39;(&amp;quot;LaTeXKnit&amp;quot; &amp;quot;%l %(mode) %s&amp;quot;
                 TeX-run-TeX nil (latex-mode) :help
                 &amp;quot;Run LaTeX after Knit&amp;quot;) t)
  (setq TeX-command-default &amp;quot;Knit&amp;quot;)
  (mapc (lambda (suffix)
          (add-to-list &#39;TeX-file-extensions suffix))
        &#39;(&amp;quot;nw&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Snw&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Rnw&amp;quot;)))

(defun ess-swv-remove-TeX-commands (x)
  &amp;quot;Helper function: check if car of X is one of the Knitr strings&amp;quot;
  (let ((swv-cmds &#39;(&amp;quot;Knit&amp;quot; &amp;quot;LaTeXKnit&amp;quot;)))
    (unless (member (car x) swv-cmds) x)))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just little changes to the original functions defined in &lt;code&gt;ess-swv.el&lt;/code&gt;. Now you can, via &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt;, access &lt;code&gt;Knit&lt;/code&gt; (which just produces the &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file) and &lt;code&gt;LaTeXKnit&lt;/code&gt;, which runs the LaTeX process as customized by AUCTeX (e.g. to use XeTeX or whatever other options you normally use) on the output, without you having to go the &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file. Which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Emacs: give a DOI, get a BibTeX entry</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2014/emacs-give-a-doi-get-a-bibtex-entry/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2014/emacs-give-a-doi-get-a-bibtex-entry/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;One of my enduring frustrations with the various academic publishing platforms (CJO, ScienceDirect, JSTOR and their ilk) is the wildly inconsistent way in which they export BibTeX entries for articles. Sometimes they put them right on the browser page for easy copy-and-paste; sometimes it comes up after a few clicks in a new window; sometimes you end up downloading a file with an impossibly long or counterintuitive name, or called something like &lt;code&gt;science.bib&lt;/code&gt; (which Chrome tends to turn into &lt;code&gt;science (14).bib&lt;/code&gt; as they accumulate). Since I really only need the BibTeX entry once to get into my master &lt;code&gt;.bib&lt;/code&gt; file, that is a waste of time and resources. So if you&amp;rsquo;re using Emacs, here&amp;rsquo;s a simple function which might be helpful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-elisp&#34;&gt;(defun get-bibtex-from-doi (doi)
 &amp;quot;Get a BibTeX entry from the DOI&amp;quot;
 (interactive &amp;quot;MDOI: &amp;quot;)
 (let ((url-mime-accept-string &amp;quot;text/bibliography;style=bibtex&amp;quot;))
   (with-current-buffer 
     (url-retrieve-synchronously 
       (format &amp;quot;http://dx.doi.org/%s&amp;quot; 
       	(replace-regexp-in-string &amp;quot;http://dx.doi.org/&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&amp;quot; doi)))
     (switch-to-buffer (current-buffer))
     (goto-char (point-max))
     (setq bibtex-entry 
     	  (buffer-substring 
          	(string-match &amp;quot;@&amp;quot; (buffer-string))
              (point)))
     (kill-buffer (current-buffer))))
 (insert (decode-coding-string bibtex-entry &#39;utf-8))
 (bibtex-fill-entry))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will ask you for the DOI (you can keep the &lt;code&gt;http://dx.doi.org/&lt;/code&gt; bit that you get if you do &amp;lsquo;Copy Link Address&amp;rsquo; from the browser), pull the BibTeX entry via the DOI API, and insert it at point. (I&amp;rsquo;m assuming the buffer is in &lt;code&gt;bibtex-mode&lt;/code&gt; already, since it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really make sense for it not to be.) Put this in your &lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;/code&gt; and you can now do &lt;code&gt;M-x get-bibtex-from-doi&lt;/code&gt;, or bind it to a keychord of your choice. The entry might still need fiddling with (e.g. to fix the citekey in line with your scheme, or to remove the Unicode characters if need be), but hopefully this might be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
