<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scottish Gaelic on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/scottish-gaelic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Scottish Gaelic on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/scottish-gaelic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dialect variation in Scottish Gaelic nominal morphology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents a dialectometric analysis of Scottish Gaelic morphology, with a focus on the noun phrase, using previously unpublished data from the Linguistic Survey of Scotland. Fifty-five morphological features were extracted across 201 survey points, and the data subjected to a variety of analyses, including cluster analysis, regression, and correlation analysis. We establish that the Gaelic noun system shows robust diatopic (i. e. geographical) variation; this challenges previous assertions in the literature, which describe Gaelic morphosyntax as geographically uniform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The life cycle of preaspiration in the Gaelic languages</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/frlsu-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/frlsu-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>This paper is a written-up version of my presentation at the 2018 conference of the Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster.
In this paper I propose (yet another) reappraisal of the arguments regarding the relationship between Norse and Gaelic in the North Atlantic world, focusing on the development of preaspiration. There is significant controversy in the literature as to whether this feature, along with others such as tonal accent, represents Norse influence on Gaelic (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonology of Gaelic tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</guid>
      <description>It is well known that many varieties of Gaelic show an opposition between two classes of words that is implemented by suprasegmental means such as pitch and glottalization. These phenomena have been compared to the ‘tonal accents’ of the North and West Germanic languages (notably by Ternes 1980, 2006), and a number of analyses have been proposed in the theoretical linguis- tics literature. In this paper, I summarize the patterns found across traditional varieties of Scottish Gaelic, and focus on the (limited number of) synchronic alternations that involve accent-related phenomena.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A metrical analysis of Scottish Gaelic tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/rnag/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/rnag/</guid>
      <description>I provide a new analysis of the ‘tonal accent’ opposition in Gaelic, conceptualizing it as involving lexically specified metrical — in particular foot — structure. As discussed among others by Ternes (1980, 2006), many Gaelic varieties use suprasegmental features such as pitch (e.g. Lewis, Wester Ross) or glottalization (e.g. Jura, Colonsay) to make two kinds of distinctions: disyllabic hiatus vs. heavy syllables (àth vs. atha); and disyllabic vs. svarabhakti words (balg vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The influence of Norse on Scottish Gaelic, 85 years on</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/frlsu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/frlsu/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose (yet another) reappraisal of the arguments regarding the relationship between Norse and Gaelic in the North Atlantic world, focusing on the development of preaspiration. There is significant controversy in the literature as to whether this feature, along with others such as tonal accent, represents Norse influence on Gaelic (e.g. Marstrander 1932; Borgstrøm 1974; Gunnar Ólafur Hansson 2001), an independent development in Gaelic (e.g. Ó Baoill 1980; Ó Murchú 1985; Ó Maolalaigh 2010), or even Gaelic influence on Norse (McKenna 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European phonological area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</guid>
      <description>This is a local colloquium talk with some preliminary ideas on the topic. If you have any kind of feedback, do please get in touch!
I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphology and dialectology: A quantitative approach</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</guid>
      <description>We present a study of Gaelic dialectal variation based on the unpublished, morphological section of the Linguistic Survey of Scotland (Gaelic). Our findings indicate that a quantitative (dialectometric) approach can yield important insights into the range of internal variation in Gaelic and elucidate certain issues of language structure. Here, we focus on two questions:
 What patterns of spatial variation are observed in the morphological data? How are different morphological features in the dialects correlated?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels: phonology and/or coarticulation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents much the same material as our presentation at OCP13</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel backness and palatalization in Irish and Scottish Gaelic: A study in rule scattering</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</guid>
      <description>We present the results of an acoustic study of the interaction of consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels. Previous descriptions of Irish (but usually not of Scottish Gaelic) often describe the distribution of front vs. back nonlow vowels as predictable (allophonic). This makes Irish a potential example of a vertical vowel system. However, the sources are mostly impressionistic, and also tend to underplay the extent of variation within and across lexical items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic and its contribution to prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports the preliminary results of an acoustic study of preaspiration in the Gaelic of North Argyll. Existing descriptions identify this area as reflecting Old Irish and Old Norse &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; geminates as [xp xt xk] clusters (&amp;lsquo;pre-affricates&amp;rsquo;), but, to our knowledge, no targeted acoustic study of these varieties had been performed to date. Our results confirm that the preaspiration found in other varieties corresponds to dorsal (velar or uvular) frication in North Argyll, rather than other conceivable interpretations of the impressionistic descriptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspiration and tonal accents as Northern Gaelic features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</guid>
      <description>I argue that the origin of both pitch accents and preaspiration in Gaelic is best understood in the context of a &amp;lsquo;Northern Gaelic&amp;rsquo; area covering Ulster and Scotland, as opposed to Connacht and Munster. Within this area, both preaspiration and pitch accents show the classic pattern of peripheral archaisms, with Lewis and West Ulster as remnant areas and Argyll as the most innovative zone. This suggests that the stronger Norse presence in the Hebrides does not correlate with a denser distribution of potential contact features, and thus the developments in both cases need not have been triggered by contact &amp;mdash; even though a reinforcing role for contact is very difficult (and probably undesirable) to exclude.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An echoing tone</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the Nordic Research Network 2015 conference at the University of Edinburgh.
In this talk, I consider the origins of pitch accents in North Germanic and in Scottish Gaelic. I argue that in both cases the more plausible hypothesis involves the realization of an identical tonal melody over different temporal domains, particularly by the mechanism of peak delay. This is not a new idea, but I support it by a consideration of the interaction of tone and apocope in Zealand Danish and in Central Scandinavian.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers the origin of &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic with a view to evaluating the hypothesis that this feature was borrowed from North Germanic varieties spoken by Norse settlers in medieval Scotland. It is shown that the &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; system in Gaelic is tightly bound with metrical structure (more precisely syllable count), certainly diachronically, and probably (at least in some varieties) synchronically. Gaelic &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; is argued to be a plausible internal development, parallel to similar phenomena in other branches of Celtic (specifically in Breton), as well as in Germanic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge talk to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving segments, but instead features attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glottal stop insertion in Scottish Gaelic and contrastive syllabification</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</guid>
      <description>Gaelic dialects, mostly in Argyll, show a process of glottal stop epenthesis in stressed light syllables. This has been analysed as a stress-to-weight effect, and I review the evidence to show that this analysis is likely correct, and also that glottal stop insertion is a live phonological process rather than a lexicalized artefact of history. If this is correct, Argyll Gaelic shows an example of lexical storage of syllable structure, sometimes argued to be impossible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</guid>
      <description>I consider the nature of the so-called &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic and argue that the contrast is one of metrical structure rather than lexical tone, at least diachronically, and probably also synchronically. This means that they can be reconstructed with an internal origin, and no recourse to contact with North Germanic is necessary to account for their appearance. The paper has the analysis in detail, and the historical argument is expounded in some detail in later talks here and here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>