<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Initial consonant mutations on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/initial-consonant-mutations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Initial consonant mutations on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/initial-consonant-mutations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Celtic mutations</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/mutations-bibliography/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/mutations-bibliography/</guid>
      <description>This is an annotated and commented bibliography of works related to the initial consonant mutations of Celtic languages, available by subscription via Oxford Bibliographies Online. Here is the table of contents:
 Introduction General overviews 3. Descriptions of individual languages 4. Welsh 4. Breton 4. Cornish 4. Irish 4. Scottish Gaelic 4. Manx 4. Ancient Celtic languages General bibliographic resources The phonology of mutations 6. Structuralist approaches 7. Rule-based phonology 8.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonology and morphosyntax of Breton mutation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</guid>
      <description>I analyse of initial consonant mutation in a Breton dialect, with a focus on establishing the division of labour between phonology and morphology in the triggering of mutation and its phonological expression. I argue that different types of mutation have different status in the grammar: some are purely phonological, others involve subsegmental morphemes with a clear morphosyntactic rationale, and for some the phonological aspects are clear but the morphosyntactic motivation remains obscure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Right at the left edge</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/rara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/rara/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I offer an overview of systems of initial consonant mutations found in the world&amp;rsquo;s languages and attempt to propose a preliminary typology. Many of these phenomena can probably be subsumed under a general theory of nonconcatenative morphology and phonology, but in some cases (notably some of the Celtic ones) the mutations&#39; place in the grammar is less clear. For another, more detailed take on this architectural issue in the specific case of Breton, see also this later paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Too many levels, too few solutions</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/16mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/16mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk is largely of historic interest, superseded in particular by this talk, also at the mfm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All that glistens is not gold</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I argue that purely phonological (e.g. autosegmental) approaches to initial consonant mutations in languages such as Fula and Irish are insufficient to account for the facts fully. In many ways this does not represent my current thinking on these matters, as can be established by looking, for instance, at this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial consonant mutation and information flow in Mende</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/ocp5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/ocp5/</guid>
      <description>I reanalyse the pattern of initial consonant mutation in Mende by arguing that the so-called &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade, usually assumed to be the derive one, is the default case morphosyntactically, and thus that the consonant mutation mechanism must derive the &amp;lsquo;strong&amp;rsquo; rather than the &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade. This is problematic for autosegmental, or probably any purely phonological, accounts of mutation, since the relationship between the weak and strong grades is one-to-many, so I suggest the choice between the two grades is made outside of phonology, with direct reference to the morphosyntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Лексикализованные вершины в валлийском синтаксисе</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I attempt to extend Nigel Duffield&amp;rsquo;s idea of &amp;lsquo;lexicalized heads&amp;rsquo; playing a rôle in the triggering of initial mutations, originally proposed for Irish, to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Right at the left edge: Initial consonant mutations in the world’s languages</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/rara-rarissima/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/rara-rarissima/</guid>
      <description>This talk was an attempt at documenting initial consonant mutations in as wide a range of languages as possible, together with an attempt at a typology. It formed the basis for the paper published in the proceedings of the conference.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
