<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prosody on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/prosody/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Prosody on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/prosody/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A metrical analysis of Scottish Gaelic tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/rnag/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/rnag/</guid>
      <description>I provide a new analysis of the ‘tonal accent’ opposition in Gaelic, conceptualizing it as involving lexically specified metrical — in particular foot — structure. As discussed among others by Ternes (1980, 2006), many Gaelic varieties use suprasegmental features such as pitch (e.g. Lewis, Wester Ross) or glottalization (e.g. Jura, Colonsay) to make two kinds of distinctions: disyllabic hiatus vs. heavy syllables (àth vs. atha); and disyllabic vs. svarabhakti words (balg vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspiration and tonal accents as Northern Gaelic features</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</guid>
      <description>I argue that the origin of both pitch accents and preaspiration in Gaelic is best understood in the context of a &amp;lsquo;Northern Gaelic&amp;rsquo; area covering Ulster and Scotland, as opposed to Connacht and Munster. Within this area, both preaspiration and pitch accents show the classic pattern of peripheral archaisms, with Lewis and West Ulster as remnant areas and Argyll as the most innovative zone. This suggests that the stronger Norse presence in the Hebrides does not correlate with a denser distribution of potential contact features, and thus the developments in both cases need not have been triggered by contact &amp;mdash; even though a reinforcing role for contact is very difficult (and probably undesirable) to exclude.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An echoing tone</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the Nordic Research Network 2015 conference at the University of Edinburgh.
In this talk, I consider the origins of pitch accents in North Germanic and in Scottish Gaelic. I argue that in both cases the more plausible hypothesis involves the realization of an identical tonal melody over different temporal domains, particularly by the mechanism of peak delay. This is not a new idea, but I support it by a consideration of the interaction of tone and apocope in Zealand Danish and in Central Scandinavian.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers the origin of &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic with a view to evaluating the hypothesis that this feature was borrowed from North Germanic varieties spoken by Norse settlers in medieval Scotland. It is shown that the &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; system in Gaelic is tightly bound with metrical structure (more precisely syllable count), certainly diachronically, and probably (at least in some varieties) synchronically. Gaelic &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; is argued to be a plausible internal development, parallel to similar phenomena in other branches of Celtic (specifically in Breton), as well as in Germanic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress and consonant length in Welsh revisited</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</guid>
      <description>I</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ареальные схождения в фонологии языков Северной Европы</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</guid>
      <description>This is the Russian-language version of this talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nordeuropäische Lautgeographie revisited</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</guid>
      <description>This presents some work in progress on common phonological features in Northern Europe (preaspiration, pitch accents, sonorant pre-occlusion). Email me if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the handout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Head-dependent asymmetries in Munster Irish prosody</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose an analysis of stress in Munster Irish which builds on two important premises. First, I argue for a distinction between the notion &amp;lsquo;head of a constituent&amp;rsquo; and the notion of &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo;: these are separate entities, and the typologically frequent isomorphic distribution of the two is just one possible outcome of the phonological computation. Second, I propose to employ a particular family of constraints requiring head-dependent asymmetries (Dresher and van der Hulst 1998) to account for the mismatch between the placement of foot heads and stress in Munster Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge talk to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving segments, but instead features attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glottal stop insertion in Scottish Gaelic and contrastive syllabification</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</guid>
      <description>Gaelic dialects, mostly in Argyll, show a process of glottal stop epenthesis in stressed light syllables. This has been analysed as a stress-to-weight effect, and I review the evidence to show that this analysis is likely correct, and also that glottal stop insertion is a live phonological process rather than a lexicalized artefact of history. If this is correct, Argyll Gaelic shows an example of lexical storage of syllable structure, sometimes argued to be impossible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</guid>
      <description>I consider the nature of the so-called &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic and argue that the contrast is one of metrical structure rather than lexical tone, at least diachronically, and probably also synchronically. This means that they can be reconstructed with an internal origin, and no recourse to contact with North Germanic is necessary to account for their appearance. The paper has the analysis in detail, and the historical argument is expounded in some detail in later talks here and here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaning licensing mismatches in Welsh</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I propose a new analysis of so-called &amp;lsquo;vowel mutation&amp;rsquo; in Welsh, whereby final syllables (both stressed and unstressed) only allow a reduced inventory (by disallowing [ə]). I argue that these final syllables are specified with something like a suprasegmental feature that triggers a feature co-occurrence effect, and that there is no need for recourse to a mechanism of metrical prominence akin to that borne by stressed syllables (as previously suggested in the literature).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure versus prominence</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the stress system of Munster Irish, which evinces a disruption of normal directionality only in words with two initial heavy syllables. The analysis relies on recursion of subsyllable constituents and on a formal distinction between &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;head status&amp;rsquo;. The full version of the analysis can be found in this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>