<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Substance-free phonology on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/substance-free-phonology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Substance-free phonology on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/substance-free-phonology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>There is no problem of /v/ in Russian phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</guid>
      <description>The dual behaviour of /v/ has been a notorious crux in Russian phonology since at least Jakobson (1956). The basic problem is that /v/ fails to trigger voicing assimilation, like sonorants, but undergoes both assimilation to following obstruents and final devoicing, like obstruents.
The commonest solution in the literature is representational: [v] is treated as a sonorant, either an underlying /w/ (Lightner 1972, Hayes 1984, Kiparsky 1985) or some labial non-glide (Coats &amp;amp; Harshenin 1971, Padgett 2002).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microvariation in laryngeal realism</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I consider the range of microvariation in the expression of laryngeal contrast, focusing on (voiceless) preaspiration in North Germanic. On the basis of an acoustic study, I suggest that both the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization have been under-reported in existing descriptions. This, in turn, has important consequences for our understanding of the phonology of laryngeal contrast. Specifically, I argue that the observed variation in laryngeal phenomena is incompatible with a version of &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; that produces inferences about phonological specifications on the basis of phonetic implementation; instead, I advocate a more abstract approach that gives primacy to phonological behaviour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
      <description>‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation in North Germanic preaspiration</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</guid>
      <description>I consider the extent of cross-dialectal variation in the expression of laryngeal contrast within North Germanic, with a focus on (voiceless) preaspiration, and suggest that the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization across the North Germanic area have been significantly under-reported in the past.
As discussed by Pétur Helgason (2002), whilst preaspiration and sonorant devoicing in Insular Nordic have long been recognized by the scholarship, their distribution and behaviour in mainland varieties have been less well understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A substance-free framework for phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-book/</guid>
      <description>The book is a revised and updated version of parts of my PhD thesis. From the publisher&amp;rsquo;s blurb:
 What is the relationship between phonetics and phonology? Are phonological features innate and universal, and do they have fixed phonetic correlates? These questions have recently received renewed prominence in theoretical debates, and this book explores them from a modular, substance-free perspective.
This in-depth analysis of Breton serves not only to introduce previously underused data into the theoretical landscape but also to demonstrate the viability of a modular framework for phonology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ATR/Laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</guid>
      <description>I consider an unusual sound change and synchronic alternation in south-eastern dialects of Welsh, traditionally referred to as ‘provection’ (Welsh calediad). This phenomenon involves the ‘devoicing’ of stops following stressed vowels. I suggest that it may be the result of a typologically rare sort of vowel-consonant featural interaction, where ‘devoicing’ is triggered by tense vowels. This is unexpected typologically, since tongue root advancement — often a correlate of ‘tense’ vowel quality — is more frequently associated with voicing rather than devoicing in obstruents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Length and tenseness across Welsh dialects</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the First Conference on Linguistic Diversity in Wales at the National Library of Wales in Aberystwyth.
This talk is about the interaction of vowel quantity and quality in different dialects of Welsh. According to existing descriptions, Welsh is a bit like English in that its short vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; in quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ ə]) and its long vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; ([iː uː eː oː]).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonologization of redundant contrasts and the Contrastivist Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</guid>
      <description>I consider two cases of predictable distributions of phonological categories: &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; long vowels in South-West Welsh and the two varieties of the FACE vowel in Ulster English. Their predictable (&amp;lsquo;non-phonemic&amp;rsquo;) distribution is a challenge to the Contrastivist Hypothesis, but I argue that it can be accommodated if we assume that learning, including category formation, proceeds bottom-up, and that learners do not unlearn predictably distributed categories unless compelled to do so by alternations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The [ATR]/laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</guid>
      <description>I offer a preliminary analysis of the phenomenon of calediad (&amp;lsquo;provection&amp;rsquo;) in South-Eastern Welsh, whereby &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (lenis) stops become &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; after a stressed vowel. I argue that since vowels before lenis stops are generally long &amp;mdash; and, given the phonology of South Welsh &amp;mdash; tense, provection is an example of vowel-consonant interaction, where the same feature is used for the tense/lax contrast in vowels and laryngeal contrast in consonants. I interpret this as supporting emergent feature theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In defence of Richness of the Base</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I briefly present the analysis of mora assignment to consonants in South Welsh. The pattern can be analysed by appeal to the form of the inputs (i.e. with a massive number of accidental gaps, which is undesirable), or by positing a constraint schema with undesirable consequences for factorial typology. I suggest that the latter solution is preferable theoretically, although it may be premature to choose it for that reason alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</guid>
      <description>Here, I propose an analysis of the interacting between final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian (and other related varieties of northern Italy). Historically, stressed vowels lengthen before voiced obstruents, but this is opacified by final devoicing. I capitalize on phonetic studies showing final devoicing in the language to be incomplete and argue that the process is not in fact opaque: devoicing does not involve neutralization but instead the creation of a third, laryngealy unspecified class of obstruents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my Toronto presentation and to a certain extent my talk from the 6th CLC). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaning licensing mismatches in Welsh</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I propose a new analysis of so-called &amp;lsquo;vowel mutation&amp;rsquo; in Welsh, whereby final syllables (both stressed and unstressed) only allow a reduced inventory (by disallowing [ə]). I argue that these final syllables are specified with something like a suprasegmental feature that triggers a feature co-occurrence effect, and that there is no need for recourse to a mechanism of metrical prominence akin to that borne by stressed syllables (as previously suggested in the literature).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in the north of Italy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents in detail the analysis of Friulian also given at the 18th mfm and later published here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started here. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature geometry meets contrastive specification</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the interaction between vowel lengthening before voiced obstruents and final devoicing in two languages: Friulian and Breton. I argue that such interactions are transparent and involve a three-way laryngeal contrast formalized geometrically, with true voiceless obstruents the most structurally complex and devoiced ones least. The Friulian analysis was later published here and the Breton was largely incorporated into the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian palatalization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</guid>
      <description>In this talk we argue that the traditional view of vowel-driven palatalization in Russian is inadequate, at least for two reasons. First, it relies on a six-vowel interpretation of the Russian inventory that is not adequate from a phonetic perspective. Second, and more importantly, it undergenerates the range of alternations found in Modern Standard Russian. Instead, we argue that palatalization must be driven by a floating feature attached to the left edge of suffixes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
      <description>This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see this talk and this paper). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>