<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Substance Free Phonology in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="http://anghyflawn.github.io/img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/substance-free-phonology/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 21:18:07 BST</updated>



<item>
<title>LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/lel2e/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/lel2e/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is (optionally) a part of the pre-Honours sequence in the Linguistics undergraduate degree (but can of course be taken as an outside course). In &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;, I am responsible for the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Indo-European language family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in the phonology of European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For course materials, see the relevant page on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learn.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Learn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;, I am acting as the course organizer for LEL2D. I am also responsible for the entire phonology block. You can get some idea of its contents by looking at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://resourcelists.ed.ac.uk/lists/1713C19C-E564-12A2-D85D-27A30B730228.html&#34;&gt;Resource List&lt;/a&gt; for last year&amp;rsquo;s course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course materials will be available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learn.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course (co-taught with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/people/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt;) we consider a variety of issues connected to phonological change. Throughout the course, we address questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we reconstruct the phonology of past language states?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What types of phonological changes are attested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can synchronic phonological theory assist us in the study of historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn about the human language faculty by studying historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;, I will cover the following topics (subject to change with extreme prejudice):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanisms and types of phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical phonology and phonological representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course materials are available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.learn.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic, English, and Norse in Contact</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/celtic-norse-english/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2017/celtic-norse-english/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course has three main objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An introduction to Celtic linguistics, via familiarizing students with the structural properties of Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An brief introduction to the study of language contact, with particular attention to criteria used to diagnose contact features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A discussion of various ways in which Celtic and North Germanic languages interacted with each other and with English in the British Isles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course presupposes &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; knowledge of any modern or ancient Celtic language. However, it is also open to students pursuing Honours degrees in Celtic, as long as they have passed one of the second-year Gaelic courses &amp;mdash; while some of the linguistic concepts may require a bit of effort (especially if you haven&amp;rsquo;t taken at least LEL1 in pre-Honours), much of the language material will be familiar or sufficiently similar to Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be helpful (albeit not at all obligatory) for the early part of the course (which isn&amp;rsquo;t really about linguistics) to get some background on the early medieval period in Britain and Ireland. For a light but very informative introduction, one suggestion is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theambulist.co.uk/books/journeys&#34;&gt;Max Adams&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;In the land of giants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the weekly plan from &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, which is subject to changes in &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction and the historical setting

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic and the Anglo-Saxon conquest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic and English in the Middle Ages. The Norse presence in England, Scotland, and Ireland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Language shift. &amp;lsquo;Celtic Englishes&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Old Irish. Modern Irish phonology and morphosyntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Scottish Gaelic. Middle Welsh. Modern Welsh phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Modern Welsh morphosyntax. Cornish and Breton. An introduction to language contact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sociolinguistic complexity and types of language contact. Diagnosing historical contact. Class test (worth 30% of the mark)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Celtic hypothesis: was Early English influenced by Celtic?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact with Norse: North Germanic and English. The Norse influence and Gaelic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic Englishes: Irish English. Scotland.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic Englishes: Welsh English. Cornwall and Brittany. Summary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining 70% of the mark will be assessed by a final essay of 3,000 words, to be written between the end of teaching and the start of the exam period.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Making sense of consonant palatalization vowel backness in Irish</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Despite its status as a minority language, Modern Irish has a rich body of phonetic and phonological descriptions, based on (near-)native fieldworker knowledge and traditional auditory methods. In this paper, we draw on a range of up-to-date instrumental and quantitative methods in order to verify and expand the traditional findings regarding the nature and status of the interaction between consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the descriptive literature, there are several types of consonant-to-vowel coarticulation in Modern Irish. In the case of long vowels, the distribution of front and back vowels is free with respect to surrounding consonant palatalization: &lt;em&gt;ciúin&lt;/em&gt; /k&amp;rsquo;uːn&amp;rsquo;/ &amp;lsquo;quiet&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;buíon&amp;rsquo; /biːn/ &amp;lsquo;company&amp;rsquo;. However, descriptions recognize the phonetic reality of &amp;lsquo;on-&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;off-glides&amp;rsquo; when the backness of the long vowel does not match that of the neighbouring consonant: [kʲuːʲn], [bʷiːˠn]. In the case of short vowels, it is commonly argued that (some) front and back vowels show complementary distribution driven by consonant palatalization, such that, for instance, &lt;em&gt;giobal&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;rag&amp;rsquo; (surface [ɡʲʊbəl]) and &lt;em&gt;duine&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;man&amp;rsquo; (surface [dɪnʲə]) both contain the underlying segment (phoneme) /ɯ/, and are derived from /ɡ&amp;rsquo;ɯbəl/ and /dɯn&amp;rsquo;ə/ by &amp;lsquo;vowel separation&amp;rsquo; rules. At the same time, some of the more careful phonetic descriptions also recognize the existence of finely grained (though apparently categorical) vowel allophony driven by consonant palatalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We report the results of a project aiming to disentangle the categorical and gradient aspects of this coarticulation using instrumental methods. Previous studies  show that for low vowels the effect of consonant palatalization on the quality of adjacent vowels cannot be described as simply a &amp;lsquo;glide&amp;rsquo; &amp;mdash; the consonant exerts an influence throughout the duration of the vowel &amp;mdash; and that consonant-vowel coarticulation in Irish is gradient. In this paper, we focus on a controlled acoustic study of &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; vowels, claimed in the literature to undergo both categorical (complementary distribution) and gradient (fine-grained allophony) coarticulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We present the results of fitting a variety of generalized additive mixed models  to the acoustic data, and show that both kinds of effects co-exist in Modern Irish: a categorical rule enforcing (near-)allophony and gradient consonant-vowel coarticulation. We argue that this is a theoretically interesting example of the phenomenon of &amp;lsquo;rule scattering&amp;rsquo;, which would have been difficult to establish with confidence solely on the basis of traditional descriptions. We also discuss some of the challenges associated with gathering balanced data (necessary for quantitative analysis) using reading tasks from a minority language, even one with a well-established tradition of literacy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Problems of phonemicization</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/clc9/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/clc9/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We address a long-standing issue in the phonology of Modern Irish: the phonological status of the distinction between front and back short vowels. We argue that the approach inherent in most theoretical work on the topic, which privileges traditional &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; criteria such as predictability of distribution, misses important generalizations and cannot be sustained. Instead, we suggest that front and back (non-low) vowels in Irish are best thought of as phonologically &amp;lsquo;distinctive&amp;rsquo;, but not (significantly) &amp;lsquo;contrastive&amp;rsquo; units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reconsider the arguments for the noncontrastive status of the front/back distinction in short vowels in Modern Irish, on the basis of a cross-dialectal acoustic study. Our results show that the distributional generalizations offered in Roibeard Ó Maolalaigh&amp;rsquo;s (1997) summary of the traditional description literature, which suggests the distinction is largely allophonic, are by and large correct.  Our quantitative analysis, which relies on model comparison methods applied to generalized additive mixed models, also shows that front and back vowels form distinct categories in the output of the phonology: models that assume more than one backness category per height achieve better fit than ones assuming a surface &amp;lsquo;vertical&amp;rsquo; system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conclude that front and back vowels form distinct categories that are accessible to the phonological grammar, and offer an interpretation of the facts centred around the notion of &amp;lsquo;quasi-phonemes&amp;rsquo;: phonologically distinct elements that do not stand in contrastive distribution. We argue that this framework allows us to unify the description of the low functional load of the distribution and the analysis of vowel backness alternations in the synchronic grammar. We show that our analysis, which does not predict fully complementary distribution, is superior to previous approaches that relied on &amp;lsquo;vowel separation&amp;rsquo; rules to achieve the same outcome, since it correctly predicts the possibility of exceptions. We argue that the existence and nature of these exceptions fall out of the patterns of lexicalization and rule loss predicted by the life cycle of phonological processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work builds on that presented at &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/&#34;&gt;OCP13&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/&#34;&gt;FiSK 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Morphology and dialectology: A quantitative approach</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We present a study of Gaelic dialectal variation based on the unpublished, morphological section of the Linguistic Survey of Scotland (Gaelic). Our findings indicate that a quantitative (dialectometric) approach can yield important insights into the range of internal variation in Gaelic and elucidate certain issues of language structure. Here, we focus on two questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What patterns of spatial variation are observed in the morphological data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are different morphological features in the dialects correlated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer the first question, we fit a logistic generalized additive model against a longitude-latitude spline and observe a number of patterns. Some features show a pronounced northwest-southeast cline, usually with more morphologically &amp;lsquo;innovative&amp;rsquo; dialects in the east and south. Demographic variables, such as mean age and concentrations of speakers, may be a factor. Others show a clear focus on the Outer Hebrides, particularly from North Uist southwards. This suggests that the Gaelic dialects of the southern Outer Hebrides are the most morphologically ‘conservative’ of the surviving varieties. Our approach allows us to precisely quantify these patterns, providing a firm underpinning for earlier descriptions. In some cases, the data also pose challenges for received pedagogical practice and prescriptive standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second question, we use Ward clustering on a correlation matrix to identify which features frequently co-occur in the dialects. The results shed light both on the dialectal divisions of Gaelic and, arguably, on its grammatical structure. For instance, we identify a strong correlation between the absence of lenition in returns such as an cas (nominative), cas beag (nominative) and am fear (genitive). These patterns are not strongly correlated with other cases of lenition absence. We interpret this as suggesting that lenition in these contexts may be driven by a single grammatical mechanism (whose loss underlies this consistent absence of lenition), which is not in action in other lenition contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, our results show the potential of a quantitative approach to Gaelic dialectology and its promise for a larger study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>clc ldlt</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/clc-ldlt/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/clc-ldlt/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We will present our joint work with Máire Ní Chiosáin on vowel backness and consonant palatalization in Irish at two further conferences: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.cardiff.ac.uk/events/view/9th-celtic-linguistics-conference/&#34;&gt;9th Celtic Linguistics Conference&lt;/a&gt; in Cardiff and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.soas.ac.uk/language-documentation-and-linguistic-theory-2016/&#34;&gt;Language Documentation and Linguistic Theory 5&lt;/a&gt; in London.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>amc</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/amc/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/amc/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rug.nl/staff/r.m.knooihuizen/&#34;&gt;Remco Knooihuizen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/amc/&#34;&gt;Vowel length in Shetland Norn: Contact, change, and competing systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amc.lel.ed.ac.uk/?page_id=931&#34;&gt;First AMC Symposium&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Edinburgh&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vowel length in Shetland Norn</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/amc/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/amc/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the areas in which Scandinavian influence is apparent in the traditional Shetland Scots dialect is the distribution of vowel length: Shetland Scots generally follows the Scottish Vowel Length Rule, but also shows the complementary distribution of consonant and vowel length known from modern North Germanic languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the earliest development of Shetland Scots, three different systems of vowel length can be argued to have been in contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Nearly) unconstrained vowel length, as in Old Norse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scandinavian combinatory vowel length&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Scottish Vowel Length Rule&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these systems were in the process of change in our time period, with System 1 giving way to System 2 across Scandinavia, and the SVLR also developing at about the same time. In both System 2 and the SVLR, we also observe the rise of an interaction between vowel quantity and ‘tense/lax’ quality. Thus, the system in Shetland Norn presents a set of interesting questions for the study of historical dialectology, language contact and historical phonology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We give a detailed account of the distribution of vowel length in a 2m000-token sample of Jakob Jakobsen&amp;rsquo;s dictionary of Shetland Norn, and compare it to the contact systems. We show that clear traces of all three systems, as well as local innovations, are found in the data. We also place the Shetland Norn data in the context of both Scots and Scandinavian historical phonology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the handout has more detail than the slides.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>nrn proceedings</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/nrn-proceedings/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 17:02:38 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/nrn-proceedings/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/nrn-proceedings/&#34;&gt;My paper on tonogenesis in North Germanic&lt;/a&gt; will appear in the proceedings of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nordicresearchnetwork.co.uk/conference-2015.html&#34;&gt;Nordic Research Network 2015 conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>leave</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/leave/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 16:58:52 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/leave/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In the autumn semester of &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;, I will be on research leave and will not be teaching any courses. See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching&#34;&gt;teaching page&lt;/a&gt; for the spring semester plans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>rnag2016</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/rnag2016/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 16:55:45 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/rnag2016/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/literatures-languages-cultures/celtic-scottish-studies/staff/dr-william-lamb&#34;&gt;Will Lamb&lt;/a&gt; will present the results of &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/rnag2016/&#34;&gt;our joint work&lt;/a&gt; on quantitative approaches to dialect variation in Scottish Gaelic morphology at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smo.uhi.ac.uk/en/rannsachadh/rnag2016/&#34;&gt;Rannsachadh na Gàidhlig 2016&lt;/a&gt; at Sabhal Mòr Ostaig.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Tonal stability and tonogenesis in North Germanic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/nrn-proceedings/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/nrn-proceedings/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The origin of North Germanic tonal accents is a question with a long history and a range of available answers. Although the basic facts are not in dispute, the accents&amp;rsquo; historical development remains controversial. In this paper, I aim to contribute an argument in favour of the view that tonal accent arose in post-Viking Age North Germanic in connection with changes in syllable count (Oftedal 1952; Elstad 1980; Bye 2004, 2011; Hognestad 2012). I will argue that the genesis of &amp;lsquo;accent 1&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;accent 2&amp;rsquo; as a grammaticalization of syllable count need not be seen as an isolated, unique phenomenon in the history of the North Germanic languages: instead, it is a recurring event, as demonstrated by the genesis of new &amp;lsquo;tonal accent&amp;rsquo; oppositions triggered by apocope in at least three further separate instances in Central Scandinavia, Zealand, and East Slesvig. I also adduce further typological parallels from West Germanic and from Goidelic Celtic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The northwest European linguistic area</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/uit/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/uit/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties). These similarities have been long recognized (see Eliasson 2000, Rießler 2008 for relatively recent overviews), but frequently ascribed to bilateral contact (e.g. North Germanic &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Sámi or North Germanic -&amp;gt; Goidelic Celtic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reconsider the nature of these similarities taking into account the availability of new data and new analytical tools. It is apparent that the occurrence of the relevant &amp;lsquo;rare&amp;rsquo; phenomena has been underestimated, since they often function in a variable way, and only in some cases do they become categorical phenomena. I also draw attention to the fact that in many cases the origin and functioning of the relevant phenomena is closely connected with metrical (in particular foot and moraic) structure. This, I suggest, indicates that the role of contact may have been overstated, and that the appearance of rare phenomena such as phonological preaspiration and tonal accents may be due to the (re)use of laryngeal phonetic cues to metrical structure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>tphs paper</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/stod-paper/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/stod-paper/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My paper &lt;em&gt;Prosodic structure and suprasegmental features: Short-vowel stød in Danish&lt;/em&gt; will appear in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.springer.com/education+%26+language/linguistics/journal/10828&#34;&gt;Journal of Comparative Germanic Linguistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Download the draft version &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/stod/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Prosodic structure and suprasegmental features</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/stod/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/stod/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper sets out in detail the analysis first offered in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/&#34;&gt;21mfm presentation&lt;/a&gt;. I examine the so-called &amp;lsquo;short-vowel stød&amp;rsquo; (&lt;em&gt;kortvokalstød&lt;/em&gt;) found in certain island dialects of Danish, which differs from the &amp;lsquo;common Danish&amp;rsquo; stød in that it is associated with light syllables (open syllable with short vowels or closed syllables with low-sonority codas) rather than heavy ones. I argue that it is best represented as a [constricted glottis] feature associated with a segmentally empty mora, which is projected due to top-down requirements on the internal structure of suprasegmental constituents. Thus, stød is interpreted as another example of a &amp;lsquo;tonal accent&amp;rsquo; phenomenon that submits to an analysis purely in terms of lexically stored metrical structure. I also offer an extension of the model which allows the direct association of features to suprasegmental constituents to Icelandic preaspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ocp13-fisk</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/ocp-fisk/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/ocp-fisk/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Our joint work  with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ucd.ie/research/people/irishcelstirishflling/drmairenichiosain/&#34;&gt;Máire Ní Chiosáin&lt;/a&gt; on consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic was &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/&#34;&gt;presented&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://seas3.elte.hu/ocp13&#34;&gt;13th Old World Conference in Phonology&lt;/a&gt; in Budapest and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/&#34;&gt;Fonologi i Skandinavien (FiSK) meeting&lt;/a&gt; in Gothenburg&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels: phonology and/or coarticulation</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk presents much the same material as our presentation at &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/&#34;&gt;OCP13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vowel backness and palatalization in Irish and Scottish Gaelic: A study in rule scattering</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We present the results of an acoustic study of the interaction of consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels. Previous descriptions of Irish (but usually not of Scottish Gaelic) often describe the distribution of front vs. back nonlow vowels as predictable (allophonic). This makes Irish a potential example of a vertical vowel system. However, the sources are mostly impressionistic, and also tend to underplay the extent of variation within and across lexical items. Our study shows that the magnitude of coarticulation, whilst statistically detectable, is insufficient to account for the full range of front-back distinction. It is also comparable in Irish and in Scottish Gaelic. We argue that the interaction of palatalization and vowel backness in both languages is manifested both phonetically (as coarticulation) and phonologically (as symbolic fronting and backing rules), a situation described by Bermúdez-Otero (2015) as &amp;lsquo;rule scattering&amp;rsquo;. However, unlike other cases of rule scattering, the categorical pattern did not arise directly by phonologization of the gradient one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, I acted as the course organizer for LEL2D. I was also responsible for the entire phonology block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course materials are available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learn.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Linguistics and the Gaelic Language</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/cananachas/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/cananachas/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is an obligatory part of the pre-Honours sequence for students on the MA (Hons) degree in Gaelic and Primary Education. It will introduce students to the linguistic analysis of the Scottish Gaelic language, giving an overview of phonetics and phonology, morphology and syntax, together with consideration of key sociolinguistic principles and issues, including phenomena relating to language contact, language shift and status and corpus planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, I taught the sections on phonetics and phonology and on language change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/lel2e/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/lel2e/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is (optionally) a part of the pre-Honours sequence in the Linguistics undergraduate degree (but can of course be taken as an outside course). In &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, I was responsible for the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Indo-European language family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in the phonology of European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For course materials, see the relevant page on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learn.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Learn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course (co-taught with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/people/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt;) we consider a variety of issues connected to phonological change. Throughout the course, we address questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we reconstruct the phonology of past language states?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What types of phonological changes are attested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can synchronic phonological theory assist us in the study of historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn about the human language faculty by studying historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;, I covered the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and historical phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The origins of sound change and phonologization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical phonology and phonological representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course materials are available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.learn.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;Learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic, English, and Norse in Contact</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/celtic-norse-english/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/celtic-norse-english/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course runs for the first time in &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt; (but will probably run every other year). It has three main objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An introduction to Celtic linguistics, via familiarizing students with the structural properties of Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An brief introduction to the study of language contact, with particular attention to criteria used to diagnose contact features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A discussion of various ways in which Celtic and North Germanic languages interacted with each other and with English in the British Isles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course presupposes &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; knowledge of any modern or ancient Celtic language. However, it is also open to students pursuing Honours degrees in Celtic, as long as they have passed one of the second-year Gaelic courses &amp;mdash; while some of the linguistic concepts may require a bit of effort (especially if you haven&amp;rsquo;t taken at least LEL1 in pre-Honours), much of the language material will be familiar or sufficiently similar to Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check this page later for a course handbook. In the meantime, here is a preliminary weekly plan (subject to change with extreme prejudice):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction and the historical setting

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic and the Anglo-Saxon conquest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic and English in the Middle Ages. The Norse presence in England, Scotland, and Ireland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Language shift. &amp;lsquo;Celtic Englishes&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Old Irish. Modern Irish phonology and morphosyntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Scottish Gaelic. Middle Welsh. Modern Welsh phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Modern Welsh morphosyntax. Cornish and Breton. An introduction to language contact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sociolinguistic complexity and types of language contact. Diagnosing historical contact. Class test (worth 30% of the mark)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Celtic hypothesis: was Early English influenced by Celtic?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact with Norse: North Germanic and English. The Norse influence and Gaelic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic Englishes: Irish English. Scotland.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic Englishes: Welsh English. Cornwall and Brittany. Summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining 70% of the mark will be assessed by a final essay of 3,000 words, to be written between the end of teaching and the start of the exam period.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>tphs paper</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/tphs-paper/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 18:36:19 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/tphs-paper/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My paper &lt;em&gt;Welsh svarabhakti as stem allomorphy&lt;/em&gt; will appear in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philsoc.org.uk/transactions.asp&#34;&gt;Transactions of the Philological Society&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Download the draft version &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Welsh svarabhakti as stem allomorphy</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper develops the analysis in &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame:-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/&#34;&gt;this presentation&lt;/a&gt;. I offer an analysis of Welsh epenthesis, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (&lt;em&gt;pwdr&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]) and deletion in such clusters in polysyllables (&lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has previously been argued that both processes can be analysed in a single phonological grammar. I show that this is not tenable for South Welsh dialects, and propose an analysis in terms of part-of-speech-specific allomorphy, formalized as lexical storage of POS-characterized stems rather than roots.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>carnegie</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/carnegie/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 13:47:48 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/carnegie/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I have been awarded a £3,183 Research Incentive Grant by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegie-trust.org&#34;&gt;Carnegie Trust for the Universities of Scotland&lt;/a&gt; for the project &lt;em&gt;Preaspiration in North Germanic: Internal variation and language history&lt;/em&gt;. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amc.lel.ed.ac.uk/?page_id=1397&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonetic (non-)explanation in historical phonology: Duration, harmony, and dissimilation</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We consider the value of phonetically based explanations for phonological change by tracing the phonologization paths of durational asymmetries between vowels. The literature on phonetic motivations for phonological change identifies relative shortness of one vowel with respect to another as an important precursor to vowel reduction, which, in turn, may feed hypercorrection of the reduced vowel to give rise to vowel harmony phenomena. We examine such a case from Nivkh in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other language, similar durational asymmetries fail to promote hypercorrection, instead becoming the basis of sound change whereby the height of vowels changes to adjust their inherent duration in line with the asymmetry. This promotes apparent dissimilation phenomena; we examine such a case from Irish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, durational asymmetries provoke both harmony and dissimilation as phonological changes. While this is unsurprising given the sotchastic nature of phonologization, we suggest that such cases weaken the &lt;em&gt;predictive&lt;/em&gt; power of &amp;lsquo;evolutionary&amp;rsquo; theories of sound change: without detailed phonetic information on the precursors of phonological change, it cannot be said that explanations eschewing a role for formal factors are not necessarily more explanatory than ones that do incorporate formal theorizing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Spring 2016 teaching</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/spring-2016-teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 20:53:33 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/spring-2016-teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In the spring semester of &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, I will be teaching on the following courses: &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/lel2d/&#34;&gt;LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours; I am also the course organizer); &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/lel2e/&#34;&gt;LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours); &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/cananachas/&#34;&gt;Linguistics and the Gaelic Language&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours); &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/celtic-norse-english/&#34;&gt;Celtic, English, and Norse in Contact&lt;/a&gt; (Honours); and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/historical-phonology/&#34;&gt;Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt; (Honours/MSc).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>cjl</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/cjl/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 20:49:20 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/cjl/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;From 1st January 2016 I have been serving on the editorial board of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayJournal?jid=CNJ&#34;&gt;Canadian Journal of Linguistics | Revue canadienne de linguistique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ocp13</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/ocp13/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2015 21:08:40 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/ocp13/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/&#34;&gt;joint work&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ucd.ie/research/people/irishcelstirishflling/drmairenichiosain/&#34;&gt;Máire Ní Chiosáin&lt;/a&gt; on consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic was presented at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://seas3.elte.hu/ocp13&#34;&gt;13th Old World Conference in Phonology&lt;/a&gt; in Budapest, and is on the programme for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/&#34;&gt;Fonologi i Skandinavien (FiSK) meeting&lt;/a&gt; in Gothenburg&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>eshp2</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/eshp2/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2015 12:09:14 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/eshp2/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phonetic (non-)explanation in historical phonology: Duration, harmony, and dissimilation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (with &lt;a href=&#34;http://hum.leiden.edu/lucl/organisation/members-a-e/botmaed2.html&#34;&gt;Bert Botma&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ext-web.edu.sgu.ac.jp/hidetos/&#34;&gt;Hidetoshi Shiraishi&lt;/a&gt;) at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/symposium-on-historical-phonology&#34;&gt;2nd Edinburgh Symposium on Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Book review: Pam na fu Cymru</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/pam-na-fu-cymru/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/pam-na-fu-cymru/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;What follows is a short(ish) review of an excellently provocative new(ish) book by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SeimonBrooks&#34;&gt;Simon Brooks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pam na fu Cymru: Methiant cenedlaetholdeb Cymraeg&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;lsquo;Why Wales wasn&amp;rsquo;t: The failure of Welsh nationalism&amp;rsquo;).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:a308841650967ab9e00c045625a34756:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:a308841650967ab9e00c045625a34756:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is, as the author notes, the second part of what may be deemed a trilogy, following from the no less interesting collection &lt;em&gt;Pa beth yr aethoch chi allan i&amp;rsquo;w achub?&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;lsquo;What did you go out to save?&amp;rsquo;), which also posed some rather less comfortable questions for the Welsh language (re)vitalization movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Brooks&amp;rsquo; starting point is a denial of the &amp;lsquo;heroic narrative&amp;rsquo; of language survival, best expressed in Dafydd Iwan&amp;rsquo;s iconic &lt;em&gt;Yma o Hyd&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;lsquo;We&amp;rsquo;re still here&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/12DsDOHzmjE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this story, which is pretty much the orthodox picture, plucky little Welsh survives despite the might of the British Empire, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.llgc.org.uk/index.php?id=thebluebooks&#34;&gt;Treachery of the Blue Books&lt;/a&gt;, industrialization, and all the rest of it, and its survival is due to the fantastic resilience of the Welsh speakers in the face of rather long odds. Brooks (not unconvincingly) utterly demolishes this story, pointing out (in chapter 1, &amp;lsquo;The unexpected failure of Welsh nationalism&amp;rsquo;) that pretty much all the minority communities of Europe (except maybe the Czechs) faced rather longer odds in terms of their economy, access to education and the printing press, and other factors usually seen to foster the growth of nationalism. Brooks is really failing to hold back his anger there. In the early 19th century Wales was far advanced along the modernization path, but the language was still very much alive, and in fact newcomers in the growing industrial areas of the south were being assimilated &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; Welsh-speaking society &amp;mdash; and yet in terms of language preservation it has ended up behind not just the Czechs, Hungarians or Catalans, but much smaller and later developing nations like the Slovaks, Slovenians or Estonians. Brooks argues that although the situation in Central and Eastern Europe was different given the preponderance of multinational empires, it cannot be said that the Western European context would necessarily inhibit the growth of &amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo; nations &amp;mdash; Basques and Catalans being his two &lt;em&gt;Paradestücke&lt;/em&gt;. Wales, in fact, is somewhat of a paradoxical failure, given its favourable starting position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2, &amp;lsquo;The people of the language&amp;rsquo;, discusses the potential precursors to a stronger Welsh nationalism in early 19th century Wales, such as the &amp;lsquo;Llanover Circle&amp;rsquo;, who were strongly influenced by Herderian ideas. (Or indeed outside Wales, as in the society of Welsh clergymen of Yorkshire.) Crucially, Brooks points out, many exponents of an early form of &lt;em&gt;Landespatriotismus&lt;/em&gt; were generally conservative in their politics and Anglican in religion, rather than Liberal and Nonconformist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In chapter 3, Brooks considers the relationship between the Welsh &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;liberal&amp;rsquo; tradition and the Welsh language. For Brooks, Liberal ideas of progress, &amp;lsquo;common sense&amp;rsquo; and individual rights all end up being harmful to the cause of the  language. The Liberal ideal where the general triumphs over the particular inevitably leads to a normalization of monolingualism. Welsh speakers must learn English, because that is the way to join the community of reason and progress, and refusing to do so is harmful to their own individual good. This, of course, is the ideology of the Blue Books:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Welsh language is a vast drawback to Wales and a manifold
barrier to the moral progress and commercial prosperity of the
people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or of John Stuart Mill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experience proves that it is possible for one nationality to merge
and be absorbed in another; and when it was originally an inferior
and more backward portion of the human race, the absorption is
greatly to its advantage. Nobody can suppose that it is not more
beneficial to a Breton, or a Basque of French Navarre, to be brought
into the current of the ideas and feelings of a highly civilized and
cultivated people—to be a member of the French nationality, admitted
on equal terms to all the privileges of French citizenship, sharing
the advantages of French protection, and the dignity and prestige of
French power—than to sulk on his own rocks, the half-savage relic of
past times, revolving in his own little mental orbit, without
participation or interest in the general movement of the world. The
same remark applies to the Welshman or the Scottish Highlander as
members of the British nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, Wales was not at all unique in this: Brooks adduces examples of &amp;lsquo;assimilationist Liberalism&amp;rsquo; from the Continent in chapter 4. He also considers some responses to this tradition, both in Europe and in Wales. Here, he comes back to the idea that since liberal politics is inimical to minorities, they had to join forces with conservatism (albeit tactically and pragmatically rather than necessarily ideologically); hence František Palacký&amp;rsquo;s refusal to support the German parliament in Frankfurt: better keep the empire that can be talked to than being guaranteed to be outvoted by a parliament. In Wales, Brooks pays particular attention to Michael D. Jones &amp;ndash; best known for his role in the Welsh colonization enterprise in Patagonia &amp;ndash; and Emrys ap Iwan, who both rejected the Liberal anti-particularist stance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In chapter 5, &amp;lsquo;How Wales can be&amp;rsquo;, Brooks sets out what he sees as the quandary of Welsh nationalism. The Welsh political tradition has a strong &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;progressive&amp;rsquo; identity, first Liberal, then Labourite. Both of these traditions strongly emphasize universal values and downplay the kind of minority-community rights that underpin language revitalization. In this situation, Welsh nationalism has had relatively little space to offer a critique of this dominant narrative from the left, and hence has tended to the right, notably with Saunders Lewis. Brooks is strongly critical of &amp;lsquo;civic nationalism&amp;rsquo; (continuing a theme from &lt;em&gt;Pa beth yr aethoch&lt;/em&gt;), which inherits the emphasis on universality and individual rights, and hence perpetuates the asymmetrical power relationship between English (the &amp;lsquo;default&amp;rsquo; language of the &amp;lsquo;general&amp;rsquo; values) and Welsh. His preferred solution appears to be a discarding of assimilationist, English-inclined liberalism in favour of one where Welsh is made into the same kind of &amp;lsquo;general&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;common&amp;rsquo; language (at least in some parts of the country) that English is now across Wales. He recognizes that this requires policy solutions that are not, strictly speaking, consistent with the mainstream liberal views of &amp;lsquo;liberty&amp;rsquo; &amp;mdash; such as requiring immigrants to Welsh-speaking communities to learn Welsh (after all, Brooks points out, immigrants to the English-speaking British communities are expected, indeed often required by law, to learn English) or introducing positive discrimination measures in areas such as housing. The trade-off, however, is worth it, since the alternative is the progressive weakening of the language, which is presumably undesirable even for &amp;lsquo;civic&amp;rsquo; nationalists, given the relative weakness of a purely political Welsh identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brooks certainly does not pull his punches. It&amp;rsquo;s a highly interesting book even for someone like me who only has a fairly passing acquaintance with either the history of nationalism or relevant issues in language policy. Brooks&amp;rsquo; warning to Welsh nationalism that an uncritical embrace of the British Left means siding with what is often an unthinkingly assimilationist narrative is a challenging idea that deserves to be taken seriously (it is certainly much more nuanced than the simplistic &amp;lsquo;BritNats don&amp;rsquo;t notice they&amp;rsquo;re nationalist&amp;rsquo; smugness we&amp;rsquo;ve been recently seeing so much of). At the same time Brooks offers some tantalizing pointers showing how a left-wing perspective is not entirely incompatible with the sort of recipes he has in mind for protecting the Welsh language. One point that struck me as quite pertinent is the idea that under a liberal regime minority communities have a right to security (i.e. to not being persecuted) but not a right to survival or even growth &amp;mdash; a useful perspective for someone like me who hasn&amp;rsquo;t encountered it before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in sum, a challenging but interesting read. I teach some lectures on Celtic in our second-year &lt;em&gt;Structure and history of European languages&lt;/em&gt; course, and the few minutes I spend on Welsh sociolinguistics have so far been rather colonized by the &amp;lsquo;heroic narrative&amp;rsquo; of Welsh language survival. It strikes me that I probably have to fix this now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:a308841650967ab9e00c045625a34756:1&#34;&gt;Or more precisely Welsh-language nationalism.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:a308841650967ab9e00c045625a34756:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2015/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2015/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to a range of important topics in (generative) phonological theory and to phonological data analysis. On the theoretical side, we will cover the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of phonological theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivations, underlying representations, rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process interaction and rule ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suprasegmental phonology: syllable structure, stress, tone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced feature theory: feature geometry, unary features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constraints in phonology: well-formedness conditions, templates, conspiracies, the &amp;lsquo;duplication problem&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explanation in phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, there is a strong emphasis on building data analysis and problem solving skills. Click &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/phonological-theory/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for last year&amp;rsquo;s course handbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this course, students will be able to progress to advanced study of phonological theory. In &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, we will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be offering LASC10089 Current Issues in Phonology, but it is planned that this will run in the second semester of &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;. Get in touch early with prospective supervisors if you&amp;rsquo;re thinking about an Honours dissertation in phonology in &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;, because it is likely you&amp;rsquo;ll need to do some summer reading. Conversely, LASC10046 Historical Phonology &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; running this year, but not next year. Plan accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teaching language in schools: beyond foreign languages</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/language-in-schools/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/language-in-schools/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scotsman.com/news/insight-why-scots-face-a-language-barrier-1-3853275&#34;&gt;An excellent piece&lt;/a&gt; by Dani Garavelli in Scotland on Sunday on the state of modern foreign languages in Scottish schools includes a familiar litany of failings: a relatively early end of compulsory language study, staffing issues, teaching methods, differences between schools with more opportunities for pupils from more privileged backgrounds, and so on, and on, and on. One of the points strikes a bit closer to home for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One [factor] is that our children are taught very little English
grammar. This means that when it comes to studying another language
they have to learn concepts such as tenses and verb conjugation from
scratch. “When they come into our class, they have never heard terms
like past participle,” says one ML teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, I submit, a big problem, not just as far as modern languages go. The science of language should be taught in schools, as part of the English curriculum, for foreign languages, and just more generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can quite vividly recall the shock I experienced when, as a PhD student, I tutored an Introduction to Linguistics course. Well, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t even that: at that time, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uit.no&#34;&gt;University of Tromsø&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s courses were set up in a way where all students in the &amp;lsquo;Faculty of Humanities&amp;rsquo; (this basically meant Norwegian language &amp;amp; literature, foreign languages &amp;amp; literatures, and a few other allied subjects) had to do something called &lt;em&gt;examen facultatum&lt;/em&gt;, which was a brief introduction to all the subjects taught at the faculty, including linguistics. So the students were a mix of language-y and non-language-y types. In my first two or three tutorials I had the distinct feeling I was running full speed into a brick wall. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t that they were lazy, or weren&amp;rsquo;t trying hard, or anything like that &amp;mdash; clearly not &amp;mdash; but I was getting nowhere. And then it hit me: the very idea that the structure of language is an object of analysis was just foreign to them. This was very new to me. I went to school in Russia, where (at least way back when) some versions of phonetic, morphological and syntactic analysis are taught (and assessed) from a very early stage and throughout the school years. The way it&amp;rsquo;s done can be, and often is, dry and unenlightening, but the very concept of analysing language is not something that&amp;rsquo;s alien and new when you start university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things seem to be quite different in Norway &amp;mdash; and, it would seem, in much of the English-speaking world as well. And that is a problem. Teaching the science of language can help with a lot, and it should not be too difficult to find interesting angles. People are fascinated by language and want to know more. Not giving them the tools and knowledge to master what can be mastered in this area is selling them short. And it can, in fact, be harmful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, people&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://languagelog.ldc.upenn.edu/nll/?p=1357&#34;&gt;nervous cluelessness&lt;/a&gt; about language provides fertile ground to all sorts of prejudice. Consider &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.english.ox.ac.uk/about-faculty/faculty-members/language-and-linguistics/cameron-professor-deborah&#34;&gt;Deborah Cameron&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s admirable &lt;a href=&#34;https://debuk.wordpress.com/2015/07/05/just-dont-do-it/&#34;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://debuk.wordpress.com/2015/07/26/a-response-to-naomi-wolf/&#34;&gt;crusade&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://debuk.wordpress.com/2015/08/03/how-to-write-a-bullshit-article-about-womens-language/&#34;&gt;against&lt;/a&gt; bullshit attitudes to women&amp;rsquo;s language &amp;mdash; really just using a vaguely-plausibly-sounding factoid to clamp down on women. Of course it&amp;rsquo;s not plausible to teach schoolchildren about the intricacies of creaky voice &amp;mdash; but it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; (or should be) plausible to equip them with the knowledge that language is not something policed from above but a real phenomenon that can be analysed and talked about in scientific terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar story can be told with non-standard forms of speech. People tend to dismiss them as &amp;lsquo;slang&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;incorrect&amp;rsquo; versions of General English, but there is a lot of teaching that could be done on the basis of comparing pupils&amp;rsquo; native varieties with General English. It should not be too difficult to show the difference between &amp;lsquo;accent&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;dialect&amp;rsquo; using a localized version of the anecdote recounted by Joseph Wright in his &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/stream/englishdialectgr00wriguoft#page/n9/mode/2up&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;English dialect grammar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (which I lifted, of course, from John Wells&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;Accents of English&lt;/em&gt;): a local pronunciation of phrase in General English (in Wright, &lt;em&gt;the roads are dirty&lt;/em&gt; with a characteristic Northern English [oː] vowel) is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; standard &amp;mdash; it is General English with an &amp;lsquo;accent&amp;rsquo; &amp;mdash; but it is of course appreciably different from the &amp;lsquo;dialect&amp;rsquo; version, which Wells tentatively respells as &lt;em&gt;&amp;rsquo;t reeads is mucky&lt;/em&gt;, with phonetic (&lt;em&gt;reeads&lt;/em&gt;), lexical (&lt;em&gt;&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;mucky&lt;/em&gt;) and syntactic (with &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; following the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_subject_rule&#34;&gt;Northern Subject Rule&lt;/a&gt;) differences from General English. This is all eminently teachable, and in-depth attention to people&amp;rsquo;s native varieties can show that these varieties are just as &amp;lsquo;logical&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;rule-bound&amp;rsquo; as General English (just look at the work of linguists like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ulster.ac.uk/staff/am.henry.html&#34;&gt;Alison Henry&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gla.ac.uk/schools/critical/staff/jennifersmith/&#34;&gt;Jennifer Smith&lt;/a&gt; to see how interesting and important these non-standard varieties can be). Instead, what we all too often get is disparagement of non-standard varieties, often with more or less overt class prejudice thrown into the mix &amp;mdash; in Scotland, it&amp;rsquo;s the slang spoken by the neds of the schemes. Or do a quick search for &amp;lsquo;fleg&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;say nahim&amp;rsquo; &amp;mdash; representations of typical lower-status pronunciations in Ulster English &amp;mdash; to see how they&amp;rsquo;re used as markers of working-class speech to satirize (overwhelmingly working-class) protesters. It might be less acceptable to say they&amp;rsquo;re trash from the estate, but to point fingers at their language counts as funny. (This often comes packaged with the oh-so-funny observation that Ulster Scots is English with a Ballymena accent &amp;mdash; although a test along the lines of Wright&amp;rsquo;s anecdote can quickly disavow this.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the other side of this barricade you will often find well-meaning but rather ill-informed defences along the lines of &amp;lsquo;Scots is a separate language because it&amp;rsquo;s a mixture of English and Scandinavian&amp;rsquo;. This reflects people&amp;rsquo;s interest &amp;mdash; but also the limitations of trying to find stuff out for oneself without access to the necessary background knowledge about how languages develop and change, and why &amp;lsquo;language mixture&amp;rsquo; is such an imprecise description of what&amp;rsquo;s going on here (or indeed why this kind of appeal shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be necessary to justify people&amp;rsquo;s ways of speaking). And this is the kind of stuff that should not be all that difficult to teach in schools. In Norway, schoolchildren learn about the precise differences between Norwegian dialects and about the history of the language, with a taste of Old Norse thrown into the mix, and there&amp;rsquo;s no logical reason something similar couldn&amp;rsquo;t be done here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So learning about language can help us with learning about all sorts of ways in which it functions in society, about its different forms and shapes, and about the connection between language and history. This is perhaps unsurprising: people are just interested in these sorts of things. But the thing is that it is really not helpful to talk about these uses of language &lt;em&gt;without actually understanding how the structure of language works&lt;/em&gt;. This is where I pivot back to where I started &amp;mdash; the teaching of (English) grammar. Yes, teaching grammar can help with the teaching of foreign languages (I can still remember the epiphany I had when one of my linguistics lecturers used syntactic theory to explain in one sentence when to use the strong and weak forms of German adjectives &amp;mdash; something that I otherwise tried and pretty miserably failed to memorize). But you need to understand how language works before you move on to what it does &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s the door to all of these other things. If you&amp;rsquo;re going to explain the deal with the Northern Subject Rule, you rely on knowing what number or agreement are. If you&amp;rsquo;re going to talk about creaky voice (all right, &amp;lsquo;vocal fry&amp;rsquo;), you have to have some idea of what vocal folds are. And this means this kind of stuff is useful. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be a throwback to the supposedly good old days of drumming what an adverb is into impressionable young minds &amp;mdash; indeed it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be something different, something that allows the learner to play around and see &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; things work, show that learning about language can be fun. There are ways of doing this &amp;mdash; language is one big puzzle, and putting the pieces together doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be a matter of arduous rote learning. Have a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uklo.org&#34;&gt;UK Lingustics Olympiad&lt;/a&gt; for examples of fun language puzzles &amp;mdash; this kind of thing can be done on the basis of English material as well.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2b5cc0bc4cb7c2b416c14a66310cf9b4:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2b5cc0bc4cb7c2b416c14a66310cf9b4:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line? Knowledge about language is important. It&amp;rsquo;s important to help children learn foreign languages better, it&amp;rsquo;s important for them to understand why things in Standard English are the way they are, and it&amp;rsquo;s also important as a base for understanding the kinds of stuff that laypeople care about most, all the accents and dialects, &amp;lsquo;men&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;women&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rsquo; language, language history sort of thing. It requires a concerted effort. Knowledge about language isn&amp;rsquo;t widespread, because people assume that knowing how to speak (especially how to speak &amp;lsquo;properly&amp;rsquo;) is sufficient. It&amp;rsquo;s not part of the curriculum and it&amp;rsquo;s not part of teacher training. It&amp;rsquo;s a shame. Here in Scotland we have (false modesty aside) some cracking linguistics and English language departments, and we have students doing some absolutely brilliant work (including work on accents, dialects and social varieties of English, in Scotland and elsewhere), because they think it&amp;rsquo;s interesting, because they care about it, but (hopefully) most of all because it&amp;rsquo;s fun. So it can be done, and there&amp;rsquo;s no reason why it couldn&amp;rsquo;t be done more. We do really owe it to the children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2b5cc0bc4cb7c2b416c14a66310cf9b4:1&#34;&gt;Incidentally, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uklo.org/about/educational-rationale&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; on the UKLO website makes much the same points I do here, so it&amp;rsquo;s not just me.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2b5cc0bc4cb7c2b416c14a66310cf9b4:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>sem1 teaching</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/sem1-teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 20:57:36 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/sem1-teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In the autumn semester of &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, I am teaching &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2015/phonological-theory/&#34;&gt;LASC10088 Phonological Theory&lt;/a&gt;. For further teaching plans, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>frlsu</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/frlsu/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/frlsu/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented our &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/&#34;&gt;joint work on Argyll Gaelic preaspiration&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ppls.ed.ac.uk/people/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; at the conference of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.frlsu.org&#34;&gt;Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster&lt;/a&gt; (University of the West of Scotland, Ayr).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic and its contribution to prosodic structure</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper reports the preliminary results of an acoustic study of
preaspiration in the Gaelic of North Argyll. Existing descriptions
identify this area as reflecting Old Irish and Old Norse &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo;
geminates as [xp xt xk] clusters (&amp;lsquo;pre-affricates&amp;rsquo;), but, to our
knowledge, no targeted acoustic study of these varieties had been
performed to date. Our results confirm that the preaspiration found in
other varieties corresponds to dorsal (velar or uvular) frication in
North Argyll, rather than other conceivable interpretations of the
impressionistic descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discuss the broader repercussions of these findings regarding the
nature of preaspiration in these varieties. In particular, we find only
very scant evidence of pre-frication after long vowels (in words like
&lt;em&gt;pàpa&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;Pope&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;bàta&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;boat&amp;rsquo;), which contrasts with regular
pre-frication after short vowels. This apparent neutralization of
laryngeal contrast outside the initial foot suggests that (at least
Argyll) Gaelic shows a weakly unconditioned reduction process (lenition;
Honeybone 2012) similar to languages such as English or
Icelandic. Further, if this analysis is correct, it suggests that
preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic contributes a mora to the stressed
syllable (in parallel to South Argyll Gaelic, and in an echo of Ó Baoill
1980). We argue that the development from preaspiration to a moraic
segment is parallel to that hypothesized by Pétur Helgason (2002) for
Icelandic, and discuss the consequences of this analysis for the
question of internal vs external origin of preaspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound files are embedded in the handout: they can be played with Adobe Reader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ahrc</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/ahrc/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 19:42:04 BST</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/ahrc/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I have been invited to serve on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ahrc.ac.uk/peerreview/college&#34;&gt;AHRC Peer Review College&lt;/a&gt; from October 2015 through 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Irish isn’t ‘compromised’ — it just needs more support</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/irish-isnt-compromised-it-just-needs-more-support/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/irish-isnt-compromised-it-just-needs-more-support/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;There is a very interesting article now up on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sluggerotoole.com&#34;&gt;Slugger O&amp;rsquo;Toole&lt;/a&gt;, based around an interview with Dr &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.diarmuidjohnson.net&#34;&gt;Diarmuid Johnson&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://sluggerotoole.com/2015/07/26/do-urban-gaeltachts-produce-a-compromised-irish&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do urban Gaeltachts produce a compromised Irish?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Go read it now &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s well written and very well informed, especially if you compare it to the general level of debate around in the Irish language in Northern Ireland (as some &amp;mdash; though by no means all &amp;mdash; comments demonstrate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure &amp;mdash; I&amp;rsquo;m an admirer of Diarmuid Johnson, and I owe him a debt of gratitude for the kind assistance I received from him in the course of my own research in  West Wales. Nevertheless, I do think that Barton Creeth is on to something in the final paragraph, saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be many who argue Johnson’s purism about the language is
misplaced. [&amp;hellip;] What we have in Belfast, in terms of language
revival, is probably as good as it gets, and other minority language
activists can learn a lot from the Belfast experience. The hybrid,
urban, pidginised and creolised Irish of Belfast, Dublin, Derry and
other cities across Ireland is probably the future of the language,
and it likely means a new chapter in the history of the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s really jagging for me is the use of &amp;lsquo;compromised&amp;rsquo; to describe the non-traditional (&amp;lsquo;urban&amp;rsquo;) varieties of Irish. I suspect it starts out as an aesthetic judgement of someone very familiar with traditional Irish, but equally I suspect being perceived by many &amp;mdash; including those outside the &amp;lsquo;movement&amp;rsquo; &amp;mdash; as a value judgement. Indeed, in that same paragraph we find the burden of justification being laid squarely on the minority language users:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, parents and educators need to seriously think about
the source of Irish in Irish-medium education, and whether
Irish-medium education, in its current form, offers children the
best possible resources to fully develop intellectually and
emotionally. I’ll look forward to hearing the responses from people
who work in Irish Medium Education as well as from urban language
activists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest for a moment: would we be hearing these challenges to prove that bilingualism offers the &amp;lsquo;best possible resources&amp;rsquo; for the &amp;lsquo;full development&amp;rsquo; of children if the language in question were a &amp;lsquo;major world language&amp;rsquo; rather than a minority one with a history of political string attachment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that traditional varieties of Irish as spoken in the Gaeltacht are under severe pressure as it finds its position weakened as a community language. An increasing proportion of those who use Irish are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nspk.org.uk/&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;new speakers&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;, with relatively little access to traditional Irish as their input in language learning (as Johnson rightly points out). Indeed, some scholars, such as Dr &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dias.ie/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=576%3Adr-brian-o-curnain&amp;amp;catid=19%3Acelticstaff&amp;amp;Itemid=17&amp;amp;lang=en&#34;&gt;Brian Ó Curnáin&lt;/a&gt; at DIAS, have argued that the point of no return for traditional varieties of Irish is very close or already past, and &amp;lsquo;new-speaker&amp;rsquo; Irish is what we&amp;rsquo;re stuck with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New-speaker Irish is undoubtedly different from traditional Irish in many respects. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting, however, to look at how exactly it is different. For most people, I suspect, the most appalling sign of decline is the use of English borrowings (after all, for the average layperson, language equals vocabulary) and calques, as people complain about Gaelscoil kids saying things like &lt;em&gt;tá sin ag déanamh mo cheann isteach&lt;/em&gt;. But acquiring a language is, of course, much more than acquiring the words: it&amp;rsquo;s also about the grammatical structures and the different ways language is used in society. Some of the available research, such as that from Prof. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ulster.ac.uk/staff/am.henry.html&#34;&gt;Alison Henry&lt;/a&gt; at Ulster University (disclosure: a former colleague) has shown that to the extent learners in Irish-medium education do not attain the target state, this shows patterns associated not with some sort of terribly monstrous unnatural language but with the lack of sufficient input in an otherwise &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; acquisition context. Dr &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clairenance.co.uk&#34;&gt;Claire Nance&lt;/a&gt; has in her &lt;a href=&#34;http://theses.gla.ac.uk/4603/&#34;&gt;thesis&lt;/a&gt; shown how we can use our knowledge of the processes of language variation and change to look at the Gaelic spoken in Glasgow&amp;rsquo;s Gaelic-language school. The conclusion here, again, is that while these varieties are influenced by English, they still behave like real, living languages do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should like to emphasize that this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; some sort of professional &amp;lsquo;language-changes-deal-with-it&amp;rsquo; attitude that one sometimes has to adopt in the face of clueless pedantic hand-wringing about language. Of course, this is language change that happens in the social context of a majority-minority dynamic, so the adoption of new, English-influence norms might not necessarily be value-neutral. Nevertheless, I do find &amp;lsquo;new-speaker&amp;rsquo; Irish to be less objectionable than the idea that it might be somehow so inferior as not to merit any support at all. Of course it would be absolutely great if we could have a situation where urban Irish speakers have the opportunity to get enough input to acquire beautiful traditional Irish, but let&amp;rsquo;s face it &amp;mdash; neither polity on the island of Ireland has the political will to channel the kind of resources this would require. There is a lot that can &amp;mdash; and should &amp;mdash; be done to support the continued existence and future viability of traditional Irish-speaking communities, but to say that non-traditional varieties are little better than urban pidgins is, I think, counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is: abandoning these speakers massively narrows the base from which the future of the language can be built. As the western Gaeltachtaí shrink, seeing Irish as a Gaeltacht matter is putting it on a path to oblivion. The state can only dedicate resources to the language as long as it has some sort of duty of care towards its speakers. Once Irish goes the way of Latin in society, it goes the same way in terms of funding for arts, university teaching, research, and all the rest &amp;mdash; it becomes a niche pursuit. In this context it is mad to say that just because Dubliners use English words and much prefer &lt;em&gt;tá sé ina dhochtúir&lt;/em&gt; (if they&amp;rsquo;re lucky) to wrangling with the copula they aren&amp;rsquo;t really Irish speakers. It&amp;rsquo;s not just a tactical mistake if you&amp;rsquo;re  a language campaigner &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s just not the right thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that said, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; of course imperative that the teaching of Irish (as with any other language, and &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; a minority language) equip the learners with as much knowledge of the &amp;lsquo;target&amp;rsquo; variety as possible. This, of course, requires resources, which aren&amp;rsquo;t really forthcoming just now, but &amp;mdash; in an ideal world &amp;mdash; there would be a rethinking of how the language is taught. Diarmuid Jonhson is right to point out that the Gaeltacht simply can&amp;rsquo;t produce the numbers of native-speaker teachers &amp;mdash; teacher training in the future will inevitably have to deal with L2 speakers, so a focus on the quality of the language pedagogy there is absolutely vital. And &amp;mdash; here&amp;rsquo;s a bit of &lt;em&gt;pro domo sua&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; what is also sorely needed is a big programme of language documentation. To some extent, the teaching of Irish as a language has relied on the continuing availability of at least some L1 speakers in the profession. This has meant that the gap between language teaching and the linguistic study of the language &amp;mdash; as wide in Ireland as anywhere in the English-speaking world &amp;mdash; has not been at the top of people&amp;rsquo;s concerns. But we should be worried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; academic descriptions of Irish &amp;mdash; mostly done in the mid to late 20th century, in line with the linguistic theories prevalent then &amp;mdash; and there is a wealth of archival material, but there is so, so much more than can and should be done. Linguistic science has come on massively since then, and without taking anything at all away from the achievements of these scholars, to whom we owe an eternal debt for documenting the language, we are now in a position to ask questions that would just not occur back then. And these are the sort of questions that a teacher should be able to answer if they come up &amp;mdash; and when the teacher is not a &amp;lsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo; speaker, how are they going to do it? As a very small example, I&amp;rsquo;m now engaged in research (with Dr &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ucd.ie/research/people/irishcelstirishflling/drmairenichiosain/&#34;&gt;Máire Ní Chiosáin&lt;/a&gt; of University College Dublin, with thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.royalsoced.org.uk&#34;&gt;Royal Society of Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt; for funding) that, at bottom, addresses what you&amp;rsquo;d think was a fairly basic question &amp;mdash; how many vowels are there in Irish and Scottish Gaelic? The existing descriptions &amp;ndash; and some of them are truly excellent &amp;mdash; just don&amp;rsquo;t contain the sort of data that would allow us to answer this apparently innocuous question reliably. And don&amp;rsquo;t get me started on syntax, which for now an advanced learner can really only acquire by way of osmosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just one example of the disconnect between school- and even university-level pedagogy and linguistic research, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s really, really worrying in this minority-language context. My colleagues in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/schools-departments/literatures-languages-cultures/celtic-scottish-studies&#34;&gt;Celtic &amp;amp; Scottish Studies&lt;/a&gt;  here at Edinburgh hope to begin addressing this by including a linguistics component in their new degree in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/schools-departments/literatures-languages-cultures/celtic-scottish-studies/undergraduate/gaelic-and-primary-education/overview&#34;&gt;Gaelic and Primary Education&lt;/a&gt;, but this is only a start, and anyway there is just so much more of the actual research that needs done on these languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in any case, even this little self-serving rant aside, the phenomenon (I&amp;rsquo;m carefully avoiding saying &amp;lsquo;problem&amp;rsquo;) Diarmuid Johnson has identified is real enough: the education systems patently do not give the learners the amount of exposure to traditional varieties for them to be acquired reliably. This should, of course, be remedied &amp;mdash; it probably won&amp;rsquo;t any time soon, realistically, but one can always hope. But even if it isn&amp;rsquo;t, new-speaker Irish (or Gaelic, or Welsh, or your minority language of choice) is here to stay, and its speakers are friends to the language, not a blight on the landscape. Even if their Irish is imperfect by the high standards of the past, they deserve help and support.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Preaspiration and tonal accents as Northern Gaelic features</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic:-reconsidering-contact-origins/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic:-reconsidering-contact-origins/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I argue that the origin of both pitch accents and preaspiration in Gaelic is best understood in the context of a &amp;lsquo;Northern Gaelic&amp;rsquo; area covering Ulster and Scotland, as opposed to Connacht and Munster. Within this area, both preaspiration and pitch accents show the classic pattern of peripheral archaisms, with Lewis and West Ulster as remnant areas and Argyll as the most innovative zone. This suggests that the stronger Norse presence in the Hebrides does not correlate with a denser distribution of potential contact features, and thus the developments in both cases need not have been triggered by contact &amp;mdash; even though a reinforcing role for contact is very difficult (and probably undesirable) to exclude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handout is slightly more detailed than the slides. Note that the file is quite large because of the maps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ICCS</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/iccs/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/iccs/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic:-reconsidering-contact-origins/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pitch accent and preaspiration in Gaelic: Reconsidering contact origins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.celticstudiescongress.org&#34;&gt;15th International Congress of Celtic Studies&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Glasgow, Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>gregynog</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/gregynog/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/gregynog/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Free and not so free: Dialect variation and quantity-quality interactions in Welsh vowels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://privatewww.essex.ac.uk/~rborsley/wss/wss-22.htm&#34;&gt;22nd Welsh Linguistics Seminar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Free and not so free</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer an analysis of &amp;lsquo;length&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;tenseness&amp;rsquo; found in an acoustic study of eight speakers. The results confirm the existence of a categorical pattern whereby the quality of long mid vowels in penults depends on the phonological height of the following vowel (Awbery 1984, Wmffre 2003). One speaker shows a distribution of tenseness that categorically tracks length in penults, much as described in the literature and shown for monosyllables by Mayr &amp;amp; Davies (2011). Finally, one speaker shows a fairly robust duration distinction between &amp;lsquo;long&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;short&amp;rsquo; vowels but no qualitative distinction, consistently producing &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; vowels irrespective of phonological quantity. I suggest that this latter system is historically original (contrary to the suggestions of Wmffre 2003, who sees lax vowels in words like &lt;em&gt;cefn&lt;/em&gt; as a result of a lowering process, and of Rees 2013, who suggests that tensing of short vowels in penults precedes their lengthening). Finally, I offer a brief comparison of penults with unstressed vowels, which, contrary to descriptions, appear to show little continuous (or discrete variation), with non-trivial phonological consequences. Much of the presentation is similar to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/&#34;&gt;23mfm talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Welsh vowels presentation at the mfm</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/welsh-vowels/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/welsh-vowels/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quantity-quality interactions in Welsh vowels: Phonologization across dialects&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/mfm/23mfm.html&#34;&gt;23rd Manchester Phonology Meeting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Quantity-quality interactions in Welsh vowels</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I present the results of a phonetic study of the relationship between vowel quality and vowel quantity. The results confirm that the descriptions are correct in setting up a categorical distinction between two varieties of long mid vowels (tense [eː oː] and lax [ɛː ɔː]) in South-West Welsh. This system plausibly arose as the enhancement of a pattern where there is no quality distinctions between short and long vowels, with continuous variation in height in both prosodic contexts. The rise of the south-western pattern is connected to the phonologization of a trading relation in duration between the stressed penultimate and the final syllable, which is still attested in the relevant varieties. This presents an interesting example of &amp;lsquo;rule scattering&amp;rsquo; (Bermúdez-Otero 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handout is much more detailed than the slides. However, there is a rather embarrassing misinterpretation of the durational effect for the &amp;lsquo;non-enhanced&amp;rsquo; system. I&amp;rsquo;m leaving this unchanged in the interest of historical veracity, but see my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/&#34;&gt;Gregynog presentation&lt;/a&gt;, once it&amp;rsquo;s available, for the corrected version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I plan on releasing the data behind this presentation fairly soon &amp;mdash; check back later for a link.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Making Emacs hold your hand: don&#39;t edit a TeX file when you don&#39;t mean to</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/making-emacs-hold-your-hand-dont-edit-a-tex-file-when-you-dont-mean-to/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/making-emacs-hold-your-hand-dont-edit-a-tex-file-when-you-dont-mean-to/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;As a user of LaTeX, R and Emacs, I naturally write up my research in &lt;code&gt;.Rnw&lt;/code&gt; files, using &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name/knitr&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt; to produce &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; sources. With Emacs, this means I have access to both the awesome AUCTeX for writing LaTeX and the excellent ESS environment for the statistics at the same time. However, being the absent-minded academic that I am, I sometimes end up opening the woven &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file instead of the &lt;code&gt;.Rnw&lt;/code&gt; and make edits to that, which means it gets overwritten and lost the next time I run &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt;. This is suboptimal, but of course Emacs allows us to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be achieved by &lt;em&gt;advising&lt;/em&gt; the relevant function &amp;mdash; in this case &lt;code&gt;switch-to-buffer&lt;/code&gt;. The following bit of Elisp code will ask you when you&amp;rsquo;re trying to switch to a buffer with a &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file when there&amp;rsquo;s a corresponding &lt;code&gt;.Rnw&lt;/code&gt; file open at the some time. It&amp;rsquo;s not particularly robust (e.g. it doesn&amp;rsquo;t take cognizance of multiple buffers visiting files of the same name), but it gets the basic job done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-lisp&#34;&gt;        (defun tex-Rnw-check (name)
          &amp;quot;When opening a .tex file, check to make sure there isn&#39;t a
      corresponding .Rnw available, to make sure we don&#39;t try to edit
      the wrong file.&amp;quot;
          (when (and (bufferp name)
                     (buffer-file-name name))
            (let* ((rnw-file (format &amp;quot;%s.Rnw&amp;quot; (file-name-sans-extension (buffer-file-name name)))))
              (when (and (equal (file-name-extension (buffer-file-name name)) &amp;quot;tex&amp;quot;)
                         (member rnw-file (mapcar #&#39;buffer-file-name (buffer-list))))
                (if (yes-or-no-p &amp;quot;You are trying to open a .tex file, but the corresponding .Rnw file seems to be open. Are you sure?&amp;quot;)
                    name
                  (find-buffer-visiting rnw-file))))))
      
        (defadvice switch-to-buffer (around noweb-check activate)
          (let ((buffer-or-name (or (tex-Rnw-check (ad-get-arg 0))
                                    (ad-get-arg 0))))
            ad-do-it))
        (ad-update &#39;switch-to-buffer)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This uses the old &lt;code&gt;defadvice&lt;/code&gt; mechanism rather than the new &lt;code&gt;add-function&lt;/code&gt;, but seems to work well enough. (I&amp;rsquo;m stuck on Emacs 24.3, as later versions seems to have funky bugs with the display of some Unicode characters that I badly need.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>About my name</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/my-name/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/my-name/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My name is obviously problematic for English speakers (or indeed for Russian speakers), so I&amp;rsquo;m just putting this up for future reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Russian, my surname is Иосад, pronounced in Modern Standard Russian as something like [i.aˈsat] &amp;mdash; that&amp;rsquo;s two onsetless syllables in a row, plus final devoicing. English speakers rightly ignore the final devoicing, but the two first syllables can still be a problem. The suggested version for English speakers is [ˈjɔːsəd], with the vowel of &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sense, this is nothing but reverting to the historical origins of the name. It is originally Jewish, possibly deriving from Hebrew יסד, and pronounced with an initial [j]. In pre-Revolutionary Russia, &amp;lsquo;my&amp;rsquo; version of the name would have been written Iосадъ, because of the rule that prohibited writing any version of И (including Й, the expected spelling for [j]) before a vowel (see e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dotted_I_(Cyrillic&#34;&gt;this Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;). After the spelling reform which abolished I/i in Cyrillic, the name was automatically respelled as Иосад rather than the more correct Йосад. (The same fate befell the words for &lt;em&gt;ion&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;iodine&lt;/em&gt;, which are still spelt &lt;em&gt;ион&lt;/em&gt; and, occasionally, &lt;em&gt;иод&lt;/em&gt;, despite being pronounced with [j].) I suppose at some stage my family gave up on correcting people and adopted the spelling pronunciation. So, now you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/erschler/&#34;&gt;David Erschler&lt;/a&gt; for help with the Hebrew.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Representation and variation in substance-free phonology: A case study in Celtic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/thesis/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/thesis/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here you will find some material related to my PhD thesis entitled &lt;em&gt;Representation and variation in substance-free phonology&lt;/em&gt;, which I submitted to the University of Tromsø on 3rd August 2012 and which I successfully defended in a &lt;em&gt;viva voce&lt;/em&gt; examination on 18th February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The official version of the thesis can be downloaded from &lt;a href=&#34;http://munin.uit.no&#34;&gt;Munin&lt;/a&gt;, the University of Tromsø&amp;rsquo;s institutional repository, &lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/10037/4794&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can download the LaTeX source code for the thesis &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.anghyflawn.net/phd-thesis&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an &lt;a href=&#34;http://uit.no/ansatte/organisasjon/nyhetsartikkel?p_document_id=325183&amp;amp;p_dimension_id=88147&amp;amp;p_menu=28723&amp;amp;p_lang=2&#34;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; I did for the faculty&amp;rsquo;s web site (it is in Norwegian).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/pdf/viva.presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the handout for the short presentation of the thesis&amp;rsquo; main results that I had to do for the viva.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Norwegian doctoral defence is accompanied by a &amp;lsquo;trial lecture&amp;rsquo; (&lt;em&gt;prøveforelesning&lt;/em&gt;) on a topic of the committee&amp;rsquo;s choosing. &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/pdf/viva.lecture.pdf&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the handout for mine, entitled &lt;em&gt;Progress and problems in language revitalization: The Celtic languages&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
