<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Contrast in Phonology on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/contrast-in-phonology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Contrast in Phonology on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/contrast-in-phonology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
      <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
      <description>‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonologization of redundant contrasts and the Contrastivist Hypothesis</title>
      <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</guid>
      <description>I consider two cases of predictable distributions of phonological categories: &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; long vowels in South-West Welsh and the two varieties of the FACE vowel in Ulster English. Their predictable (&amp;lsquo;non-phonemic&amp;rsquo;) distribution is a challenge to the Contrastivist Hypothesis, but I argue that it can be accommodated if we assume that learning, including category formation, proceeds bottom-up, and that learners do not unlearn predictably distributed categories unless compelled to do so by alternations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonemicization vs. phonologization</title>
      <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</guid>
      <description>We consider the status of &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (really lenis) fricatives in Old English and in Brythonic Celtic. In the received view, they are not &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; in Old English, yet their distribution is clearly sensitive to phonological structure. We propose that they are distinct phonological symbols, coerced into predictable distributions by the phonological computation. We also offer a similar analysis for Brythonic Celtic. The situation is argued to result as a predictable consequence of the life cycle of phonological processes rather than from language contact, contra previous suggestions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
      <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge talk to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving segments, but instead features attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>