<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>English on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/english/</link>
    <description>Recent content in English on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/english/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in sonorant-consonant clusters in areal perspective</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in lC and rC clusters</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</guid>
      <description>The insertion of an unstressed vowel in lC and rC clusters of non-rising sonority (fil[ə]m), is widely known as characteristic of Irish English. It is frequently cited as a substrate feature carried over from Irish, where this process is productive (Ní Chiosáin 1999), as it is in the related Scottish Gaelic. However, this feature is also known from Older Scots, modern Scots dialects (Maguire 2017), and traditional varieties of English. Therefore, it might be an areal effect in the British and Irish Isles; notably, a similar phenomenon is also attested in Welsh (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonemicization vs. phonologization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</guid>
      <description>We consider the status of &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (really lenis) fricatives in Old English and in Brythonic Celtic. In the received view, they are not &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; in Old English, yet their distribution is clearly sensitive to phonological structure. We propose that they are distinct phonological symbols, coerced into predictable distributions by the phonological computation. We also offer a similar analysis for Brythonic Celtic. The situation is argued to result as a predictable consequence of the life cycle of phonological processes rather than from language contact, contra previous suggestions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
