<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>English in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="http://anghyflawn.github.io//img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/english/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 19:59:38 BST</updated>



<item>
<title>Celtic, Norse, and English in contact</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/celtic-norse-english/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2016/celtic-norse-english/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course runs for the first time in &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt; (but will probably run every other year). It has three main objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An introduction to Celtic linguistics, via familiarizing students with the structural properties of Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An brief introduction to the study of language contact, with particular attention to criteria used to diagnose contact features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A discussion of various ways in which Celtic and North Germanic languages interacted with each other and with English in the British Isles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course presupposes &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; knowledge of any modern or ancient Celtic language. However, it is also open to students pursuing Honours degrees in Celtic, as long as they have passed one of the second-year Gaelic courses &amp;mdash; while some of the linguistic concepts may require a bit of effort (especially if you haven&amp;rsquo;t taken at least LEL1 in pre-Honours), much of the language material will be familiar or sufficiently similar to Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check this page later for a course handbook. In the meantime, here is a preliminary weekly plan (subject to change with extreme prejudice):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction and the historical setting

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic and the Anglo-Saxon conquest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic and English in the Middle Ages. The Norse presence in England, Scotlad, and Ireland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Language shift. &amp;lsquo;Celtic Englishes&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Old Irish. Modern Irish phonology and morphosyntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Scottish Gaelic. Middle Welsh. Modern Welsh phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic language structures: Modern Welsh morphosyntax. Cornish and Breton. An introduction to language contact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sociolinguistic complexity and types of language contact. Diagnosing historical contact. Class test (worth 30% of the mark)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Celtic hypothesis: was Early English influenced by Celtic?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact with Norse: North Germanic and English. The Norse influence and Gaelic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic Englishes: Irish English. Scotland.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic Englishes: Welsh English. Cornwall and Brittany. Summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining 70% of the mark will be assessed by a final essay of 3,000 words, to be written between the end of teaching and the start of the exam period.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2015/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2015/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to a range of important topics in (generative) phonological theory and to phonological data analysis. On the theoretical side, we will cover the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of phonological theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivations, underlying representations, rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process interaction and rule ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suprasegmental phonology: syllable structure, stress, tone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced feature theory: feature geometry, unary features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constraints in phonology: well-formedness conditions, templates, conspiracies, the &amp;lsquo;duplication problem&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explanation in phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, there is a strong emphasis on building data analysis and problem solving skills. Click &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/phonological-theory/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for last year&amp;rsquo;s course handbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this course, students will be able to progress to advanced study of phonological theory. In &lt;sup&gt;2015&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2016&lt;/sub&gt;, we will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be offering LASC10089 Current Issues in Phonology, but it is planned that this will run in the second semester of &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;. Get in touch early with prospective supervisors if you&amp;rsquo;re thinking about an Honours dissertation in phonology in &lt;sup&gt;2016&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2017&lt;/sub&gt;, because it is likely you&amp;rsquo;ll need to do some summer reading. Conversely, LASC10046 Historical Phonology &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; running this year, but not next year. Plan accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>frlsu</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/frlsu/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/frlsu/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I will present our &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/&#34;&gt;joint work on Argyll Gaelic preaspiration&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/people/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; at the conference of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.frlsu.org&#34;&gt;Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster&lt;/a&gt; (University of the West of Scotland, Ayr).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic and its contribution to prosodic structure</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper reports the preliminary results of an acoustic study of
preaspiration in the Gaelic of North Argyll. Existing descriptions
identify this area as reflecting Old Irish and Old Norse &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo;
geminates as [xp xt xk] clusters (&amp;lsquo;pre-affricates&amp;rsquo;), but, to our
knowledge, no targeted acoustic study of these varieties had been
performed to date. Our results confirm that the preaspiration found in
other varieties corresponds to dorsal (velar or uvular) frication in
North Argyll, rather than other conceivable interpretations of the
impressionistic descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discuss the broader repercussions of these findings regarding the
nature of preaspiration in these varieties. In particular, we find only
very scant evidence of pre-frication after long vowels (in words like
&lt;em&gt;pàpa&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;Pope&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;bàta&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;boat&amp;rsquo;), which contrasts with regular
pre-frication after short vowels. This apparent neutralization of
laryngeal contrast outside the initial foot suggests that (at least
Argyll) Gaelic shows a weakly unconditioned reduction process (lenition;
Honeybone 2012) similar to languages such as English or
Icelandic. Further, if this analysis is correct, it suggests that
preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic contributes a mora to the stressed
syllable (in parallel to South Argyll Gaelic, and in an echo of Ó Baoill
1980). We argue that the development from preaspiration to a moraic
segment is parallel to that hypothesized by Pétur Helgason (2002) for
Icelandic, and discuss the consequences of this analysis for the
question of internal vs external origin of preaspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Pitch accent and preaspiration in Gaelic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I will argue in this talk that the origin of both pitch accents and preaspiration in Gaelic is best understood in the context of a &amp;lsquo;Northern Gaelic&amp;rsquo; area covering Ulster and Scotland, as opposed to Connacht and Munster. Within this area, both preaspiration and pitch accents show the classic pattern of peripheral archaisms, with Lewis and West Ulster as remnant areas and Argyll (in particular North Argyll) as the most innovative zone. This strongly suggests that the stronger Norse presence in the Hebrides does not correlate with a denser distribution of potential contact features, and thus the developments in both cases need not have been triggered by contact &amp;mdash; even though a reinforcing role for contact is very difficult (and probably undesirable) to exclude.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ICCS</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/iccs/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/iccs/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I will present &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pitch accent and preaspiration in Gaelic: Reconsidering contact origins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.celticstudiescongress.org&#34;&gt;15th International Congress of Celtic Studies&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Glasgow, Scotland.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Why teach the kids Gaelic if you can teach them Mandarin?</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/why-teach-the-kids-gaelic-if-you-can-teach-them-mandarin/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/ocp4/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Лексикализованные вершины в валлийском синтаксисе</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I attempt to extend Nigel Duffield&amp;rsquo;s idea of &amp;lsquo;lexicalized heads&amp;rsquo; playing a rôle in the triggering of initial mutations, originally proposed for Irish, to Welsh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Initial consonant mutation and information flow in Mende</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/ocp5/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/ocp5/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I reanalyse the pattern of initial consonant mutation in Mende by arguing that the so-called &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade, usually assumed to be the derive one, is the default case morphosyntactically, and thus that the consonant mutation mechanism must derive the &amp;lsquo;strong&amp;rsquo; rather than the &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade. This is problematic for autosegmental, or probably any purely phonological, accounts of mutation, since the relationship between the weak and strong grades is one-to-many, so I suggest the choice between the two grades is made outside of phonology, with direct reference to the morphosyntax.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Liquids and spirants</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here, I consider some cases of fricatives phonologically patterning with liquids, and argue that this phenomenon is merely the extension of the well-known cross-linguistic diversity in the representation of the former. I interpret this as providing support for substance-free representations with a non-trivial phonology-phonetics mapping. I provide a concrete analysis of initial mutations involving sonorants in Scottish Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>All that glistens is not gold</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I argue that purely phonological (e.g. autosegmental) approaches to initial consonant mutations in languages such as Fula and Irish are insufficient to account for the facts fully. In many ways this does not represent my current thinking on these matters, as can be established by looking, for instance, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-mutation/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Too many levels, too few solutions</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/16mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/16mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk is largely of historic interest, superseded in particular by &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt;, also at the mfm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Fonetikk versus fonologi</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Dette er det fyrste føredraget i prosjektet om russisk vokalreduksjon. Sluttversjonen kan ein finne i &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/&#34;&gt;denne artikkelen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>







<item>
<title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>











<item>
<title>Structure versus prominence</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I propose an analysis of the stress system of Munster Irish, which evinces a disruption of normal directionality only in words with two initial heavy syllables. The analysis relies on recursion of subsyllable constituents and on a formal distinction between &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;head status&amp;rsquo;. The full version of the analysis can be found in &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Russian palatalization</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk we argue that the traditional view of vowel-driven palatalization in Russian is inadequate, at least for two reasons. First, it relies on a six-vowel interpretation of the Russian inventory that is not adequate from a phonetic perspective. Second, and more importantly, it undergenerates the range of alternations found in Modern Standard Russian. Instead, we argue that palatalization must be driven by a floating feature attached to the left edge of suffixes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Right at the left edge</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/rara/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/rara/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I offer an overview of systems of initial consonant mutations found in the world&amp;rsquo;s languages and attempt to propose a preliminary typology. Many of these phenomena can probably be subsumed under a general theory of nonconcatenative morphology and phonology, but in some cases (notably some of the Celtic ones) the mutations&amp;rsquo; place in the grammar is less clear. For another, more detailed take on this architectural issue in the specific case of Breton, see also &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-mutation/&#34;&gt;this later paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Feature geometry meets contrastive specification</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I propose an analysis of the interaction between vowel lengthening before voiced obstruents and final devoicing in two languages: Friulian and Breton. I argue that such interactions are transparent and involve a three-way laryngeal contrast formalized geometrically, with true voiceless obstruents the most structurally complex and devoiced ones least. The Friulian analysis was later published &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and the Breton was largely incorporated into the thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>How good is the internal evidence for multiple-level phonological computation? A view from Russian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Relying in part on the analysis of palatalization offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I argue that Russian does not provide strong &lt;em&gt;phonology-internal&lt;/em&gt; evidence for level ordering, contra suggestions by authors such as Morris Halle and Jerzy Rubach. A more focused argument to the same effect is offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A bad case of excessive computation</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I use the analysis of palatalization in Modern Standard Russian offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to argue that these data do not provide a watertight argument for multilevel phonological computation, and that phonological analysis must be combined with a theory of ordering (such as Stratal OT) if the hypothesis of parallel computation is to be challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in the north of Italy</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk presents in detail the analysis of Friulian also given at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/&#34;&gt;18th mfm&lt;/a&gt; and later published &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Explaning licensing mismatches in Welsh</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I propose a new analysis of so-called &amp;lsquo;vowel mutation&amp;rsquo; in Welsh, whereby final syllables (both stressed and unstressed) only allow a reduced inventory (by disallowing [ə]). I argue that these final syllables are specified with something like a suprasegmental feature that triggers a feature co-occurrence effect, and that there is no need for recourse to a mechanism of metrical prominence akin to that borne by stressed syllables (as previously suggested in the literature). (A fuller version of the analysis can be found in the thesis.) The argument also stresses the need for a distinction between metrical headship and prominence features such as stress (see also &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I consider the nature of the so-called &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic and argue that the contrast is one of metrical structure rather than lexical tone, at least diachronically, and probably also synchronically. This means that they can be reconstructed with an internal origin, and no recourse to contact with North Germanic is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to account for their appearance. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; has the analysis in detail, and the historical argument is expounded in some detail in later talks &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/&#34;&gt;Toronto presentation&lt;/a&gt; and to a certain extent my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/&#34;&gt;talk from the 6th CLC&lt;/a&gt;). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration. I argue that the tight connection between phonological contrast and phonetic representation proposed by laryngeal realism isn&amp;rsquo;t correct in any case, so this mismatch is not a major problem for the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Deconstructing mutation in Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer the analysis of Breton initial mutations found in my thesis. I argue that there is no such thing as a unified &amp;lsquo;mutation&amp;rsquo; mechanism: instead, this labels covers a variety of processes with different places in the overall grammar. The article-length version of the argument is &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-mutation/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A unified account of the behaviour of high vowels in Bothoa Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer an analysis of gliding in Bothoa Breton, as presented in the thesis. I argue that high vowels (especially [i]) either become glides or coalesce with a preceding consonant, in order to avoid hiatus. However, this pattern is disrupted if the high vowel becomes a nucleus at an earlier stage in the cyclic derivation. This provides an argument for stratal models of phonology-morphology interactions, and a strong argument &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; Output-Output Correspondence, because some of the exceptional non-gliding cases cannot be explained by reference to a free-standing form with transparent non-gliding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here, I propose an analysis of the interacting between final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian (and other related varieties of northern Italy). Historically, stressed vowels lengthen before voiced obstruents, but this is opacified by final devoicing. I capitalize on phonetic studies showing final devoicing in the language to be incomplete and argue that the process is not in fact opaque: devoicing does not involve neutralization but instead the creation of a third, laryngealy unspecified class of obstruents. I also observe that the distribution of moraicity in Friulian presents a challenge to accepted theories of weight assignment, and propose an analysis that relies on language-specific featural representations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>In defence of Richness of the Base</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I briefly present the analysis of mora assignment to consonants in South Welsh. The pattern can be analysed by appeal to the form of the inputs (i.e. with a massive number of accidental gaps, which is undesirable), or by positing a constraint schema with undesirable consequences for factorial typology. I suggest that the latter solution is preferable theoretically, although it may be premature to choose it for that reason alone.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>The phonological endgame</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I present an analysis of Welsh &amp;lsquo;svarabhakti&amp;rsquo;, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (&lt;em&gt;pwdr&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]). This pattern is said to coexist with a pattern of deleting consonants in such clusters in polysyllables (&lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has been argued that the two differing outcomes can be reconciled by appeal to a single constraint on the form of feet. I show that this analysis is not tenable for South Welsh, and propose that deletion (as in &lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt;) is not part of the phonological grammar (at least in South Welsh).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Glottal stop insertion in Scottish Gaelic and contrastive syllabification</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Gaelic dialects, mostly in Argyll, show a process of glottal stop epenthesis in stressed light syllables. This has been analysed as a stress-to-weight effect, and I review the evidence to show that this analysis is likely correct, and also that glottal stop insertion is a live phonological process rather than a lexicalized artefact of history. If this is correct, Argyll Gaelic shows an example of lexical storage of syllable structure, sometimes argued to be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge&lt;/em&gt; talk&lt;/a&gt; to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving &lt;em&gt;segments&lt;/em&gt;, but instead &lt;em&gt;features&lt;/em&gt; attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonemicization vs. phonologization</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We consider the status of &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (really lenis) fricatives in Old English and in Brythonic Celtic. In the received view, they are not &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; in Old English, yet their distribution is clearly sensitive to phonological structure. We propose that they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; distinct phonological symbols, coerced into predictable distributions by the phonological computation. We also offer a similar analysis for Brythonic Celtic. The situation is argued to result as a predictable consequence of the life cycle of phonological processes rather than from language contact, &lt;em&gt;contra&lt;/em&gt; previous suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Head-dependent asymmetries in Munster Irish prosody</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose an analysis of stress in Munster Irish which builds on two important premises. First, I argue for a distinction between the notion &amp;lsquo;head of a constituent&amp;rsquo; and the notion of &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo;: these are separate entities, and the typologically frequent isomorphic distribution of the two is just one possible outcome of the phonological computation. Second, I propose to employ a particular family of constraints requiring head-dependent asymmetries (Dresher and van der Hulst 1998) to account for the mismatch between the placement of foot heads and stress in Munster Irish. Overall, the paper is an argument for elaborate abstract structure as an explanatory factor in phonology, as opposed to relatively shallow, substance-based representations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Honours Foundation: Phonology and Phonetics</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2013/hfpp/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2013/hfpp/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course was an introduction to phonological theory and to laboratory phonology &amp;mdash; the use of phonetic evidence to answer theoretical phonological questions. I was responsible for the morphophonology portion of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course has now been discontinued. LEL Honours students interested in these topics may look at LASC10088 &lt;em&gt;Phonological Theory&lt;/em&gt; and/or LASC10090 &lt;em&gt;Phonetics and Laboratory Phonology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Minority languages, microvariation, minimalism and meaning</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/infl-book/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/infl-book/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This books is a collection of papers presented at the inaugural conference of the Irish Network in Formal Linguistics. To see the table of contents and the editors&amp;rsquo; introduction, go &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cambridgescholars.com/download/sample/59622&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-linguistic variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2013&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2014&lt;/sub&gt;, I was responsible for most of the phonology block. We covered the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and theory. Universals in phonology; descriptive and analytic universals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universals of inventory organization; feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syllable structure. Typology of syllable structures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimality Theory and its application to syllable structure typology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government Phonology; restrictiveness in theory-building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress; metrical typology; metrical typology in OT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2e/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2e/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is (optionally) a part of the pre-Honours sequence in the Linguistics undergraduate degree (but can of course be taken as an outside course). In &lt;sup&gt;2013&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2014&lt;/sub&gt;, I was responsible for the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in the phonology of European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
