<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Laryngeal phonology on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Laryngeal phonology on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/laryngeal-phonology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The life cycle of preaspiration in the Gaelic languages</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/frlsu-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/frlsu-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>This paper is a written-up version of my presentation at the 2018 conference of the Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster.
In this paper I propose (yet another) reappraisal of the arguments regarding the relationship between Norse and Gaelic in the North Atlantic world, focusing on the development of preaspiration. There is significant controversy in the literature as to whether this feature, along with others such as tonal accent, represents Norse influence on Gaelic (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drift revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/eshp4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/eshp4/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I offer a framework for understanding convergent diachronic developments in the phonological systems of unrelated languages, informed by the life cycle of phonological processes. I focus on preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the traditional /p t k/ series) in several languages of north-western Europe that are either unrelated, or not related closely enough for preaspiration to be inherited: they include the North Germanic languages, varieties of English, the Gaelic languages, Welsh, and the Sámi languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspirasjon i norsk i nye og gamle kjelder</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gjert-kristoffersen-fs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gjert-kristoffersen-fs/</guid>
      <description>This paper (in Norwegian) contains an overview of traditional and modern sources of information regarding preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the /p t k/ series) in Norwegian vernaculars. Traditional sources note them in the dialects of North Gudbrandsdalen, Härjedalen, Rogaland, and a few in Northern Norway. However, I argue that preaspiration is much more widespread than that: I collect evidence from more recent instrumental studies, from dialect corpora, and from an original acoustic study with a focus on Northern Norwegian varieties, and argue, following scholars such as Gunnar Ólafur Hansson and Pétur Helgason, that preaspiration is pervasive in North Germanic vernaculars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation and (presumed) change in Norwegian preaspiration</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/ucl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/ucl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can language areas arise by drift?</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/stirling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/stirling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The influence of Norse on Scottish Gaelic, 85 years on</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/frlsu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/frlsu/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose (yet another) reappraisal of the arguments regarding the relationship between Norse and Gaelic in the North Atlantic world, focusing on the development of preaspiration. There is significant controversy in the literature as to whether this feature, along with others such as tonal accent, represents Norse influence on Gaelic (e.g. Marstrander 1932; Borgstrøm 1974; Gunnar Ólafur Hansson 2001), an independent development in Gaelic (e.g. Ó Baoill 1980; Ó Murchú 1985; Ó Maolalaigh 2010), or even Gaelic influence on Norse (McKenna 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norwegian preaspiration in traditional and modern sources</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/fgls/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/fgls/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I survey traditional descriptions of Norwegian dialects with particular attention to their discussion of voiceless stop preaspiration, and conclude that it is highly probable preaspiration has been consistently under-reported in these sources. As surveyed in detail by Pétur Helgason (2002), preaspiration in Norwegian has been reported most prominently for northern Gudbrandsdalen (Ross 1907; Horne 1917), Rogaland (Oftedal 1947; Wolter 1965), and for Senja by Iversen (1913). To Helgason’s list should be added Vestvågøya (Elstad 1982) and contact varieties in Northern Norway (Jahr 2008).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pre-sonorant voicing and language contact</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/</guid>
      <description>I draw attention to the fact that whilst pre-sonorant voicing of fricatives across a word boundary appears to be fairly widely spread (at least in Europe), pre-sonorant voicing of all obstruents appears to cluster in areas where &amp;lsquo;aspirating&amp;rsquo; languages are in contact with &amp;lsquo;voice&amp;rsquo; languages: the languages involved are Breton (Celtic/Gallo-Romance), Franconian/Netherlandic (e.g. Limburg Dutch, Luxembourgish), Western Polish and Slovak (Slavic/Germanic).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microvariation in laryngeal realism</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I consider the range of microvariation in the expression of laryngeal contrast, focusing on (voiceless) preaspiration in North Germanic. On the basis of an acoustic study, I suggest that both the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization have been under-reported in existing descriptions. This, in turn, has important consequences for our understanding of the phonology of laryngeal contrast. Specifically, I argue that the observed variation in laryngeal phenomena is incompatible with a version of &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; that produces inferences about phonological specifications on the basis of phonetic implementation; instead, I advocate a more abstract approach that gives primacy to phonological behaviour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation in North Germanic preaspiration</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</guid>
      <description>I consider the extent of cross-dialectal variation in the expression of laryngeal contrast within North Germanic, with a focus on (voiceless) preaspiration, and suggest that the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization across the North Germanic area have been significantly under-reported in the past.
As discussed by Pétur Helgason (2002), whilst preaspiration and sonorant devoicing in Insular Nordic have long been recognized by the scholarship, their distribution and behaviour in mainland varieties have been less well understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic and its contribution to prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports the preliminary results of an acoustic study of preaspiration in the Gaelic of North Argyll. Existing descriptions identify this area as reflecting Old Irish and Old Norse &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; geminates as [xp xt xk] clusters (&amp;lsquo;pre-affricates&amp;rsquo;), but, to our knowledge, no targeted acoustic study of these varieties had been performed to date. Our results confirm that the preaspiration found in other varieties corresponds to dorsal (velar or uvular) frication in North Argyll, rather than other conceivable interpretations of the impressionistic descriptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonemicization vs. phonologization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</guid>
      <description>We consider the status of &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (really lenis) fricatives in Old English and in Brythonic Celtic. In the received view, they are not &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; in Old English, yet their distribution is clearly sensitive to phonological structure. We propose that they are distinct phonological symbols, coerced into predictable distributions by the phonological computation. We also offer a similar analysis for Brythonic Celtic. The situation is argued to result as a predictable consequence of the life cycle of phonological processes rather than from language contact, contra previous suggestions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</guid>
      <description>Here, I propose an analysis of the interacting between final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian (and other related varieties of northern Italy). Historically, stressed vowels lengthen before voiced obstruents, but this is opacified by final devoicing. I capitalize on phonetic studies showing final devoicing in the language to be incomplete and argue that the process is not in fact opaque: devoicing does not involve neutralization but instead the creation of a third, laryngealy unspecified class of obstruents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my Toronto presentation and to a certain extent my talk from the 6th CLC). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in the north of Italy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents in detail the analysis of Friulian also given at the 18th mfm and later published here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started here. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature geometry meets contrastive specification</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the interaction between vowel lengthening before voiced obstruents and final devoicing in two languages: Friulian and Breton. I argue that such interactions are transparent and involve a three-way laryngeal contrast formalized geometrically, with true voiceless obstruents the most structurally complex and devoiced ones least. The Friulian analysis was later published here and the Breton was largely incorporated into the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
      <description>This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see this talk and this paper). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brythonic ‘second lenition’ revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I evaluate the arguments for two competing reconstructions regarding the laryngeal phonology of Proto-Brythonic. I defend the &amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo; interpretation which underplays the role of a &amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo; contrast and instead relies on two separate lenition processes (due to authors such as David Greene and Patrick Sims-Williams), against the &amp;lsquo;classical&amp;rsquo; one due to Kenneth Jackson and defended by John Koch and Graham Isaac, which emphasizes the rôle of aspiration in Proto-Brythonic &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; stops.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>