<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Pavel Iosad in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="https://anghyflawn.github.io/img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 22:02:47 BST</updated>



<item>
<title>Teachings</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Pavel Iosad</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to a range of important topics in (generative) phonological theory and to phonological data analysis. On the theoretical side, we cover the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of phonological theory: contrast, phonemes, allophones, alternations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivations, underlying representations, rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process interaction and rule ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suprasegmental phonology: syllable structure, stress, tone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced feature theory: feature geometry, unary features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explanation in phonology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, there is a strong emphasis on building data analysis and problem solving skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is also offered for MSc students (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/18-19/dpt/cxlasc11148.htm&#34;&gt;LASC11148&lt;/a&gt;). It is suitable for postgraduate students who have had some previous exposure to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this course, students will be able to progress to advanced study of phonological theory. In &lt;sup&gt;2018&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, we are offering LASC10046 Historical Phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Linguistics and English Language 1A</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel1a/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel1a/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the introductory linguistics &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; course for all first-year students in Linguistics and English Language. With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/graeme-trousdale&#34;&gt;Graeme Trousdale&lt;/a&gt;, I am responsible for the data analysis/language puzzles component of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic Linguistics</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/celtic-linguistics/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/celtic-linguistics/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course offers students a broad introduction to linguistics of the Celtic languages, one of the two main language groupings in the British and Irish Isles. The focus is on structural topics and engagement with the language material. We cover the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The place of Celtic in the Indo-European family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External history of the Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structural properties of the Celtic languages, in both their modern and medieval attestations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in linguistic theory for which the Celtic languages furnish valuable material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course is also offered to MSc students, as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/18-19/dpt/cxlasc11153.htm&#34;&gt;LASC11153&lt;/a&gt;, usually if they are able to pass out of introductory structure courses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>News</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 21:49:56 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teaching</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 21:49:56 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In Semester 1 of &lt;sup&gt;2018&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2019&lt;/sub&gt;, I am teaching Honours/MSc courses in &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/phonological-theory/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phonological Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/celtic-linguistics/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Celtic Linguistics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and run the data analysis component of &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel1a/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linguistics and English Language 1A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. My guidance and feedback hour this semester is 13:00&amp;ndash;15:00 on Thursdays.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Talks</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/talks/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/talks/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I  presented &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/rnag/&#34;&gt;A metrical analysis of Scottish Gaelic tonal accent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/literatures-languages-cultures/celtic-scottish-studies/conf/rannsachadh-na-gaidhlig-2018&#34;&gt;Rannsachadh na Gàidhlig 2018&lt;/a&gt;), and (co-authored with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/~wmaguire/&#34;&gt;Warren Maguire&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/icehl/&#34;&gt;English epenthesis in lC and rC clusters: Areal effect or drift?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.conferences.cahss.ed.ac.uk/icehl20/&#34;&gt;ICEHL XX&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Scottish Gaelic</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/scottish-gaelic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/scottish-gaelic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Prosody</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/prosody/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/prosody/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Presentations</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Germanic</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/germanic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/germanic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>English</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/english/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/english/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/celtic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/celtic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>English epenthesis in lC and rC clusters</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/icehl/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/icehl/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The insertion of an unstressed vowel in &lt;em&gt;lC&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;rC&lt;/em&gt; clusters of non-rising sonority (&lt;em&gt;fil[ə]m&lt;/em&gt;), is widely known as characteristic of Irish English. It is frequently cited as a substrate feature carried over from Irish, where this process is productive (Ní Chiosáin 1999), as it is in the related Scottish Gaelic. However, this feature is also known from Older Scots, modern Scots dialects (Maguire 2017), and traditional varieties of English. Therefore, it might be an areal effect in the British and Irish Isles; notably, a similar phenomenon is also attested in Welsh (e. g. Schumacher 2011, Iosad 2017)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reconsider whether areality best explains the prevalence of epenthesis in English. Epenthesis in various rC and lC clusters recurs throughout the history of English: Luick (1914) identifies two separate sound changes involving this epenthesis in Old English, with a third one in Middle English (Jordan 1934), all with different trigger contexts and patterns of quality of the epenthetic vowel. In fact, epenthesis in such clusters is extremely common across West Germanic (cf. Howell &amp;amp; Somers Wicka 2007): it is attested in Old High German (Reutercrona 1920, Braune 2004) and retained in Middle High German (Michels 1979) and many modern dialects (Schirmunski 1962); in Old, Middle, and Modern Dutch (van Loey 1976, Warner et al. 2001), and in Frisian (Steller 1928, Visser 2017). Epenthesis appears rarely in ancient North Germanic, but is widely attested at least in Danish dialects (Hansen 1962). Common to Germanic epenthesis patterns are a diversity of affected clusters and qualities of inserted vowel, a lack of regularity of epenthesis as a sound change, and erosion over time due to syncope processes targeting both epenthetic and original vowels. This makes it clear they cannot all be inherited from a single sound change in the protolanguage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We argue that parallel developments of post-sonorant epenthesis across (at least West) Germanic represent an instance of drift arising from variation at an earlier stage (e. g. Joseph 2013). The recurring epenthesis ‘events’ are not separate, but instead are best seen as attestations of a variable phenomenon always present to some extent in the West Germanic languages. This makes them distinct from exceptionless excrescence, which arises from retiming of vocalic gestures (Hall 2006), as attested in Scottish Gaelic and in the Sámi languages. We argue that these differences undermine the case for epenthesis as an areal feature in the British and Irish Isles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A metrical analysis of Scottish Gaelic tonal accent</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/rnag/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/rnag/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I provide a new analysis of the ‘tonal accent’ opposition in Gaelic, conceptualizing it as involving lexically specified metrical — in particular foot — structure. As discussed among others by Ternes (1980, 2006), many Gaelic varieties use suprasegmental features such as pitch (e.g. Lewis, Wester Ross) or glottalization (e.g. Jura, Colonsay) to make two kinds of distinctions: disyllabic hiatus vs. heavy syllables (&lt;em&gt;àth&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;atha&lt;/em&gt;); and disyllabic vs. svarabhakti words (&lt;em&gt;balg&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;balach&lt;/em&gt;). Ternes rightly compares these patterns with tonal accent systems in Germanic, and postulates lexical tone as the key distinction between the two ‘accents’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-tonal analyses have been proposed by authors such as Bosch &amp;amp; de Jong (1997); Smith (1999); Brown (2009); Iosad (2015). In particular, Smith and Iosad offer analyses where the svarabhakti vowel in words like balg is metrically invisible, with consequences for the patterning of tone and glottalization. However, this analysis can only work if svarabhakti vowels are fully predictable synchronically. In this simple form, the analysis is untenable: svarabhakti vowels may be absent in contexts where they are phonologically motivated (e.g. [x] representing preaspiration of [k] does not trigger svarabhakti &lt;em&gt;olc&lt;/em&gt; [ɔɫxk], *[ɔɫɔxk]), and conversely svarabhakti-related suprasegmental patterns can appear when they are synchronically unmotivated (e.g. [faɫa.i], [mara.i] with ‘monosyllabic’ accent for &lt;em&gt;falbhaidh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;marbhaidh&lt;/em&gt;). Similar counterexampels can be adduced for glottalization: compare [marəv] for marbh with svarabhakti-induced lack of glottalization but [marɪç] &lt;em&gt;marbhaidh&lt;/em&gt; where the lack of [ʔ] cannot be so explained. Building on recent work in the analysis of tonal accents (e.g. Morén-Duolljá 2013, Köhnlein 2016, Iosad 2016, Kehrein 2017), in this paper I show how these problems can be resolved if both glottalization and tonal accents in Scottish Gaelic are analysed using lexically pre-specified foot structure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Frlsu Presentation</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/frlsu-presentation/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 09:57:41 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/frlsu-presentation/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;em&gt;The Norse influence on Scottish Gaelic, 85 years on&lt;/em&gt;  at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://frlsu.org/frlsu-programme/&#34;&gt;12th conference of the Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster&lt;/a&gt;. Get the slides and handout &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/frlsu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Laryngeal Phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Language Contact</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/language-contact/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/language-contact/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The influence of Norse on Scottish Gaelic, 85 years on</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/frlsu/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/frlsu/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose (yet another) reappraisal of the arguments
regarding the relationship between Norse and Gaelic in the North
Atlantic world, focusing on the development of preaspiration. There is
significant controversy in the literature as to whether this feature,
along with others such as tonal accent, represents Norse influence on
Gaelic (e.g. Marstrander 1932; Borgstrøm 1974; Gunnar Ólafur Hansson
2001), an independent development in Gaelic (e.g. Ó Baoill 1980; Ó
Murchú 1985; Ó Maolalaigh 2010), or even Gaelic influence on Norse
(McKenna 2013). With recent advances in our understanding of how the
social context of contact influences its linguistic outcomes (e.g.
Thomason &amp;amp; Kaufman 1988; Trudgill 2011; Millar 2016), the debate around
the role of language contact in the development of Gaelic varieties has
begun to acquire a more solid theoretical underpinning; see in
particular Stewart (2004); Lindqvist (2015) and most recently Lewin
(2017).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I offer an account of the development of preaspiration combining these
sociolinguistic insights with the theory of the life cycle of
phonological processes (e.g. Bermúdez-Otero 2007; 2015; Bermúdez-Otero &amp;amp;
Trousdale 2012). I argue that this theory offers a useful diagnostic for
historical language contact, since discontinuities in the life cycle can
only be contact-induced. I propose a model of the development of Gaelic
preaspiration consistent with the life cycle model, starting with
variable preaspiration, arguing that variable preaspiration is a
pan-Gaelic phenomenon under-reported in traditional sources. Under this
analysis, the rise of categorical preaspiration is a Northern Gaelic
innovation (cf. Clayton 2010), centred on Argyll. With this linguistic
argument in hand, I argue that a Norse origin for this feature is
unlikely to be compatible with what we know about the sociolinguistic
context of the (re-)Gaelicization of Argyll (Jennings &amp;amp; Kruse (2009a);
(2009b); Clancy (2011); Whyte (2017), &lt;em&gt;pace&lt;/em&gt; Macniven (2015)).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>History of Phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I have a uploaded a revised draft of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/history-of-phonology/&#34;&gt;paper on phonology in the Soviet Union&lt;/a&gt; for the forthcoming &lt;em&gt;Oxford History of Phonology&lt;/em&gt;. Comments welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Writings</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>History of Phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonology in the Soviet Union</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This invited contribution to a collection on the history of phonology explores the history of phonological studies in the USSR. I offer a short history of phonology in Russia and the USSR before the formation of the two main theoretical currents (the &amp;lsquo;Leningrad&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Moscow&amp;rsquo; schools), and emphasize both their mutual common roots and their closeness to other structuralist frameworks, in particular Prague phonology. I discuss the differences between the two schools both in their approach to the phoneme and in their analysis of morphophonological alternations. Throughout, the focus is on the ways in which a focus on Russian shaped the directions of phonological thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the revised version of the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vja</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/vja/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 21:37:38 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/vja/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;As of July 2018, I will serve as a member of the editorial board at Russia&amp;rsquo;s premier linguistics journal, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.issuesinlinguistics.ru&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voprosy jazykoznanija&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Frlsu</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/frlsu/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 21:37:25 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/frlsu/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I will present &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/frlsu/&#34;&gt;The influence of Norse on Scottish Gaelic, 85 years on&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://frlsu.org/conferences/2018-2/&#34;&gt;12th conference of the Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>26mfm</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/26mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 15:44:59 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/26mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;em&gt;There is no problem of /v/ in Russian phonology&lt;/em&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/mfm/26mfm.html&#34;&gt;26th Manchester Phonology Meeting&lt;/a&gt;. Get the slides and handout &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/26mfm/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Substance Free Phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/substance-free-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/substance-free-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Russian</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/russian/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonetics Phonology Interface</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>There is no problem of /v/ in Russian phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/26mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/26mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The dual behaviour of /v/ has been a notorious crux in Russian phonology since at least Jakobson (1956). The basic problem is that /v/ fails to trigger voicing assimilation, like sonorants, but undergoes both assimilation to following obstruents  and final devoicing, like obstruents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commonest solution in the literature is representational: [v] is treated as a sonorant, either an underlying /w/ (Lightner 1972, Hayes 1984, Kiparsky 1985) or some labial non-glide (Coats &amp;amp; Harshenin 1971, Padgett 2002). Most recently, Reiss (2017) analyses /v/ as /V/, underspecified for [±voice] – patterning with sonorants, but not a sonorant in featural terms – that is devoiced to [f]. He argues that this is an insurmountable challenge to the Contrastivist Hypothesis (Hall 2007), since [v] and [f] are minimally distinct in terms of voicing, but do not pattern phonologically like other similar pairs in Russian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument rests on two premises: Russian /v/ lacks a voicing specification, and is thus unable to trigger assimilation (cf. Kiparsky 1985, Hall 2004), but becomes phonologically voiceless in the course of the derivation. In this paper I argue that the first premise is correct, but there is no evidence that the latter process is phonological; instead, there is every reason to treat all (de)voicing patterns affecting Russian /v/ as belonging to the phonetic component, just as is the case for sonorants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this analysis, the apparent serial interaction of the obstruentization of /v/ and its devoicing follows from the feed-forward architecture of grammar, not from ordering within the phonology (for a related analysis, see Knyazev 2004, 2006). I argue that Russian /v/ is laryngeally underspecified not just in the input to phonology but also in its output; it is in no sense the voiced counterpart of /f/, which joins the better known [t͡s], [t͡ʃʲ], and [x] in lacking such a counterpart (cf. already Kiparsky 1985). If the patterns of /v/ (de)voicing are phonetic, then a whole host of facts cease to be problematic for phonological analysis, including the famous variability in the behaviour of devoiced /v/ as an assimilation trigger ([jazf] ∼ [jasf] for /jazv/ ‘sore.GEN.PL’; Reformatskiĭ 1975); the behaviour of [v] and sonorants in voicing assimilation (Kulikov 2013); the fact that some (de)voicing patterns are specific to [v], such as the minority but robust pattern of progressive assimilation in [v#v] sequences (Vorontsova 2007); and the sensitivity of sonorant and /v/ (de)voicing to prosodic boundary strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dissociation between laryngeal assimilation in obstruents and in /v/ is also expected to follow from the life cycle of phonological processes (Bermúdez-Otero 2015): historically, the former predates the latter by several centuries, and there is ample dialect evidence showing that the devoicing of /v/, even where it did happen, did not always result in [f], [x] being a frequent outcome (e. g. Kasatkin 2005, Galinskaya 2008). The proposed analysis is reminiscent of ‘rule scattering’ (Zsiga 2000, Bermúdez- Otero 2015), with both phonological and phonetic patterns of (de)voicing found in the same language; in fact, I argue that phonetic /v/ (de)voicing coexists with another phonetic pattern of obstruent devoicing and assimilation – the gradient congener of phonological assimilation rules arising via rule scattering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, many aspects of the behaviour of Russian [v] may have a phonetic rationale, at least historically (albeit possibly not synchronically, as argued by Bjorndahl 2015). However, in this paper I argue that the best analysis of the problem of /v/ is a substance-free one that does not encode these explanations in the phonological grammar, contra e. g. Padgett (2002), but also respects the privileged role of contrast in phonological representation, contra Reiss (2017).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Aaz</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/aaz/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 10:43:47 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2018/aaz/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;An obituary of the great Russian linguist Andrei Zaliznyak that I co-wrote with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.su.se/english/profiles/tamm-1.182300&#34;&gt;Maria Koptjevskaja-Tamm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ruslang.academia.edu/DmitriSitchinava&#34;&gt;Dmitri Sitchinava&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hse.ru/en/org/persons/34802244&#34;&gt;Alexander Piperski&lt;/a&gt; has appeared in &lt;em&gt;Linguistic Typology&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1515/lingty-2018-0006&#34;&gt;Read it in open access here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Optimality Theory</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/optimality-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/optimality-theory/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>North Germanic</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/north-germanic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/north-germanic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ot handbook</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/ot-handbook/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2016/ot-handbook/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My chapter on Optimality Theory has appeared in the &lt;em&gt;Routledge handbook of phonological theory&lt;/em&gt; (edited by S. J. Hannahs and Anna Bosch). Download the draft &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/ot-handbook/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Optimality Theory: Motivations and perspectives</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/ot-handbook/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/ot-handbook/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This chapter provides an introduction to the basic mechanisms of Optimality Theory in phonology and to the most important motivations cited for its widespread adoption. I also review some of the empirical and conceptual challenges it has faced. Ultimately, I suggest, many of these challenges can be traced back to the fact that while OT grew out of a general dissatisfaction with some aspects of late-1980s rule-based phonology, it was adopted as a general theory of phonological computation without an explicit statement of the division of labour vis-à-vis other components of linguistic knowledge with which it interacts. I conclude the chapter by a discussion of ways in which OT still remains relevant even within a changed phonological landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapter is © Routledge&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Norwegian preaspiration in traditional and modern sources</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/fgls/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/fgls/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I survey traditional descriptions of Norwegian dialects
with particular attention to their discussion of voiceless stop
preaspiration, and conclude that it is highly probable preaspiration has
been consistently under-reported in these sources. As surveyed in detail
by Pétur Helgason (2002), preaspiration in Norwegian has been reported
most prominently for northern Gudbrandsdalen (Ross 1907; Horne 1917),
Rogaland (Oftedal 1947; Wolter 1965), and for Senja by Iversen (1913).
To Helgason’s list should be added Vestvågøya (Elstad 1982) and contact
varieties in Northern Norway (Jahr 2008). Other varieties, by
implication, lack preaspiration, and it is usually treated as
characteristic of most mainland North Germanic varieties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I survey the results of recent empirical studies. Pétur Helgason
(2002) has shown that preaspiration is widespread in mainland
varieties; in particular, he has demonstrated that it is pervasive,
albeit variable, in Central Standard Swedish. Preaspiration has also
been shown to exist in Trøndelag (Moxness 1998; van Dommelen 1998; van
Dommelen, Holm &amp;amp; Koreman 2011; Ringen &amp;amp; van Dommelen 2013), Dalane
(Tengesdal 2015), and Oslo (Allen 2016). Finally, I briefly present
the results of my own instrumental study demonstrating the
pervasiveness of preaspiration in speakers from both Rogaland and
Northern Norway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argue that this situation is less likely to be due to language change,
and more likely to reflect fieldworkers’ lack of expectation to find
preaspiration: for instance, Elstad (1982) notes preaspiration for
Vestvågøya where Christiansen (1933) does not mention it for the
neighbouring island of Gimsøya; Tengesdal (2015) directly contradicts
Oftedal’s (1947) impressionistic claims — even though the same author
correctly identified preaspiration in Scottish Gaelic (Oftedal 1956). I
compare these findings to the recent discussion by Kristoffersen (2016)
of the late discovery of the lack of tonal contrasts in rural dialects
around Bergen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Fgls</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/fgls/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/fgls/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/fgls/&#34;&gt;Norwegian preaspiration in traditional and modern sources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.conferences.cahss.ed.ac.uk/germanic-language-studies/&#34;&gt;13th Forum for Germanic Language Studies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Current Issues in Phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/current-issues-in-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/current-issues-in-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This advanced course introduces students to a variety of live research issues in phonological theory. I teach this course with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/heinz-giegerich&#34;&gt;Heinz Giegerich&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt;. Check back nearer the time for a list of topics I will cover.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2e/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2e/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is (optionally) a part of the pre-Honours sequence in the Linguistics undergraduate degree (but can of course be taken as an outside course). In &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I am responsible for the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Indo-European language family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in the phonology of European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-Indo-European languages of Europe (Basque; Finno-Ugric)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I am acting as the course organizer for LEL2D. I am also responsible for the entire phonology block.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2018/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course (co-taught with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt;) we consider a variety of issues connected to phonological change. Throughout the course, we address questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we reconstruct the phonology of past language states?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What types of phonological changes are attested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can synchronic phonological theory assist us in the study of historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn about the human language faculty by studying historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I will cover the following topics (subject to change with extreme prejudice):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanisms and types of phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical phonology and phonological representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teaching</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 21:44:31 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In the second semester of &lt;sup&gt;2017&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2018&lt;/sub&gt;, I am teaching &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc10046.htm&#34;&gt;Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt; (Honours/MSc), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc10089.htm&#34;&gt;Current Issues in Phonology&lt;/a&gt; (Honours/MSc), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc08020.htm&#34;&gt;LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours; I am also the course organizer), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxlasc08021.htm&#34;&gt;LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/17-18/dpt/cxcelt08019.htm&#34;&gt;Linguistics and the Gaelic Language&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Pilot</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/pilot/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 21:41:13 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/pilot/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I have been awarded funding from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ppls.ed.ac.uk&#34;&gt;School of Philosophy, Psychology and Language Sciences&lt;/a&gt; Pilot Project Fund to initiate work on a database of Gaelic dialect forms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Esohph</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/esohph/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2017/esohph/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offered two presentations at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/symposium-on-historical-phonology/&#34;&gt;Third Edinburgh Symposium on Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on pre-sonorant voicing and language contact in the fringe session on laryngeal phonology and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/&#34;&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt; on the history of Brythonic tense and lax vowels in the main session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Welsh</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/welsh/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Breton</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/breton/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Towards a history of the tenseness contrast in Brythonic vowels</title>
<link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Modern Welsh is similar to many modern Germanic languages such as English, German and Dutch in showing an association between &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; vowel quality and phonological length. Specifically, long vowels tend to be tense in quality and short vowels tend to be lax, with concomitant alternations. As in the Germanic case, there is some disagreement in the literature on whether quality or quantity (or both) is phonologically relevant in Modern Welsh. In this paper I aim to add to this debate via an overview of the diatopic variation in the relationship between vowel quantity and quality in Welsh and more broadly in the Brythonic languages. I argue that tense/lax quality is likely to be diachronically secondary with respect to quantity, being derivable from prosodic contexts &amp;mdash; primarily vowel length and syllable structure. One of the notable consequences of this is that even when tense/lax quality has been phonologized (as in, for instance, south-western dialects of Welsh), it is still partly conditioned by quantity and syllable structure; conversely, the distribution of quantity is not significantly determined by vowel quality, which supports the contention that quantity is synchronically active in Welsh phonology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support this case for a secondary development of tense/lax quality, I offer a reconstruction of its rise that starts with a tensing of word-final stressed vowels, perhaps initially only restricted to high vowels. This later undergoes rule generalization  to embrace both non-high vowels (as in most dialects with tense [e: oː]) and to syllable-final rather than word-final position (as in South Welsh dialects, where long vowels are allowed in penultimate stressed syllables). I show that intermediate stages of this development are attested across modern Welsh dialects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argue that the Brythonic languages present an interesting test case for theories that attempt to connect the &amp;lsquo;transphonologization&amp;rsquo; of quantity as quality with the rise of vowel shifts: despite the long/short vowels undergoing a tense/lax split, much as in many Germanic languages, the Brythonic system neither became prone to vowel shifting (as in the case of English) nor underwent a further split where the new qualities fit into a new quantity system (as in many North Germanic varieties).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
