<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Pavel Iosad in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 13:12:26 BST</updated>



<item>
<title>Pavel Iosad</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>News</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 13:06:26 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Off</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/off/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 13:06:26 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/off/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I am on research leave in &lt;sup&gt;2021&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2022&lt;/sub&gt;, and am not teaching any courses in this session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Icngl12</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/icngl12/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 17:35:18 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/icngl12/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; entitled &lt;em&gt;Phonological convergence in north-western Europe: language contact or drift?&lt;/em&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hf.uio.no/multiling/english/news-and-events/events/conferences/2021/international-conference-of-nordic-and-general-lin/&#34;&gt;12th International Conference of Nordic and General Linguistics&lt;/a&gt; organized by the University of Oslo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Presentations</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Germanic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/germanic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/germanic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/celtic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/celtic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological convergence in north-western Europe</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer a framework for understanding convergent diachronic
developments in the phonological systems of unrelated languages,
informed by the life cycle of phonological processes. I focus on
preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the traditional /p t k/ series) in
several languages of north-west Europe where preaspiration cannot be
due to shared inheritance, including the North Germanic languages,
varieties of English, the Gaelic languages, Welsh, and the Sámi
languages. Preaspiration is often claimed to be typologically rare and
diachronically unstable (Silverman 2003, Blevins 2017); hence, its
appearance in unrelated languages with a history of contact is often
ascribed to that contact (Marstrander 1932, Posti 1954, Wagner 1964,
Borgstrøm 1974, Salmons 1992, Gunnar Ólafur Hansson 2001, Rießler
2008, McKenna 2013). However, this scenario is open to challenge.
First, more or less convincing non-contact scenarios for the
development of preaspiration in individual cases have been proposed (Ó
Baoill 1980, Ó Murchú 1985, Ní Chasaide 1986, Goblirsch 2005). Second,
it has been argued (Pétur Helgason 2002, Clayton 2010) that variable,
‘weak’ forms of preaspiration, which authors such as Silverman (2003)
argue to be diachronically unstable, can persist over long time
periods. Third, preaspiration appears to be more widespread than often
assumed, being recently described for Irish (Ní Chasaide 1986), Welsh
(Morris &amp;amp; Hejná 2019), English (Docherty &amp;amp; Foulkes 1999, Hejná 2015,
Kettig 2015, Fiasson 2016), and North Germanic vernaculars (Pétur
Helgason 2002, Schaeffler 2005, Tengesdal 2015). Fourth, historical
and sociolinguistic evidence does not always support the possibility
of contact-induced transfer (Iosad 2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, these arguments undermine the case for contact as the
primary vector of the spread of preaspiration in north-western Europe.
I suggest, however, that the convergent development of preaspiration
in North Germanic, the Gaelic languages and the Sámi languages should
not be entirely written off as coincidental. Instead, I propose to
view this development as an instance of drift along the lines of Sapir
(1921). Specifically, I suggest that the similarities arise because
the development of preaspiration follows the life cycle of
phonological processes (Bermúdez-Otero 2007, 2015). Under this
account, preaspiration arises as a variable by-product of the
realization of laryngeal contrast. It can remain a variable phonetic
rule (as in Ulster Irish, Welsh, English, and some Norwegian
varieties), but it can also (as in Icelandic and some Scottish Gaelic
varieties) enter the phonological grammar, with a concomitant
narrowing in the range of variation. Compatible accounts of the
diachrony of preaspiration are offered by Gunnar Ólafur Hansson (2001)
and Pétur Helgason (2002) for North Germanic and Ó Maolalaigh (2010),
Clayton (2010) and Iosad (2020) for the Gaelic languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suggestion that drift can arise as a consequence of initially
variable phonetic patterns proceeding along the life cycle, which
makes them progressively more entangled in the categorical grammar, is
consistent with the proposal by Joseph (2013) that the historical
source of ‘drift’ in related languages is the narrowing of the range
of variation found in the proto-language. In the cases considered
here, however, the original variation is not inherited, even though
the mechanism of drift is the same. I further suggest that the
convergent developments have been facilitated by the fact that the
languages share significant commonalities in their phonological
grammar, particularly with respect to the role of moraic quantity
(these may or not may be contact-induced at a greater time depth; cf.
Salmons [1992]). These similarities may ‘prime’ (in the sense of
Kiparsky [1995]) the co-option of similar phonetic cues such as
preaspiration to signal quantitative patterns, further contributing to
the convergence. I also suggest that a similar mechanism may have led
to the rise of at least two other areal phenomena in the region: tonal
accents and sonorant pre-stopping.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Otipl Colloquium</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/otipl-colloquium/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 18:12:22 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/otipl-colloquium/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on the life cycle of some phonological patterns in Russian for the Colloquium series at the Department of Theoretical and Applied Linguistics (OTiPL), Moscow State University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Russian</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/russian/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonology Morphology Interface</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonology-morphology-interface/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonology-morphology-interface/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonetics Phonology Interface</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonetics-phonology-interface/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Жизненный цикл морфонологических процессов в русском языке</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Характерное свойство динамических подходов к русской фонологии и морфонологии — как выполненных в духе порождающих фонологических теорий, так и (пост)структуралистских — обширное использование правил, обязательно применяемых в определенном порядке. Обоснование этого порядка — важнейшая задача для теоретического осмысления фактов русского языка, без решения которой динамические подходы являются по сути нефальсифицируемыми: в отсутствие четких ограничений на количество правил и порядок их применения любое чередование можно подвергнуть сколь угодно абстрактному анализу с произвольным количеством правил.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;В число теорий, призванных выявить ограничения на возможный порядок правил, входит, в частности, лексическая фонология и морфология (включая стратификационные варианты теории оптимальности). В рамках этой модели порядок правил ограничен морфологической и синтаксической структурой высказывания.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Подобные стратификационные модели делают интересные предсказания не только в синхронии, но и в диахронии, в рамках так назывемой модели «жизненного цикла фонологических процессов». В докладе рассматриваются примеры жизненного цикла нескольких процессов (палатализации велярных, редукции безударных гласных, поведения согласного /в/) в литературном и диалектном языке и описываются перспективы дальнейшего исследования этих вопросов.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/Ehwb1odKr_g&#34;&gt;Запись доклада на YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teachings</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2021/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2021/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2020&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2021&lt;/sub&gt;, I am acting as the course organizer for LEL2D. I am also responsible for the entire phonology block, and for the ‘implications of variation and universals’ block (with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/graeme-trousdale&#34;&gt;Graeme Trousdale&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Linguistics</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2021/historical-linguistics/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2021/historical-linguistics/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course introduces the type of changes that a language may undergo, at all levels of linguistic structure, and the theoretical frameworks that are available to discuss them. The course also looks at sociolinguistic influences on language change and the consequences of language contact including language convergence, creolisation and language death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2020&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2021&lt;/sub&gt;, I am conducting tutorials covering the entire range of the course’s topics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teaching in spring term 2021</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/2021-spring-teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/2021-spring-teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In Semester 2 of &lt;sup&gt;2020&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2021&lt;/sub&gt;, I am course organizer for the pre-Honours course &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2021/lel2d/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I also teach the universals of variation and phonology blocks. I also teach in pre-Honours on &lt;em&gt;Linguistics and the Gaelic Language&lt;/em&gt;, and at Honours/MSc level on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2021/historical-linguistics/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historical Linguistics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/guided-research/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guided Research in Linguistics and English Language&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Writings</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Scottish Gaelic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/scottish-gaelic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/scottish-gaelic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Papers</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Dialectology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/dialectology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/dialectology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Glossa paper</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/glossa-paper/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/glossa-paper/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My paper with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/william-lamb&#34;&gt;Will Lamb&lt;/a&gt; entitled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dialect variation in Scottish Gaelic nominal morphology: A quantitative study&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has appeared in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.glossa-journal.org&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glossa: A Journal of General Linguistics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Dialect variation in Scottish Gaelic nominal morphology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a dialectometric analysis of Scottish Gaelic morphology, with a focus on the noun phrase, using previously unpublished data from the Linguistic Survey of Scotland. Fifty-five morphological features were extracted across 201 survey points, and the data subjected to a variety of analyses, including cluster analysis, regression, and correlation analysis. We establish that the Gaelic noun system shows robust diatopic (i. e. geographical) variation; this challenges previous assertions in the literature, which describe Gaelic morphosyntax as geographically uniform. In addition, we argue that our dialectometric results provide an insight into the grammatical structure of the language that is not easily achievable through the analysis of individual varieties. In particular, we argue that the results highlight a dissociation between morphological categories such as case and gender and their morphophonological exponents, which are particularly complex in Scottish Gaelic. The paper thus serves as a proof of concept for the use of dialectometric findings in a theoretical context.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Frlsu Published</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/frlsu-published/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 09:44:49 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/frlsu-published/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/frlsu-proceedings/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The life cycle of preaspiration in the Gaelic languages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has appeared in the &lt;a href=&#34;www.abdn.ac.uk/pfrlsu/volumes/vol-6/&#34;&gt;Proceedings of the 2018 Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Laryngeal Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Language Contact</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/language-contact/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/language-contact/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Конвергенция фонологических систем в Северной Европе</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/zvegincev-conference/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/zvegincev-conference/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is a Russian summary of the work that I presented, among other places, at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/eshp4/&#34;&gt;Edinburgh Symposium on Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;В докладе предлагается подход к диахронической конвергенции фонологических систем в неродственных языках, основанный на теории «жизненного цикла фонологических процессов» [Bermúdez-Otero 2007], на примере развития преаспирациии сильных («глухих») взрывных в нескольких языках северной Европы.
Преаспирация обычно считается явлением типологически редким и диахронически нестабильным [Silverman 2003]. Тем более удивительным кажется ее наличие в таких географически, но не генеалогически, близких языках, как северогерманские, английский (несколько разновидностей), гойдельские языки (ирландский и шотландский), валлийский и саамские языки. Если учесть, что эти языки имеют обширную историю контактов, такое распространение преаспирации часто объяснялось именно взаимовлиянием (ср., например, [Marstrander 1932; Posti 1954; Wagner 1964; Rießler 2008]).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;В последнее время, однако, этот сценарий подвергся пересмотру. Во-первых, для отдельных случаев были предложены более или менее убедительные сценарии эндогенного развития [Ó Baoill 1980; Ní Chasaide 1986; Goblirsch 2005]. Во-вторых, было показано [Pétur Helgason 2002; Clayton 2010], что «слабая», необязательная преаспирация, рассматривавшаяся ранее как диахронически нестабильная, в действительности может сохраняться в течение длительного времени. В-третьих, детальные инструментальные исследования обнаружили, что редкость преаспирации не следует преувеличивать: ее наличие было описано в языках, где ранее она считалась отсутствовавшей, в том числе ирландском, валлийском, английском и многочисленных северогерманских диалектах [Pétur Helgason 2002; Schaeffler 2005]. В-четвертых, данные исторической социолингвистики также не всегда поддерживают контактный сценарий [Iosad 2020].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Все эти соображения указывают на то, что роль языковых контактов в распространении преаспирации на северо-западе Европы следует пересмотреть. В докладе, тем не менее, показано, что схождения между германскими, кельтскими и саамскими языками в этой области не следует списывать как случайные. Вместо этого их можно рассматривать как результат «дрейфа» в духе У. Сепира, а точнее — того, что развитие преаспирации следует жизненному циклу фонологических процессов. Диахроническая траектория преаспирации в этом случае такова, что она возникает как побочный продукт реализации противопоставления по звонкости, а затем становится необязательным («интегральным») признаком, манипулируемым в рамках фонетического компонента грамматики (так, например, в ольстерских диалектах ирландского, в валлийском или в норвежских диалектах). Следующий шаг развития — превращение в фонологическую единицу, благодаря чем преаспирация, с одной стороны, становится обязательной, а с другой — претерпевает сужение диапазона варьирования (так в исландском или в диалектах шотландского); ср. совместимые предложения для северогерманских языков в [Pétur Helgason 2002] и для гойдельских в [Clayton 2010].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Предложенный подход совместим с предложением Б. Джозефа [Joseph 2013], который рассматривает «дрейф» в родственных языках как результат сужения диапазона варьирования, наблюдавшегося в праязыке. Сходство результатов обеспечивает в наших не только единство механизма, который стоит за этим сужением («жизненный цикл»), но и то, что рассмотренные языки обнаруживают нетривиальные сходства в устройстве фонологической грамматики, особенно в том, что касается количественных противопоставлений [Ewels 2009]. Эти сходства создают своеобразный «прайминговый» эффект [Kiparsky 1995], при котором сходные фонетические ключи (такие как преаспирация) используются для выражения сходных фонологических контрастов.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The life cycle of preaspiration in the Gaelic languages</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/frlsu-proceedings/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/frlsu-proceedings/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper is a written-up version of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/frlsu/&#34;&gt;presentation at the 2018 conference of the Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose (yet another) reappraisal of the arguments
regarding the relationship between Norse and Gaelic in the North
Atlantic world, focusing on the development of preaspiration. There is
significant controversy in the literature as to whether this feature,
along with others such as tonal accent, represents Norse influence on
Gaelic (e.g. Marstrander 1932; Borgstrøm 1974; Gunnar Ólafur Hansson
2001), an independent development in Gaelic (e.g. Ó Baoill 1980; Ó
Murchú 1985; Ó Maolalaigh 2010), or even Gaelic influence on Norse
(McKenna 2013). With recent advances in our understanding of how the
social context of contact influences its linguistic outcomes (e.g.
Thomason &amp;amp; Kaufman 1988; Trudgill 2011; Millar 2016), the debate around
the role of language contact in the development of Gaelic varieties has
begun to acquire a more solid theoretical underpinning; see in
particular Stewart (2004); Lindqvist (2015) and most recently Lewin
(2017).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I offer an account of the development of preaspiration combining these
sociolinguistic insights with the theory of the life cycle of
phonological processes (e.g. Bermúdez-Otero 2007; 2015; Bermúdez-Otero &amp;amp;
Trousdale 2012). I argue that this theory offers a useful diagnostic for
historical language contact, since discontinuities in the life cycle can
only be contact-induced. I propose a model of the development of Gaelic
preaspiration consistent with the life cycle model, starting with
variable preaspiration, arguing that variable preaspiration is a
pan-Gaelic phenomenon under-reported in traditional sources. Under this
analysis, the rise of categorical preaspiration is a Northern Gaelic
innovation (cf. Clayton 2010), centred on Argyll. With this linguistic
argument in hand, I argue that a Norse origin for this feature is
unlikely to be compatible with what we know about the sociolinguistic
context of the (re-)Gaelicization of Argyll (Jennings &amp;amp; Kruse (2009a);
(2009b); Clancy (2011); Whyte (2017), &lt;em&gt;pace&lt;/em&gt; Macniven (2015)).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Zvegincev</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/zvegincev/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 09:32:12 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/zvegincev/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I gave &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/zvegincev-conference/&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on my ongoing project on northern European areal phonology at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://tipl.philol.msu.ru/index.php/science/conferences/zvegintsev2020&#34;&gt;2020 Zvegintsev Conference&lt;/a&gt; to celebrate 60 years of my &lt;em&gt;alma mater&lt;/em&gt;, OTiPL.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Abralin</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/abralin/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 09:18:28 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/abralin/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/abralin/&#34;&gt;talk with an overview of some of my recent work on Russian phonology&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aovivo.abralin.org/en/&#34;&gt;Abralin ao Vivo&lt;/a&gt; series of online talks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Rebooting Slavic phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/abralin/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/abralin/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The Slavic languages have historically played a very prominent role in the development of Western phonological theory, from some of the earliest pioneers of phonemic theory such as Jan Baudouin de Courtenay, Mikołaj Kruszewski and Lev Shcherba, through the Praguian structuralism of Nikolai Trubetzkoy and (early) Roman Jakobson, and to some of the foundational work of generative phonology. In particular, Morris Halle and Theodore Lightner offered comprehensive analyses of Russian phonology that relied heavily on multi-level derivations, abstract underlying representations and a suite of rules that largely recapitulated diachronic developments. These devices were widely taken up both in the analysis of other Slavic languages and more broadly within the generative phonological tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the present day, the phonological analysis of the Slavic languages is arguably still overshadowed by the frameworks set by these pioneers. On the one hand, much (although by no means all) current theoretical work within the SPE tradition (including ‘post-SPE’ constraint-based frameworks) still operates with assumptions inherited from this work; on the other hand, a number of productive traditions (notably those in Government Phonology and allied theories) in the analysis of Slavic are explicitly framed as alternatives to these approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk I sketch out an approach that both rejects the highly abstract analyses of early generative phonology and the wholesale rejection of the SPE tradition. I review some recent work in Russian phonology and argue that closer attention to the phonetics-phonology interface, featural representations, and contrast, combined with a fairly orthodox version of a stratal approach to morphology-phonology interaction, provides us with the means to make significant progress in the analysis of Russian, and likely the Slavic languages more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch the talk below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rua5e8Wdmzo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vaplujub</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/vaplujub/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 10:31:55 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/vaplujub/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I have contributed a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/&#34;&gt;brief paper&lt;/a&gt; on Russian yer vowels to a Festschrift for my undergraduate supervisor, Vladimir Plungian.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Per aspera ad astra</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this brief paper, I suggest that, contrary to much previous literature, the quality of the yer vowels in Modern Russian is predictable, and does not have to be encoded in the underlying representation. This is a consequence of an approach that rejects the long-standing tradition of positing highly abstract underlying representations, and in particular derives the palatalization of consonants from the backness of following vowels. I argue that the quality of yers is predictable from the context, particularly from the palatalization of preceding consonants and from whether the morphological context drives the &lt;a href=&#34;{{ ref &amp;quot;writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology.md&amp;quot; }}&#34;&gt;otherwise well-known&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;e ~ ’o&lt;/em&gt; alternation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2020&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2021&lt;/sub&gt;, in response to the Covid-19 crisis, I am teaching on this course as part of a team that also includes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/patrick-honeybone&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/benjamin-molineaux&#34;&gt;Benjamin Molineaux&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/laura-m-arnold&#34;&gt;Laura Arnold&lt;/a&gt;. I will teach a block that includes the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of phonological theory: contrast, phonemes, allophones, alternations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivations, underlying representations, rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process interaction and rule ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, there is a strong emphasis on building data analysis and problem solving skills. The course will also cover topics relevant to the phonology of English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is also offered for MSc students (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/20-21/dpt/cxlasc11148.htm&#34;&gt;LASC11148&lt;/a&gt;). It is suitable for postgraduate students who have had some previous exposure to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Linguistics and English Language 1A</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel1a/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel1a/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the introductory linguistics &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; course for all first-year students in Linguistics and English Language. With &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/graeme-trousdale&#34;&gt;Graeme Trousdale&lt;/a&gt;, I am responsible for the data analysis/language puzzles component of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Guided Research in Linguistics and English Language</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/guided-research/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/guided-research/</guid>
<description>

&lt;p&gt;This is a course that offers students the opportunity to pursue their own research in area related to the topic of the seminar. In &lt;sup&gt;2020&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2021&lt;/sub&gt;, I am offering a guided research seminar in both semesters on the following topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-where-when-why-linguistic-diversity-typology-and-historical-linguistics&#34;&gt;What’s Where When Why: Linguistic diversity, typology, and historical linguistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we approach the study of diversity and variation across languages? Why are some structures rare, and others common? Why do certain features tend to occur together? Explaining such patterns, which are pervasive across language families and linguistic subfields, is the aim of linguistic typology. A venerable tradition, going back to Wilhelm von Humboldt in the early 19th century, gives a role to structural factors, by identifying ‘types’ that languages belong to, and the properties associated with them. Linguistic structures, however, do not exist in a vacuum, and patterns of variation are often related to contingencies of history. Closely related languages, for instance, are often typologically similar. In the early 20th century, the notion of ‘language areas’ was crystallized and thereby introduced geography into the mix. Increased understanding of the mechanics of language contact also led to deeper insights into how it influences patterns of diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, linguistic typology has increasingly abandoned its focus on structural properties of languages, moving towards a research programme that aims to explain how linguistic diversity patterns in space and time: from ‘what’ to ‘where’, ‘when’, and of course ‘why’. In this seminar we will look at the range of diversity in a number of domains of grammar, consider some key concepts of linguistic typology, and analyse the ways in which theories of grammatical structure and the study of language change, history, anthropology, and geography all contribute to understanding the diversity of human language.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Sem1 Start</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/sem1-start/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/sem1-start/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In Semester 1 of &lt;sup&gt;2020&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2021&lt;/sub&gt;, I am teaching on  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel1a/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linguistics and English Language 1A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I am responsible for the data analysis block, and on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/phonological-theory/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phonological Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I am also offering a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/guided-research/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guided Research in LEL&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; seminar entitled &lt;em&gt;What’s Where When Why: Linguistic diversity, typology, and historical linguistics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Rhema Paper</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/rhema-paper/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 09:51:53 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/rhema-paper/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/&#34;&gt;paper on the &lt;em&gt;e ~ ’o&lt;/em&gt; alternation in Russian in Stratal Phonology&lt;/a&gt; (in Russian) has appeared in &lt;a href=&#34;http://rhema-journal.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rhema&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Морфонологическая стратификация в русском языке | Stratal phonology and Russian morphophonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;В работе предлагается анализ фрагмента русской морфонологии – чередования &lt;em&gt;e~’o&lt;/em&gt; и некоторых связанных с ним явлений – в духе порождающих стратификационных подходов наподобие лексической фонологии. Цель работы – показать, что это чередование обладает целым рядом свойств, обычно характерных для основообразующих фонологических правил. Таким образом, утверждается, что, с одной стороны, русский материал поддерживает модель, предполагающую стратификацию морфонологических систем, а с другой – стратификационные модели открывают продуктивные подходы к анализу русской морфонологии, эксплицитно связывающие морфонологическую структуру как с фонологическими закономерностями, так и с морфологической и семантической структурой русских слов.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper analyses a fragment of the morphophonological grammar of Russian, namely the so-called &lt;em&gt;e~’о&lt;/em&gt; alternation, within a Lexical Phonology-style stratal model. The aim is to demonstrate that the rule shows a range of properties usually associated with stem-level phonology. Thus, on the one hand, Russian data provides further support for a stratal model of morphophonology, and on the other hand stratal models appear to be a productive approach to Russian morphophonological alternations that explicitly links morphophonology with both phonological patterns and the morphological and semantic structure of Russian words.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Prosodic Structure</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The phonology of Gaelic tonal accent</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;It is well known that many varieties of Gaelic show an opposition
between two classes of words that is implemented by suprasegmental
means such as pitch and glottalization. These phenomena have been
compared to the ‘tonal accents’ of the North and West Germanic
languages (notably by Ternes 1980, 2006), and a number of analyses
have been proposed in the theoretical linguis- tics literature. In
this paper, I summarize the patterns found across traditional
varieties of Scottish Gaelic, and focus on the (limited number of)
synchronic alternations that involve accent-related phenomena. In
particular, I address the interaction between tonal accents and
vowel-zero alterna- tions. I argue that it further supports the
analyses of Gaelic tonal accents as reflecting differences in
syllabification or more generally metrical structure, as envisaged by
Oftedal (1956); Clements (1986); Smith (1999); Iosad (2015) and most
recently in the comprehensive analysis by Morrison (2019). I also
discuss what kind of new data is necessary to make further progress in
our understanding of the accentual phonology of Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>History of Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonology in the Soviet Union</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This invited contribution to a collection on the history of phonology explores the history of phonological studies in the USSR. I offer a short history of phonology in Russia and the USSR before the formation of the two main theoretical currents (the &amp;lsquo;Leningrad&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Moscow&amp;rsquo; schools), and emphasize both their mutual common roots and their closeness to other structuralist frameworks, in particular Prague phonology. I discuss the differences between the two schools both in their approach to the phoneme and in their analysis of morphophonological alternations. Throughout, the focus is on the ways in which a focus on Russian shaped the directions of phonological thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel2e/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel2e/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is (optionally) a part of the pre-Honours sequence in the Linguistics undergraduate degree (but can of course be taken as an outside course). In &lt;sup&gt;2019&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2020&lt;/sub&gt;, I am responsible for the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Indo-European language family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in the phonology of European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-Indo-European languages of Europe (Basque; Finno-Ugric)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2019&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2020&lt;/sub&gt;, I am acting as the course organizer for LEL2D. I am also responsible for the entire phonology block.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course (co-taught with my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt;) we consider a variety of issues connected to phonological change. Throughout the course, we address questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we reconstruct the phonology of past language states?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What types of phonological changes are attested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can synchronic phonological theory assist us in the study of historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn about the human language faculty by studying historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2019&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2020&lt;/sub&gt;, I will cover the following topics :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanisms and types of phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The life cycle of phonological processes; transmission and diffusion in phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical phonology and phonological representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Current Issues in Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/current-issues-in-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/current-issues-in-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This advanced course introduces students to a variety of live research issues in phonological theory. I teach this course with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/michael-ramsammy&#34;&gt;Michael Ramsammy&lt;/a&gt;. This year, I am teaching the blocks on phonological analysis with Optimality Theory (3 weeks) and issues around phonological representation and contrast (2 weeks).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Sem2 Start</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/sem2-start/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 12:32:22 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2020/sem2-start/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In Semester 2 of &lt;sup&gt;2019&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2020&lt;/sub&gt;, I am course organizer for the pre-Honours course &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel2d/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I also teach the phonology block. I also teach in pre-Honours on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/lel2e/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and on &lt;em&gt;Linguistics and the Gaelic Language&lt;/em&gt;, and at Honours/MSc level on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/historical-phonology/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historical Phonology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2020/current-issues-in-phonology/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current Issues in Phonology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
