<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Pavel Iosad in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 18:02:19 GMT</updated>



<item>
<title>Teachings</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Pavel Iosad</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course (co-taught with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.homepages.ed.ac.uk/bmolinea/&#34;&gt;Benjamin Molineaux&lt;/a&gt;) we consider a variety of issues connected to phonological change. Throughout the course, we address questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we reconstruct the phonology of past language states?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What types of phonological changes are attested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can synchronic phonological theory assist us in the study of historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn about the human language faculty by studying historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, I expect to cover the following topics :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanisms and types of phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, I am the Course Organizer for this course; more information on the teaching will be available in due course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Presentations</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>North Germanic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/north-germanic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/north-germanic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Livssyklusmodellen for fonologiske mønster i norsk og nordisk</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/mons/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/mons/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;[The conference has been rescheduled from November 2021 to November 2022]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I føredraget set eg fram nokre resultat frå ei gransking av fleire fonologiske mønster i norsk (og i den breiare vestnordiske konteksten), med utgangspunkt i livssyklusmodellen for lydendring. I denne modellen skjer lydendring ved at automatisk fonetisk variasjon vert til fonetiske reglar, deretter til kategoriske fonologiske reglar og vidare til sykliske fonologiske reglar i samspel med morfologien. Eg viser korleis denne modellen kastar nytt lys over fleire velkjende mønster i norsk fonologi og morfologi, frå både strukturelle, historiske og dialektologiske standpunkt. Eg set spesielt fokus på samspelet mellom den laryngale kontrasten i klusilane og utviklinga av vokalisk kvantitet i norske dialektar og andre vestnordiske språk, og viser korleis vi kan forstå fenomen som preaspirasjon og lenisering i lys av livssyklusmodellen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Categories</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Structure of a Language</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/sotl/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/sotl/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is a new course that aims to give students the chance to build their skills in linguistic analysis and their understanding of the range of linguistic diversity, by means of sustained engagement with a range of material in the target language. Students should expect a very significant independent study component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; intended as a ‘language learning’ course aiming to build practical competence in the language. Early on in the course, students will be provided with grammatical information and pointers to resources that will allow them to begin analysing extracts of texts and/or other materials in the target language. Students will be expected to have prepared for the teaching sessions by analysing extracts provided beforehand: in class, we will focus on going over the analysis and discussion of relevant theoretical concepts, as well as any appropriate sociohistorical background to the material. &lt;em&gt;Structure of a Language&lt;/em&gt; is a course in the linguistics of the target language: you will use your analysis skills in concert with appropriate readings to gain a knowledge of the language&amp;rsquo;s structure and of other relevant information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, the target language is &lt;strong&gt;Ukrainian&lt;/strong&gt;. More information will appear in due course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, I am fully responsible for this course. Students will build on fundamental concepts in phonology to engage with a range of intermediate and advanced topics, with a focus on the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of phonological theory: contrast, phonemes, allophones, alternations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivations, underlying representations, rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process interaction and rule ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, there is a strong emphasis on building data analysis and problem solving skills. Teaching sessions are built around discussion of puzzles and data sets. Students are assessed via a semester-long project focused on describing and analysing the phonological patterns of a language of their choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is also offered for MSc students (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/22-23/dpt/cxlasc11148.htm&#34;&gt;LASC11148&lt;/a&gt;). It is suitable for postgraduate students who have had some previous exposure to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Linguistics and English Language 1A</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/lel1a/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/lel1a/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the introductory linguistics &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; course for all first-year students in Linguistics and English Language. This year, I am the Course Organizer; in addition, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/graeme-trousdale&#34;&gt;Graeme Trousdale&lt;/a&gt;, I am responsible for the data analysis/language puzzles component of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teaching linguistics</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/teaching-linguistics/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/teaching-linguistics/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>News</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Linguistics puzzles in the university curriculum</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/lagb-workshop/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/lagb-workshop/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Self-contained linguistics puzzles (Zaliznyak 1963) are extremely well-established as a means of introducing school-age young people to linguistics, primarily via the Linguistics Olympiad movement. They are carefully curated data sets that allow the solver to discover regular patters in the structure of unfamiliar languages. Crucially, solving such puzzles generally requires no prior exposure to technical concepts, and they can be tackled only with general reasoning skills. As such, they are very well suited as a ‘gateway’ towards the field for pupils who may not otherwise have engaged with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we report the preliminary results from several years of introducing puzzles into the university curriculum. We demonstrate that they are a viable way of introducing and reinforcing key technical concepts and developing general analytical skills from a very early stage. Furthermore, we show how this effect is boosted when puzzles are tightly integrated into the curriculum and overall pedagogical approach, facilitating not only the achievement of learning outcomes at the level of the individual course/module but also the development of independent enquiry skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linguistics puzzles of the kind we are using show some overlap with activities aligned to two general pedagogical approaches, namely problem-based learning and self-directed learning. For instance, like problem-based learning, they focus on developing generic skills needed to solve problems, and on creating a knowledge base of key concepts in linguistics. However, unlike standard problem-based learning, the puzzles we use are not open-ended\dash they do have a unique solution. On the other hand, as is the case in self-directed learning, they do provide an appropriate scaffold for further instruction on the topic. Our activities align further with problem-based learning in terms of problem design, in that our aim is to create a puzzle which is appropriately difficult, but also engaging to a range of learners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we report on the introduction of a ‘puzzle component’ into a first-year &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; linguistics course that is taken both by students pursuing linguistics degrees and by ‘outside’ students who choose it as an option. In this context, the puzzle component runs ‘alongside’ the core curriculum, with students having the opportunity to work on one or more new puzzles every week, without the expectation that the problems they solve relate to any specific part of the curriculum. Based on a student survey offered to five cohorts of students who have taken this course after the introduction of the component, we report both quantitative and qualitative data suggesting very high levels of satisfaction and effectiveness: importantly, students do not just find the puzzles enjoyable, but also report that, in retrospect, they found them to be useful as a means to both reinforce linguistic concepts and build more generally applicable reasoning and problem-solving skills. However, we also identify some pedagogical challenges that we have faced, in particular the difficulty of managing student expectation around the appropriate levels of support for these activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second challenge uncovered by this project concerns the relationship between puzzles and the specific curricular context of the course. We consider this in more detail by reporting a second project in which we rebuilt the pedagogy of a large ($\approx$140 students) upper beginner/lower intermediate course around puzzle solving, as a key element of adapting course delivery during the Covid-19 crisis. The course in question involves primarily technical analysis of linguistic structure. As part of this effort, we were able to maintain the technical content of the course effectively unchanged whilst re-centring our pedagogy around student-led enquiry and problem-based learning, leading to good academic outcomes coupled with high levels of satisfaction. We suggest that this success speaks to the issue of curricular integration, and argue that problem-based learning is an effective avenue to better achievement and more authentic pedagogy in linguistics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Lagb</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/lagb/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/lagb/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/lagb-workshop/&#34;&gt;talk on our work with puzzles in the university linguistics curriculum&lt;/a&gt; with Graeme Trousdale and Rob Truswell at the 2022 LAGB conference &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.ed.ac.uk/itamar/lagb2022/&#34;&gt;workshop on &lt;em&gt;Advances and challenges in teaching linguistics at university&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Autumn Teaching</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/sem1-teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/sem1-teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In Semester 1 of &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, I am running the Honours/MSc course &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2019/phonological-theory/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phonological Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the pre-Honours on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2019/lel1a/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linguistics and English Language 1A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I am also responsible for the puzzle component. Furthermore, I am offering a new Honours course called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/sotl/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Structure of a Language&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: in &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, we are exploring the structure of Ukrainian.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Writings</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Uralic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/uralic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/uralic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Ttfs</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/ttfs/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/ttfs/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/trond-trosterud-fs/&#34;&gt;paper on the historical phonology of Sámi preaspiration&lt;/a&gt; has appeared in a Festschrift for &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.uit.no/ansatte/person?p_document_id=41545&#34;&gt;Trond Trosterud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Laryngeal phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Den historiske utviklinga til preaspirasjon i samiske språk</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/trond-trosterud-fs/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/trond-trosterud-fs/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Preaspiration of voiceless stops is a well-known feature of the phonological systems of the Sámi languages,as in Northern Sámi [jahki] &lt;em&gt;jahki&lt;/em&gt; ‘year’. In some form, it is found in all Sámi varieties that we have records of, with the sole exception of Inari Sámi. We also possess a good understanding of how Sámi preaspiration is related to the consonant gradation systems of other Uralic languages, in particular those of the Finnic varieties. Present-day Sámi languages differ somewhat in the role that preaspirated stops play in their phonological systems. In this paper I outline how this variation arose in the course of the historicaldevelopment from Proto-Sámi to the present-day languages. I propose a scenario grounded in the life cycle of phonological processes (Kiparsky 1995, Bermúdez-Otero 2007, 2015). I argue that this framework is especially well suited to clarifying diverse developments of phonetic and phonological patterns from acommon historical source, and is applicable also to Sámi material. I justify this approach by tracing the development of preaspiration from a phonetic rule of Proto-Sámi to the various outcomes attested in the present-day languages.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>What did representations ever do for us?</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/egg/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2022/egg/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course we will examine how representational explanations in phonology work, when we should consider using them in preference to others, and what kind of predictions representational theories can and cannot make. Focusing on phenomena in segmental phonology, we will consider how (whether?) representational devices such as underspecification, privativity, the contrastive hierarchy, and geometric structure can constrain our expectations regarding what a possible phonological process is, as well as how they relate to each other. Our main focus will be on what kind of data can motivate us to adopt a representational solution. We will consider both mainstream substance-based views of representation in the SPE tradition and various substance-free approaches to feature theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course will be quite practical, with a focus on hands-on discussion of curated data sets. This course is most suitable for attendees who already have a grasp of how to construct a basic phonological analysis. As such, there is no set reading, but a familiarity with analysis techniques will be assumed that can be gained by at least a cursory examination of a textbook in generative phonological analysis, insofar as it covers underlying and surface representations, rules and rule ordering, and a basic introduction to phonological features.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ichl</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/ichl/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/ichl/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented two talks at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ichl.ling-phil.ox.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;25th International Conference on Historical Linguistics&lt;/a&gt;: one on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25/&#34;&gt;the life cycle of Uralic consonant gradation&lt;/a&gt; in the main session, and one coauthored with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maths.ed.ac.uk/~bgoddard/&#34;&gt;Ben Goddard&lt;/a&gt;, Francesca Iezzi, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/graeme-trousdale&#34;&gt;Graeme Trousdale&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25-workshop/&#34;&gt;historical linguistics in schools&lt;/a&gt; at a workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical linguistics in schools</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25-workshop/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25-workshop/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Knowledge about language (KAL) is frequently cited as an important component of literacy strategies, but there is considerable debate about what that knowledge is, how it should be communicated, and how understanding of KAL should be assessed. At advanced levels in the English school system, the topic of language change is often a specified component of particular assessments of KAL (e.g. the AQA A-level in English Language has an area of study in which candidates “explore processes of language change”) and assessment of classical languages involves specific questions on grammatical terminology (e.g. the OCR A-level in Latin has questions on “syntax and accidence”). As such, the curricula draw on concepts from approaches to both diachronic linguistics and the synchronic analysis of older languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, new incentives to encourage a deeper understanding of how language works have been made available to British schools. One of these is UKLO, the United Kingdom Linguistics Olympiad, a national competition for school children in which they have to solve linguistics problems, typically involving an unfamiliar language. Problems in the UKLO competition have involved puzzles about historical linguistic data sets, focussing on e.g. reconstruction and early writing systems. As one of the science Olympiads, UKLO has clear overlaps with the British Mathematical Olympiad (BMO), especially in that they both involve problem-solving and enquiry-based learning over small data sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we report on a project at the University of Edinburgh designed to enhance children’s capacity to think like mathematicians and linguists. In doing so, we intend to address the fifth question posed by the workshop organisers, i.e. ‘In general, does (or can) historical linguistics contribute to the reinvention of language courses at schools among more scientific lines?’ We focus particularly on puzzles we have created on historical themes (e.g. a number system used by Cistercian monks, runic transcriptions) and show how such puzzles serve a number of educational purposes. At a subject specific level, they provide opportunities to introduce complex historical concepts (e.g. sound change) in an engaging way, and offer ways of exploring connections between language families that may not be immediately apparent in the modern language classroom. They also encourage abstract thinking at a cross-linguistic level (e.g. grammaticalization of gender systems across languages spoken in Europe). At a more general level, they develop problem-solving and lateral thinking skills which transcend traditional discipline boundaries (e.g. by looking at how historical and contemporary writing systems involve patterns of rotation and reflection, it is possible to see how an understanding of language links to mathematical concepts).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The life cycle of phonological patterns explains drift in sound change</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I address the nature of ‘drift’ (Sapir 1921) in phonological change from the perspective of the life cycle of phonological processes (Kiparsky 1995; Bermúdez-Otero 2007; 2015; Bermúdez-Otero &amp;amp; Trousdale 2012). I support the basic account of drift offered by Joseph (2013); Natvig &amp;amp; Salmons (2020), in which parallel changes arise from shared patterns of phonetic and phonological variation inherited from the proto-language. Specifically, I propose that a complete account of drift can be provided if we complement the insight that parallel changes draw on the inherited pool of variation with the proposition that change proceeds along the trajectory guided by the life cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In historical phonology, ‘drift’ refers to similar or identical innovations that occur in related varieties after their separation. Some instances of this phenomenon can be explained with reference to relatively ordinary propagation, especially when the languages remain in contact: a classic case is Slavic, in which the last common innovation — the loss of the yers — post-dates the diversification of the proto-language by several centuries (cf. Trubetzkoy 1924). Other instances clearly represent parallel changes, such as the [s]-retraction of Germanic discussed by Joseph (2013), or West Germanic ‘breaking’ processes (Howell 1991). For yet other cases, the respective rôles of parallel development and contact remain controversial: cf. Natvig &amp;amp; Salmons (2020) on the uvular rhotic in Germanic or Sandøy (2003) on common developments in Western Nordic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insight that languages inherit similar patterns of structured variability (Joseph 2013) accounts for similar starting points in such changes. A second challenge is explaining why developments arising from similar pools of variation need to follow similar lines. Often, parallel development can usefully be explained with reference to typology and the phonetic grounding of much sound change (Garrett &amp;amp; Johnson 2013; Kümmel 2015). However, this is not always the case. In this regard, a particular challenge is presented by examples where drift involves changes that are typologically rare, lack clear functional grounding, or otherwise confound synchronic and/or diachronic expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper I consider just such a case: the ‘consonant gradation’ of the Finnic and Sámi languages. This complicated phenomenon (for handbook overviews, cf. Laanest 1982; Korhonen 1981) involves a number of non-trivial convergences, such as consonant weakening after even-numbered vowels, a ‘strength’ asymmetry between consonants (and clusters) determined by the presence of a coda in the following syllable, the lengthening of consonants before long vowels, and the creation of ternary quantity distinctions. This constellation of highly unusual features could suggest that gradation is the result of a single innovation in Proto-Finnic-Sámi (cf. relatively recently Gordon 1997). However, I argue that there are good reasons to reject common origin. They include fundamental differences in the nature of the alternations in the two subgroups (lenition in Finnic, fortition in Sámi [Ravila 1951; Sammallahti 1998]) and the demonstrably late relative date of the changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I offer a reconstruction of the development of gradation that takes seriously the idea that ‘phonetic’ gradation is shared by the two branches and goes back to an earlier period than the separate rise of ‘phonological’ gradation (Ravila 1960; Leppik 1968), framing it within the context of the life cycle model of phonological processes. I argue that inherited phonetic tendencies related to timing, which had the status of phonetic rules (the ‘phonologization’ stage of the life cycle) followed broadly similar paths as they ‘stabilized’ into phonological rules; the details, however, inevitably differed, giving the attested diversity of outcomes. I conclude that the life cycle model is successful in accounting even for drift involving typologically unusual changes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Prosodic structure</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Metrical structure and Stratal Phonology provide a complete account of Danish stød</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we demonstrate that the patterning of stød in Standard Danish submits to a complete, non-stipulative account within an approach that embraces metrical structure as the mechanism behind accentual contrasts (Köhnlein 2019), and the main tenets of Stratal Phonology (Bermúdez- Otero 2018). Our approach maintains the empirical coverage of the ‘Non-Stød Model’ developed by Basbøll (2005 et passim), but builds on widely accepted principles of morphology-phonology interaction instead of a proliferation of bespoke domains, in addition to incorporating insights from other approaches (notably Itô &amp;amp; Mester 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stød is a laryngealization prosody that, in Standard Danish, is restricted to stressed syllables with heavy, high-sonority rhymes (with a long vowel or a sonorant coda). Subject to this pho- notactic constraint, we formulate the following basic generalization: by default, stød is assigned to a stressed syllable at the word level unless some disyllabic domain was constructed at the stem level. Stem-level disyllabic domains arise when either the root is underlyingly disyllabic, or a suffix is attached at the stem level. We demonstrate that this simple generalization interacts with regular phonological phenomena (e. g. lexical word-final extrametricality and epenthesis in rising-sonority clusters) and morphologically specific patterns to derive precisely the attested paradigms of stød assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis relies on widely accepted principles of morphology-phonology interaction, and is consistent with relevant morphological generalizations: for instance, the unpro- ductive plural suffix -e always shows root attachment, triggering stem-level phonology (Giegerich 1999, Bermúdez-Otero 2018), whilst for the productive -er suffix this pattern is exceptional. In the paper, we show that the basic analysis extends to disyllabic and longer nouns, nominal compounds, and simple and prefixed verbs, as well as to exceptional patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, we show that a metrical approach to accentual distinctions (Morén-Duolljá 2013, Köhnlein 2016, 2019) extends readily beyond ‘tonal’ accents to other distinctions such as stød (Iosad 2016, Morrison 2019). Furthermore, integrating the metrical, domain-based approach with the principles of Stratal Phonology yields a consistent and empirically adequate account of this phenomenon that builds on a small number of first principles. This, we suggest, reinforces the nature of both Stratal Phonology and the metrical view of accentuation as productive research programmes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>29mfm</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/29mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/29mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented (with Yonatan Goldshtein) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/&#34;&gt;a talk on the synchrony of Danish stød&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/mfm/29mfm.html&#34;&gt;29th Manchester Phonology meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonology in the Soviet Union</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This invited contribution to a collection on the history of phonology explores the history of phonological studies in the USSR. I offer a short history of phonology in Russia and the USSR before the formation of the two main theoretical currents (the &amp;lsquo;Leningrad&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Moscow&amp;rsquo; schools), and emphasize both their mutual common roots and their closeness to other structuralist frameworks, in particular Prague phonology. I discuss the differences between the two schools both in their approach to the phoneme and in their analysis of morphophonological alternations. Throughout, the focus is on the ways in which a focus on Russian shaped the directions of phonological thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>History of phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/history-of-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/history-of-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>History of Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/oxhop/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/oxhop/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/history-of-phonology/&#34;&gt;paper on phonology in the Soviet Union&lt;/a&gt; has appeared in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-oxford-history-of-phonology-9780198796800?cc=uk&amp;amp;lang=en&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oxford History of Phonology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Elan Dresher and Harry van der Hulst.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Romance</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/romance/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/romance/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Length and quantity in Romance</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/mrl/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/mrl/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this chapter we consider the phonological status and patterning
of vowel and consonant length and syllabic quantity across Romance
varieties. The chapter is divided into two parts. In the first
section, we provide an overview of the status of vowel and consonant
length in the modern Romance varieties and describe the diachronic
context. Synchronically, the presence of a phonemic contrast between
short and long vowels is characteristic particularly of Gallo-Romance
(including the varieties of northern Italy and Alpine Romance); some
kind of distinction between short and long vowels and/or consonants
(not necessarily one with phonemic significance) is found in a broader
range of varieties, primarily in Italy. Diachronic traces of length,
however, are found across most Romance languages. The second section
takes up the question of phonological weight and shows that
weight-sensitive patterns, primarily relating to the placement of
stress, minimality requirements, and prosodic morphology, are
pervasive throughout the family, even in languages without
phonological length distinctions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>aarhus</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/aarhus/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/aarhus/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented an invited &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/&#34;&gt;talk on the origin of West Jutland stod&lt;/a&gt; at the Jutland Prosody Workshop organized at Aarhus University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The origin of West Jutland stød</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I offer a reconstruction of the history of the so-called West Jutland stød that reaffirms the proposition that it is a reflex of Proto-Nordic preaspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Irish</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/irish/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/irish/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Mrl</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/mrl/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 10:24:26 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/mrl/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/mrl/&#34;&gt;overview paper on length and quantity in the Romance languages&lt;/a&gt; (with &lt;a href=&#34;https://research.vu.nl/en/persons/w-leo-wetzels&#34;&gt;Leo Wetzels&lt;/a&gt;) has appeared in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/9783110550283/html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manual of Romance phonetics and phonology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Christoph Gabriel, Randall Gess and Trudel Meisenburg.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Mons</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/mons/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/mons/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/mons/&#34;&gt;keynote presentation&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.uit.no/tavla/artikkel?p_document_id=720437&#34;&gt;19. møte om norsk språk&lt;/a&gt; conference in Tromsø on the application of the life cycle model of phonological change to some data from Norwegian (and Western Nordic more generally) has been postponed to 2022. I will, however, present some of this material in a poster presentation at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/symposium-on-historical-phonology/eshp5/&#34;&gt;5th Edinburgh Symposium on Historical Phonology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Frlsu2021</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/frlsu2021/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/frlsu2021/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented (with David Wheatley) a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/frlsu2021/&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on the acoustics of ‘fortis’ and ‘lenis’ in Donegal Irish as documented in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.doegen.ie&#34;&gt;Doegen recordings archive&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frlsu2021.anglistik.uni-muenchen.de/index.html&#34;&gt;13th Conference of the Forum for Research on the Languages of Scotland and Ulster&lt;/a&gt;. We will also present this talk at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dias.ie/2021/11/12/tionol-2021/&#34;&gt;Tionól 2021&lt;/a&gt; at the School of Celtic Studies, Dublin Institute for Advanced Study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Acoustic correlates of the fortis/lenis distinction in early 20th century Donegal Irish</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/frlsu2021/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/frlsu2021/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we address the long-standing question of how the
distinction between fortis and lenis consonants arose and functioned
in Old Irish, and how it is reflected in the present-day Gaelic
languages. We report an empirical study of early-twentieth-century
Donegal Irish recordings from the Doegen collection. The results show
that fortis sonorants (traditionally written /L/ and /N/) displayed
significantly greater duration than the equivalent lenis sonorants
(/l/ and /n/) both word-medially and word-finally, suggesting that the
fortis/lenis distinction did correspond to a duration distinction.
Furthermore, ‘voiceless’ stops /p t k/ displayed significantly greater
duration than ‘voiced stops’ /b d g/. The magnitude of the effect
suggests that the voiced/voiceless contrast in stops during this
period was an aspiration contrast, with postvocalic voiceless stops
showing preaspiration (Ní Chasaide 1986; Iosad 2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a longstanding dispute surrounding the ordering and
relationship of lenition and degemination in the Gaelic languages, how
duration and fortis/lenis status interacted in the Old Irish period,
and how these changes led to synchronic phonemic distinctions in Old
Irish and the modern Gaelic languages. In particular, it is unclear
whether postvocalic stops Old Irish showed a length distinction, and
how the length distinction related to the fortis/lenis distinction in
the sonorants. For both Old Irish (Thurneysen 1946) and Donegal Modern
Irish (Quiggin 1906; Wagner 1958–1969) it has been suggested that both
stops and sonorants were lengthened after a short vowel (cross-cutting
the laryngeal contrast in stops), although these accounts are disputed
(Greene 1956).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our results suggest that there was no across-the-board fortition in
Donegal Irish: in stops, duration follows laryngeal contrast, and in
sonorants it follows the fortis/lenis distinction. We explore the
dialectological and historical implications of this result.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Rnag</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/rnag/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 21:06:34 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/rnag/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/&#34;&gt;paper on the phonology of Gaelic tonal accent&lt;/a&gt; has appeared in the proceedings volume from Rannsachadh na Gàidhlig 10.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The phonology of Gaelic tonal accent</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;It is well known that many varieties of Gaelic show an opposition
between two classes of words that is implemented by suprasegmental
means such as pitch and glottalization. These phenomena have been
compared to the ‘tonal accents’ of the North and West Germanic
languages (notably by Ternes 1980, 2006), and a number of analyses
have been proposed in the theoretical linguis- tics literature. In
this paper, I summarize the patterns found across traditional
varieties of Scottish Gaelic, and focus on the (limited number of)
synchronic alternations that involve accent-related phenomena. In
particular, I address the interaction between tonal accents and
vowel-zero alterna- tions. I argue that it further supports the
analyses of Gaelic tonal accents as reflecting differences in
syllabification or more generally metrical structure, as envisaged by
Oftedal (1956); Clements (1986); Smith (1999); Iosad (2015) and most
recently in the comprehensive analysis by Morrison (2019). I also
discuss what kind of new data is necessary to make further progress in
our understanding of the accentual phonology of Gaelic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Scottish Gaelic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/scottish-gaelic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/scottish-gaelic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Welsh</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/welsh/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The ATR/Laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I consider an unusual sound change and synchronic alternation in south-eastern dialects of Welsh, traditionally referred to as ‘provection’ (Welsh &lt;em&gt;calediad&lt;/em&gt;). This phenomenon involves the ‘devoicing’ of stops following stressed vowels. I suggest that it may be the result of a typologically rare sort of vowel-consonant featural interaction, where ‘devoicing’ is triggered by tense vowels. This is unexpected typologically, since tongue root advancement — often a correlate of ‘tense’ vowel quality — is more frequently associated with voicing rather than devoicing in obstruents. I argue that in Welsh the phonologization of the quality distinction in stressed vowels has created a system where such an interaction is dispreferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that the unusual consonant-vowel interaction in south-eastern Welsh is facilitated by the phonological ambiguity of the ‘tenseness’ contrast in vowels. Although the distinction between ‘tense’ and ‘lax’ vowel pairs is made consistently in most Welsh dialects, it is often fairly inert phonologically. This makes it possible for it to become involved in a variety of phonological processes. I survey the diversity of ways in which quantity-quality interactions in vowels found across Welsh dialects, and argue that the attested multiple paths of phonologization support a bottom-up, substance-free approach to phonologization. I suggest that the particular strength of the substance-free model lies in its ability to account for different — sometimes drastically so — phonological behaviour emerging from ambiguous data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Substance-free phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/substance-free-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/substance-free-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Feature theory</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/feature-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/feature-theory/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Off</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/off/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 13:06:26 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2021/off/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I am on research leave in &lt;sup&gt;2021&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2022&lt;/sub&gt;, and am not teaching any courses in this session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
