<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Pavel Iosad in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 11:59:28 GMT</updated>



<item>
<title>Pavel Iosad</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>News</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 11:57:37 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Amc</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/amc/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 11:57:37 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/amc/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented an invited &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/amc2024/&#34;&gt;talk on the status of phonological patterns in language contact&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amc.lel.ed.ac.uk/amc-symposium/fourth-amc-symposium/&#34;&gt;Fourth AMC Symposium&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Presentations</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Language contact</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/language-contact/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/language-contact/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>In search of (lost?) contact-induced change in phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/amc2024/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/amc2024/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is a keynote presentation at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amc.lel.ed.ac.uk/amc-symposium/fourth-amc-symposium/&#34;&gt;Fourth AMC Symposium&lt;/a&gt;: a themed conference on the topic of language contact and language change. In this talk, I explore how we can integrate current approaches in phonological theory and historical phonology with current understanding in the study of language contact. I argue that phonological patterns, especially those that go beyond exchange of matter such as phonemes, require quite specific social and historical conditions to spread by contact. In the talk I show that these conditions may be met more rarely than is sometimes assumed in the literature, both for recipient-language agentivity situations with stable bilingualism and — especially so — for language shift and ‘substrate’ situations. I also point to further challenges presented by phonology for the study of language contact.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Categories</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teachings</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Linguistics and English Language 1A</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/lel1a/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/lel1a/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the introductory linguistics &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; course for all first-year students in Linguistics and English Language. This year, I am the Course Organizer and am teaching the phonetics and skills blocks; in addition, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/graeme-trousdale&#34;&gt;Graeme Trousdale&lt;/a&gt;, I am responsible for the data analysis/language puzzles component of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Teaching</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 17:12:12 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2024&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2025&lt;/sub&gt;, I am convening &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/lel1a/&#34;&gt;Linguistics and English Language 1A&lt;/a&gt; in Semester 1. I am on research leave in Semester 2.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Promotion</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/promotion/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 17:04:02 BST</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/promotion/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I was promoted to Professor, with the award of a personal chair of Synchronic and Diachronic Phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Writings</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Suprasegmental phenomena in Germanic: Tonal accent</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Several Germanic varieties possess a phonological contrast usually referred to as “tonal accent.” They demonstrate phonological contrasts between words that are otherwise identical in their segmental make-up and the location of stress, as in (Urban East) Norwegian &lt;em&gt;bønder&lt;/em&gt; ‘farmers’ and bønner ‘beans’, both segmentally [ˈbønːər]. Usually, the contrast is treated as implemented by pitch trajectories; hence, the name &amp;lsquo;tonal accent.&amp;rsquo; Within Germanic, tonal accent contrasts are found in three (historically, perhaps four) areas. First, they occur in most varieties of Norwegian and Swedish, as well as in some Danish dialects; in addition, most varieties of Danish show a peculiar type of accentual distinction based on laryngealization, traditionally known as stød. Second, they are found in a set of West Germanic dialects along the middle Rhine and the Moselle, the so-called Franconian tonal area. Third, they are reported from many varieties of Low German, specifically North Low Saxon. Finally, they may have been present historically in Frisian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three aspects of Germanic tonal accent systems are of particular interest to linguistic theory. In terms of synchronic analysis, accents have been considered as sui generis objects, as fundamentally tonal phenomena, and as artifacts of contrasts in metrical (foot) structure and its mapping to intonation. Diachronically, Germanic accents are a poor fit to the cross-linguistic typology of tonogenesis: their development is intimately tied to processes manipulating metrical structures, such as vowel lengthening, syllable deletion and insertion, and clash resolution. Finally, they offer some enlightening case studies with respect to the role of language contact in the development of prosodic systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Prosodic structure</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Papers</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Germanic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/germanic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/germanic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Egg</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/egg/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/egg/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I taught two courses at this year’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eggschool.org&#34;&gt;Eastern Generative Grammar&lt;/a&gt; summer school in Brașov, Romania: one on &lt;em&gt;Slavic phonology&lt;/em&gt; and an &lt;em&gt;Introduction to representations and contrast&lt;/em&gt;. The course materials are available on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://egg2024.anghyflawn.net&#34;&gt;dedicated website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Oxfordre</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/oxfordre/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/oxfordre/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/&#34;&gt;overview of Germanic tonal accents&lt;/a&gt; appeared in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oxfordre.com/linguistics&#34;&gt;The Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Germanic linguistics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Representations and contrast</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/egg2024-representations/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/egg2024-representations/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The topic of this course is how segmental representations can help understand phonological behaviour, and in particular the link between subsegmental structure and phonological activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insight that the presence of phonological structure (such as a featural specification) and its activity has a long history in phonological theory. An influential early formalization of this idea was the theory of ‘markedness’ (understood quite literally as the presence of a ‘mark’) in Prague School phonology, where it was also linked to the idea that structure was built in the context of a language’s system of contrasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea boils down to three key elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Underspecification: phonological inactivity or ‘weakness’ follows from absence of structure&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Markedness equals size: behaviours characteristic of ‘marked’ categories do not need to be stipulated if they simply derive from the presence (as opposed to absence) of phonological structure&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structure is downstream of contrast: phonological specifications are built only when necessary to make lexical distinctions (or for other pressing reasons)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this course, we will consider how these ideas have been reflected in current phonological theory, what challenges have been presented to them, and how they could be answered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course materials are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://egg2024.anghyflawn.net/representations-contrast-about.html#course-annotation&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Slavic Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/egg2024-slavic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/egg2024-slavic/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The sound patterns of the Slavic languages played a foundational role in the development of Western phonological theory. Both structuralist and generative phonology share a history (or pre-history) of close engagement with Slavic data and extensive traditions of its analysis. Despite these historical links, the approaches and results achieved in these traditions in dealing with essentially the same data can be strikingly different. Much of this divergence can be ascribed to differences in how to approach the close and complex interaction of morphology and phonology that is characteristic of Slavic languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this course, we will critically consider a number of Slavic sound patterns and focus on how they have been treated within the generative/SPE tradition. Despite significant changes in the general approach over time, including the development of nonlinear phonology and a swing towards and away from surface-oriented theories such as OT, the approach to Slavic phonology has remained surprisingly stable, and in some ways unchanged since the pioneering era of the 1950s and 1960s. Much current work still operates with abstract underlying representations and long synchronic derivations that more or less explicitly recapitulate historical developments — an approach that has been problematized or fully abandoned in other empirical domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will ask if it is still true consonant palatalization always derives from following front vowels; if consonant-final words still end in yer vowels; how many vowel phonemes we need, and how to find this out; when to give up on phonology; and how to tie it all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course materials are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://egg2024.anghyflawn.net/slavic-phonology-about.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Britac</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/britac/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/britac/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I was awarded a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thebritishacademy.ac.uk/news/the-british-academy-awards-44-new-mid-career-fellowships-to-support-outstanding-shape-researchers/&#34;&gt;British Academy Mid-Career Fellowship&lt;/a&gt; for January–December 2025 with a project on &lt;em&gt;Phonological microvariation in sound change: Mid vowel alternations in the Slavic languages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The moraic mess that is Danish</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/fino2024/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/fino2024/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In moraic theory, particular syllables of a languages are typically defined as either heavy of light for all phonological rules (Hyman 1985). However, some languages seem to treat the same syllables as light for some rules and heavy for others (e.g. Davis 2011:129-132). To account for such behaviour, Hayes (1995) proposes that moraic structure can be organized as a layered grid, where the bottom layer, typically involved in syllable-internal patterns, underlies the top layer, typically involved in higher-level prosodic structure. The present paper argues that Danish is just such a language: distinguishing two separate criteria for assigning weight to syllables allows us to understand the phonology of stød. We implement a Stratal Phonology analysis (Bermúdez-Otero 2018) by reimagining Hayes’ moraic grid representation as recursion at the level of the mora (Iosad 2013). Specifically, we suggest that maximal moraic projections are involved in syllable-level processes (Hayes’ bottom layer) and minimal moraic projections are involved in the processes assigning stød (Hayes’ top layer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous models of syllable weight in Danish have focused either on syllable-internal structure (e.g. Vazquez-Larruscaín 2021), or on the distribution of stød (e.g. Basbøll 2005, 2008). The key fact of syllable structure is that the maximal syllable in Danish is CVXsC: &lt;em&gt;host&lt;/em&gt; [hoːˀst] ‘cough’, &lt;em&gt;tekst&lt;/em&gt; [ˈtɛkst] ‘text’. In this account, the ‘core’ syllable is maximally bimoraic, /sC/ is the maximal ‘appendix’, and moraic structure is assigned without regard to sonority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key fact of the phonology of stød is that the second mora needs to be sonorous for it. When this condition is met, stød is contrastive: &lt;em&gt;kvart&lt;/em&gt; [ˈkhvɑːt] ‘quarter’ vs. &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; [ˈstɑːˀt] ‘start’. In syllables with only one sonorous mora, (&lt;em&gt;kat&lt;/em&gt; [ˈkhæt] ‘cat’), the contrast is neutralized. Basbøll argues that only sonorant segments can project morae, and further, that stød is the default prosody of the second mora of heavy syllables. In this analysis, a syllable with two sonorous morae that does not have stød needs special marking. In particular, word-final sonorants can be specified as extra-prosodic: in this case, they do not contribute to moraic structure, inhibiting stød (&lt;em&gt;ven&lt;/em&gt; [ˈvɛn] ‘friend’), as long as they remain word-final. The addition of (most) suffixes causes them to undergo default mora assignment, which results in the appearance of stød (&lt;em&gt;vennen&lt;/em&gt; [ˈvɛnˀn̩] ‘the friend’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper develops a model that integrates these two main insights. Vazquez-Larruscaín’s (2021) phonotactic generalizations apply to maximal moraic projections, which are constructed without reference to sonority. Mora recursion, by contrast, is only licensed by high sonority: therefore, obstruents are unable to support non-minimal projections and cannot carry stød. Sonorants do project recursive morae by default, but can be blocked by faithfulness from doing so, accounting to lexical marking of non-stød, as in Basbøll’s model. We show how constraint interaction in a Stratal OT grammar derives the contextual nature of this faithfulness effect. As a result, our model retains the full empirical coverage of the competing approaches whilst simplifying the necessary lexical specification and capturing the morphological influences on stød assignment (Goldshtein 2023, Goldshtein &amp;amp; Iosad 2022).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>North Germanic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/north-germanic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/north-germanic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Fino</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/fino/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2024/fino/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/fino2024/&#34;&gt;work on Danish stød&lt;/a&gt; (with &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=UyhM_K4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Yonatan Goldshtein&lt;/a&gt;) at the &lt;em&gt;Fonologi i Norden&lt;/em&gt; 2024 meeting at Stockholm University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Current Issues in Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/current-issues/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2024/current-issues/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This advanced course introduces students to a variety of live research issues in phonological theory. I teach this course with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/benjamin-molineaux&#34;&gt;Benjamin Molineaux&lt;/a&gt;. This year, I am the Course Organizer in additional to being responsible for some of the teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Romance</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/romance/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/romance/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Length in strange places</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/eshp6/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/eshp6/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;(Poster presentations)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present-day Celtic languages are characterized by a typologically relatively unusual contrast between &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; coronal sonorants. It is especially developed in the Gaelic languages. Here, &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;nn ll rr&lt;/em&gt; contrast with &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;l n r&lt;/em&gt; in postvocalic position (Irish &lt;em&gt;geal&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;bright&amp;rsquo; vs. &lt;em&gt;geall&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;promise&amp;rsquo;). Furthermore, they participate in the initial mutation system, where the &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; sonorants generally occur in the unmutated (&amp;ldquo;radical&amp;rdquo;) grade, and &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; ones in the &amp;ldquo;lenited&amp;rdquo; grade, which historically corresponds to postvocalic contexts. In the Brythonic languages, the most notable correspondent of this pattern is found in Welsh, where &lt;em&gt;ll&lt;/em&gt; acts as the &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; counterpart of : they contrast postvocalically, and is generally the radical consonant in mutation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, the &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; sonorants word-medially are long and the &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; ones are short (Stifter 2023). This circumstance is still reflected in their synchronic behaviour: both Irish (Ní Chiosáin 1991) and Scottish Gaelic (Morrison 2020) show patterns that are insightfully analysed if the &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; sonorants are contrastively moraic. However, quantity is rarely implicated in their surface realization (but see Lewin 2023). Instead, &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; sonorants are distinguished by properties such as place of articulation (Carnie 2002; Musil 2017, 2019; Nance &amp;amp; Kirkham 2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The behaviour of Celtic sonorants is unusual. Word-medially, &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; sonorants behave as the marked category, as they need to be specified as mora-bearing. This reflects their historical status as the marked member of the length opposition. Word-initially, the situation is reversed: &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; sonorants occur in the elsewhere context, while &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; ones are produced by specified mutation triggers. &lt;em&gt;Prima facie&lt;/em&gt;, this suggests a lengthening or fortition of sonorants in a strong (word-initial, non-intervocalic) position. Although not entirely unexpected (Ségéral &amp;amp; Scheer 2008; Easterday &amp;amp; Bybee 2019), it is somewhat odd to see this process involve a contrastive feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I discuss the historical origins of this pattern and draw some parallels to similar phenomena elsewhere. Specifically, I argue that the spread of the pattern to initial position did not represent a lengthening, but rather a change involving place features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The behaviour of sonorants in initial mutation across Celtic follows an implicational hierarchy. The same hierarchy is observed in several aspects of Romance historical phonology. In particular, it determines the preservation of original length contrasts in Western Romance (Brandão de Carvalho 1989). Remarkably, it is also found in the reflexes of initial sonorants in Ibero-Romance. Whilst the distinction between Latin [l n r] and [ll nn rr] is reflected in terms of place and manner (Spanish [l n ɾ] vs. [ʎ ɲ r]) word-medially, initially we find the &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; reflexes for [r] in Spanish, [r l] in Catalan, and [r l n] in Asturian (Cravens 2002).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that the spread of &amp;ldquo;quantity&amp;rdquo; to word-initial position can be understood as a consequence of the transphonologization of quantity to place and its interaction with the life cycle of intervocalic sandhi processes. Both Celtic and Ibero-Romance can be reconstructed with postvocalic lenition crossing word boundaries. I suggest that once original suprasegmental (quantity) distinctions in sonorants became available as subsegmental (featural) representational entities, it was possible for them to be incorporated into the pattern of sandhi lenition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I show how the proposed account captures the markedness paradox in Celtic by divorcing the place distinctions from distinctive quantity (moraicity). This also accounts for the fact that mutation patterns persist even when earlier word-medial quantity is lost, as in Brythonic. Furthermore, the Celtic parallel can shed light on the Ibero-Romance patterns without recourse to a poorly evidenced process of sandhi gemination (parallel to Italian &lt;em&gt;raddoppiamento&lt;/em&gt;) proposed by Cravens (2002).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Celtic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/celtic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/celtic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Welsh</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/welsh/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Irish</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/irish/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/irish/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Initial consonant mutations</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/initial-consonant-mutations/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/initial-consonant-mutations/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Companion</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/companion/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/companion/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/celtic-mutations-companion/&#34;&gt;overview of Celtic initial consonant mutations&lt;/a&gt; appeared in &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/book/10.1002/9781119693604&#34;&gt;The Wiley Blackwell Companion to Morphology&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Peter Ackema, Sabrina Bendjaballah, Eulàlia Bonet, and Antonio Fábregas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Breton</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/breton/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title></title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/celtic-mutations-companion/</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/celtic-mutations-companion/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The Celtic languages are characterized by an elaborate system of alternations of word-initial segments, traditionally known as ‘consonant mutations’. Although historically they arose from across-the-board phonological sandhi, they are now deeply embedded in morphosyntactic processes. They are relatively phonologically coherent, but also non-concatenative, and sensitive to a wide range of lexical, morphological, syntactic and semantic factors. As a result, Celtic mutations present an important test bed for theories of word structure and its interactions with both phonology and syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonological Theory</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/phonological-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/phonological-theory/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2023&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2024&lt;/sub&gt;, I am fully responsible for this course. Students will build on fundamental concepts in phonology to engage with a range of intermediate and advanced topics, with a focus on the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of phonological theory: contrast, phonemes, allophones, alternations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivations, underlying representations, rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process interaction and rule ordering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, there is a strong emphasis on building data analysis and problem solving skills. Teaching sessions are built around discussion of puzzles and data sets. Students are assessed via a semester-long project focused on describing and analysing the phonological patterns of a language of their choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course is also offered for MSc students (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drps.ed.ac.uk/23-24/dpt/cxlasc11148.htm&#34;&gt;LASC11148&lt;/a&gt;). It is suitable for postgraduate students who have had some previous exposure to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Linguistics and English Language 1A</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/lel1a/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/lel1a/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the introductory linguistics &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; course for all first-year students in Linguistics and English Language. This year, I am the Course Organizer and am teaching the phonetics, language acquisition, and language and communication blocks; in addition, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/graeme-trousdale&#34;&gt;Graeme Trousdale&lt;/a&gt;, I am responsible for the data analysis/language puzzles component of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Sem1 Teaching</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/sem1-teaching/</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/sem1-teaching/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In Semester 1 &lt;sup&gt;2023&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2024&lt;/sub&gt;, I am convening the courses &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/lel1a/&#34;&gt;Linguistics and English Language 1A&lt;/a&gt; (pre-Honours) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/phonological-theory/&#34;&gt;Phonological Theory&lt;/a&gt; (Honours/MSc).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>The ATR/Laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I consider an unusual sound change and synchronic alternation in south-eastern dialects of Welsh, traditionally referred to as ‘provection’ (Welsh &lt;em&gt;calediad&lt;/em&gt;). This phenomenon involves the ‘devoicing’ of stops following stressed vowels. I suggest that it may be the result of a typologically rare sort of vowel-consonant featural interaction, where ‘devoicing’ is triggered by tense vowels. This is unexpected typologically, since tongue root advancement — often a correlate of ‘tense’ vowel quality — is more frequently associated with voicing rather than devoicing in obstruents. I argue that in Welsh the phonologization of the quality distinction in stressed vowels has created a system where such an interaction is dispreferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that the unusual consonant-vowel interaction in south-eastern Welsh is facilitated by the phonological ambiguity of the ‘tenseness’ contrast in vowels. Although the distinction between ‘tense’ and ‘lax’ vowel pairs is made consistently in most Welsh dialects, it is often fairly inert phonologically. This makes it possible for it to become involved in a variety of phonological processes. I survey the diversity of ways in which quantity-quality interactions in vowels found across Welsh dialects, and argue that the attested multiple paths of phonologization support a bottom-up, substance-free approach to phonologization. I suggest that the particular strength of the substance-free model lies in its ability to account for different — sometimes drastically so — phonological behaviour emerging from ambiguous data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Substance-free phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/substance-free-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/substance-free-phonology/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Feature theory</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/feature-theory/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/feature-theory/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Calediad Published</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/calediad-published/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/calediad-published/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/&#34;&gt;paper on the interaction of ATR and laryngeal features in Welsh&lt;/a&gt; was published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/primitives-of-phonological-structure-9780198791126?cc=gb&amp;amp;lang=en&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primitives of phonological structure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, ed.  Florian Breit, Bert Botma, Marijn van &amp;rsquo;t Veer, and Marc van Oostendorp.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A metrical approach to ternarity in Northern European accentual contrasts</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/30mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/30mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Many languages of Northern Europe possess typologically non-trivial systems of prosodic con- trasts, analysed variously as ‘tonal/pitch accent’ (North and West Germanic, Gaelic, Baltic), laryngeal accent/stød (North Germanic, Baltic, Finnic, Gaelic), and ternary quantity distinctions (Finnic, Sámi, Gaelic). In this paper, I show that despite the diversity of phonetic correlates, the fundamental structure of these systems is almost perfectly isomorphic. Specifically, they are often three-way contrasts between stressed syllables that lack the segmental material to support the accentual contrast, and two kinds of stressed syllables that do have such segmental content: one bearing some marked accentual specification and one lacking it. I argue that this generalization is especially well captured by ‘metrical’ (more specifically foot-based) analyses of tonal accents (e. g. Morén-Duolljá 2013, Köhnlein 2016, Iosad 2016, Morrison 2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the contrasts are treated as two-way distinctions with a markedness asymmetry: for instance, Danish stød is considered the marked pole of the contrast (Basbøll 2005), while the relative markedness of North Germanic tonal accents is much debated (e. g. Kristoffersen 2006). Importantly, the two-way contrasts are often neutralized in certain segmental contexts, such as in final stressed syllables (Swedish/Norwegian) or in syllables with insufficiently sonorous rhymes (Danish stød, Franconian and Baltic accents).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borrowing a term from the Danish tradition (e. g. Grønnum &amp;amp; Basbøll 2001, cf. also Liberman 1984), I will refer to syllables that cannot support the prosodic contrasts as lacking accentual basis. In the paper, I show that different accentual systems in Northern Europe exhibit this basic ternary structure, differing primarily in how they define accentual basis, and in the mechanisms of default vs. non-default prosodification that are responsible for the contrast in syllables with basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, basis is usually defined by size: accentual contrasts can require a bimoraic high-sonority coda (Danish stød, Baltic, Franconian), a bimoraic trochaic domain (Scottish Gaelic), a bimoraic voiced domain (Livonian), or a disyllabic domain (North Germanic tonal accents, Danish short-vowel stød). This framing allows us to treat the ternary systems of languages like Estonian and Aanaar Sámi, where the relevant dimension is quantity rather than ‘accent’, within the same framework: effectively, a light stressed syllable (Estonian Q1 [ˈlinɑ] ‘flax.GEN’) is ‘too small’ to provide accentual basis, whilst heavy syllables (Q2/‘long’ [ˈlinːɑ] ‘town.GEN’ and Q3/‘overlong’ [ˈlinːnɑ] ‘town.PART’) both have sufficient moraic material to support the contrast (cf. the analysis of Estonian Q3 as ‘heavy accent’ [e.g. Hint 1997, Kuznetsova 2018]).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental identity of ‘ternary quantity’ and ‘accentual contrasts’ is highlighted by cases that submit to either analysis. A notable example is Low German, variously treated as ‘tonal’/‘accentual’ (Prehn 2007, Höder 2020), showing ternary quantity distinctions (Ternes 1981, Chapman 1993), or defining accentual basis by vowel quality (Kohler 2001). A variety of cues of similar structures is also attested in Scottish Gaelic (Ternes 2006), which Morrison (2019) analyses in terms of foot structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argue that metrical approaches such as those of Köhnlein (2016) and
Morrison (2019) provide exactly the right level of abstraction to
capture the fundamental ternary structure underlying many Northern
European accentual systems, whilst also allowing for a variety of
phonetic realizations. It is also predicted that ‘metrical’ accentual
contrasts can combine with other prosodic specifications like tone to
produce more elaborate systems: this is the case in Latvian (Krämer
forthcoming). I argue that metrical approaches are superior to
frameworks that treat lexically distinctive tones as the analytical
key to ‘accentual’ contrast (Hyman 2009, Gussenhoven &amp;amp; Peters 2019):
in particular, I suggest that ‘tonal’ approaches are unable to explain
the necessary link between size and the definition of accentual basis.
Metrical analyses, by contrast, offer an insightful and unified
framework for a range of apparently disparate phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>30mfm</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/30mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2023/30mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I presented &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/30mfm/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A metrical approach to ternarity in Northern European accentual contrasts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/mfm/30mfm.html&#34;&gt;30th Manchester Phonology Meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Historical Phonology</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/historical-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/historical-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this course (co-taught with my colleagues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lel.ed.ac.uk/homes/patrick&#34;&gt;Patrick Honeybone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.homepages.ed.ac.uk/bmolinea/&#34;&gt;Benjamin Molineaux&lt;/a&gt;) we consider a variety of issues connected to phonological change. Throughout the course, we address questions such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we reconstruct the phonology of past language states?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What types of phonological changes are attested?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can synchronic phonological theory assist us in the study of historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn about the human language faculty by studying historical phonology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, I expect to cover the following topics :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mechanisms and types of phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and phonological change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-Linguistic Variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, I am not Course Organizer any more, but do contribute to the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Dialects of English in Britain and Ireland</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/doe/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/teaching/2023/doe/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course provides a detailed account of dialects of English in Britain and Ireland. It examines how these varieties differ in terms of their phonetics, phonology, morphology, syntax and lexis. You will have the opportunity to look in detail at specific dialects, specifically at their linguistic features, historical origins, relations to other dialects, and the current forces which are shaping their development, from dialectological, sociolinguistic, perceptual and theoretical linguistic perspectives. Dialect and language contact, dialect levelling and new dialect formation are also explored. In &lt;sup&gt;2022&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2023&lt;/sub&gt;, I teach the component on the course related to Irish English and the role of contact in the development of certain varieties of Scots and Scottish English.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Akfs</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/akfs/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/news/2022/akfs/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/arne-kruse-fs/&#34;&gt;paper on the historical sociolinguistics of North Germanic influence on the Gaelic languages&lt;/a&gt; has appeared in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ssns.org.uk/monograph/islands-2022/&#34;&gt;a Festschrift for Arne Kruse&lt;/a&gt;. Read more about the book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ed.ac.uk/literatures-languages-cultures/news/festive-festschrifts.&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Gaelic</title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/gaelic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/gaelic/</guid>
<description></description>
</item>



<item>
<title></title>
<link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/arne-kruse-fs/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/arne-kruse-fs/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;What was the sociolinguistic situation in the North Atlantic in the Viking Age and its aftermath? In the near-total absence of reliable, contemporary historical sources, enquiry into language maintenance and shift in the Northern Isles, the Hebrides, and the Irish Sea basin is a fascinating, multidisciplinary enterprise, to which Arne Kruse has made very significant contributions. In this chapter, I consider how the Western Norse vernacular of the Scandinavian settlers in much of this region was ultimately replaced by the Gaelic languages. My perspective is grounded in historical sociolinguistics: I interrogate what interplay between the sociohistorical context and specific types of contact-induced change could be expected in this region in the medieval period, and try to match these predictions against what is known about Norse-Gaelic contact.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
