<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Germanic on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/germanic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Germanic on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/germanic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Suprasegmental phenomena in Germanic: Tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</guid>
      <description>Several Germanic varieties possess a phonological contrast usually referred to as “tonal accent.” They demonstrate phonological contrasts between words that are otherwise identical in their segmental make-up and the location of stress, as in (Urban East) Norwegian bønder ‘farmers’ and bønner ‘beans’, both segmentally [ˈbønːər]. Usually, the contrast is treated as implemented by pitch trajectories; hence, the name &amp;lsquo;tonal accent.&amp;rsquo; Within Germanic, tonal accent contrasts are found in three (historically, perhaps four) areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonological convergence in north-western Europe</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</guid>
      <description>I offer a framework for understanding convergent diachronic developments in the phonological systems of unrelated languages, informed by the life cycle of phonological processes. I focus on preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the traditional /p t k/ series) in several languages of north-west Europe where preaspiration cannot be due to shared inheritance, including the North Germanic languages, varieties of English, the Gaelic languages, Welsh, and the Sámi languages. Preaspiration is often claimed to be typologically rare and diachronically unstable (Silverman 2003, Blevins 2017); hence, its appearance in unrelated languages with a history of contact is often ascribed to that contact (Marstrander 1932, Posti 1954, Wagner 1964, Borgstrøm 1974, Salmons 1992, Gunnar Ólafur Hansson 2001, Rießler 2008, McKenna 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in sonorant-consonant clusters in areal perspective</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in lC and rC clusters</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</guid>
      <description>The insertion of an unstressed vowel in lC and rC clusters of non-rising sonority (fil[ə]m), is widely known as characteristic of Irish English. It is frequently cited as a substrate feature carried over from Irish, where this process is productive (Ní Chiosáin 1999), as it is in the related Scottish Gaelic. However, this feature is also known from Older Scots, modern Scots dialects (Maguire 2017), and traditional varieties of English. Therefore, it might be an areal effect in the British and Irish Isles; notably, a similar phenomenon is also attested in Welsh (e.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>