<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Papers on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Papers on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Морфонологическая стратификация в русском языке | Stratal phonology and Russian morphophonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</guid>
      <description>В работе предлагается анализ фрагмента русской морфонологии – чередования e~’o и некоторых связанных с ним явлений – в духе порождающих стратификационных подходов наподобие лексической фонологии. Цель работы – показать, что это чередование обладает целым рядом свойств, обычно характерных для основообразующих фонологических правил. Таким образом, утверждается, что, с одной стороны, русский материал поддерживает модель, предполагающую стратификацию морфонологических систем, а с другой – стратификационные модели открывают продуктивные подходы к анализу русской морфонологии, эксплицитно связывающие морфонологическую структуру как с фонологическими закономерностями, так и с морфологической и семантической структурой русских слов.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
      <description>‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>