<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Papers on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Papers on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Suprasegmental phenomena in Germanic: Tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</guid>
      <description>Several Germanic varieties possess a phonological contrast usually referred to as “tonal accent.” They demonstrate phonological contrasts between words that are otherwise identical in their segmental make-up and the location of stress, as in (Urban East) Norwegian bønder ‘farmers’ and bønner ‘beans’, both segmentally [ˈbønːər]. Usually, the contrast is treated as implemented by pitch trajectories; hence, the name &amp;lsquo;tonal accent.&amp;rsquo; Within Germanic, tonal accent contrasts are found in three (historically, perhaps four) areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/celtic-mutations-companion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/celtic-mutations-companion/</guid>
      <description>The Celtic languages are characterized by an elaborate system of alternations of word-initial segments, traditionally known as ‘consonant mutations’. Although historically they arose from across-the-board phonological sandhi, they are now deeply embedded in morphosyntactic processes. They are relatively phonologically coherent, but also non-concatenative, and sensitive to a wide range of lexical, morphological, syntactic and semantic factors. As a result, Celtic mutations present an important test bed for theories of word structure and its interactions with both phonology and syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/arne-kruse-fs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/arne-kruse-fs/</guid>
      <description>What was the sociolinguistic situation in the North Atlantic in the Viking Age and its aftermath? In the near-total absence of reliable, contemporary historical sources, enquiry into language maintenance and shift in the Northern Isles, the Hebrides, and the Irish Sea basin is a fascinating, multidisciplinary enterprise, to which Arne Kruse has made very significant contributions. In this chapter, I consider how the Western Norse vernacular of the Scandinavian settlers in much of this region was ultimately replaced by the Gaelic languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dialect variation in Scottish Gaelic nominal morphology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents a dialectometric analysis of Scottish Gaelic morphology, with a focus on the noun phrase, using previously unpublished data from the Linguistic Survey of Scotland. Fifty-five morphological features were extracted across 201 survey points, and the data subjected to a variety of analyses, including cluster analysis, regression, and correlation analysis. We establish that the Gaelic noun system shows robust diatopic (i. e. geographical) variation; this challenges previous assertions in the literature, which describe Gaelic morphosyntax as geographically uniform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Per aspera ad astra</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</guid>
      <description>In this brief paper, I suggest that, contrary to much previous literature, the quality of the yer vowels in Modern Russian is predictable, and does not have to be encoded in the underlying representation. This is a consequence of an approach that rejects the long-standing tradition of positing highly abstract underlying representations, and in particular derives the palatalization of consonants from the backness of following vowels. I argue that the quality of yers is predictable from the context, particularly from the palatalization of preceding consonants and from whether the morphological context drives the otherwise well-known e ~ ’o alternation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Морфонологическая стратификация в русском языке | Stratal phonology and Russian morphophonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</guid>
      <description>В работе предлагается анализ фрагмента русской морфонологии – чередования e~’o и некоторых связанных с ним явлений – в духе порождающих стратификационных подходов наподобие лексической фонологии. Цель работы – показать, что это чередование обладает целым рядом свойств, обычно характерных для основообразующих фонологических правил. Таким образом, утверждается, что, с одной стороны, русский материал поддерживает модель, предполагающую стратификацию морфонологических систем, а с другой – стратификационные модели открывают продуктивные подходы к анализу русской морфонологии, эксплицитно связывающие морфонологическую структуру как с фонологическими закономерностями, так и с морфологической и семантической структурой русских слов.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
      <description>‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>