<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Feature theory on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/feature-theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Feature theory on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/feature-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
      <description>‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ATR/Laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/calediad/</guid>
      <description>I consider an unusual sound change and synchronic alternation in south-eastern dialects of Welsh, traditionally referred to as ‘provection’ (Welsh calediad). This phenomenon involves the ‘devoicing’ of stops following stressed vowels. I suggest that it may be the result of a typologically rare sort of vowel-consonant featural interaction, where ‘devoicing’ is triggered by tense vowels. This is unexpected typologically, since tongue root advancement — often a correlate of ‘tense’ vowel quality — is more frequently associated with voicing rather than devoicing in obstruents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonology and morphosyntax of Breton mutation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</guid>
      <description>I analyse of initial consonant mutation in a Breton dialect, with a focus on establishing the division of labour between phonology and morphology in the triggering of mutation and its phonological expression. I argue that different types of mutation have different status in the grammar: some are purely phonological, others involve subsegmental morphemes with a clear morphosyntactic rationale, and for some the phonological aspects are clear but the morphosyntactic motivation remains obscure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The [ATR]/laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</guid>
      <description>I offer a preliminary analysis of the phenomenon of calediad (&amp;lsquo;provection&amp;rsquo;) in South-Eastern Welsh, whereby &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (lenis) stops become &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; after a stressed vowel. I argue that since vowels before lenis stops are generally long &amp;mdash; and, given the phonology of South Welsh &amp;mdash; tense, provection is an example of vowel-consonant interaction, where the same feature is used for the tense/lax contrast in vowels and laryngeal contrast in consonants. I interpret this as supporting emergent feature theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the dots</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/hxphon2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/hxphon2014/</guid>
      <description>This poster considers the status of the &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo;/&amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; contrasts across Welsh dialects and argues that it was originally an enhancement of quantity, but becomes phonologized in different ways across different dialect. For the latest in this project, see the 23mfm paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge talk to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving segments, but instead features attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/lingua-friulian/</guid>
      <description>Here, I propose an analysis of the interacting between final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian (and other related varieties of northern Italy). Historically, stressed vowels lengthen before voiced obstruents, but this is opacified by final devoicing. I capitalize on phonetic studies showing final devoicing in the language to be incomplete and argue that the process is not in fact opaque: devoicing does not involve neutralization but instead the creation of a third, laryngealy unspecified class of obstruents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified account of the behaviour of high vowels in Bothoa Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer an analysis of gliding in Bothoa Breton, as presented in the thesis. I argue that high vowels (especially [i]) either become glides or coalesce with a preceding consonant, in order to avoid hiatus. However, this pattern is disrupted if the high vowel becomes a nucleus at an earlier stage in the cyclic derivation. This provides an argument for stratal models of phonology-morphology interactions, and a strong argument against Output-Output Correspondence, because some of the exceptional non-gliding cases cannot be explained by reference to a free-standing form with transparent non-gliding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconstructing mutation in Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer the analysis of Breton initial mutations found in my thesis. I argue that there is no such thing as a unified &amp;lsquo;mutation&amp;rsquo; mechanism: instead, this labels covers a variety of processes with different places in the overall grammar. The article-length version of the argument is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my Toronto presentation and to a certain extent my talk from the 6th CLC). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaning licensing mismatches in Welsh</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I propose a new analysis of so-called &amp;lsquo;vowel mutation&amp;rsquo; in Welsh, whereby final syllables (both stressed and unstressed) only allow a reduced inventory (by disallowing [ə]). I argue that these final syllables are specified with something like a suprasegmental feature that triggers a feature co-occurrence effect, and that there is no need for recourse to a mechanism of metrical prominence akin to that borne by stressed syllables (as previously suggested in the literature).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in the north of Italy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents in detail the analysis of Friulian also given at the 18th mfm and later published here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started here. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature geometry meets contrastive specification</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the interaction between vowel lengthening before voiced obstruents and final devoicing in two languages: Friulian and Breton. I argue that such interactions are transparent and involve a three-way laryngeal contrast formalized geometrically, with true voiceless obstruents the most structurally complex and devoiced ones least. The Friulian analysis was later published here and the Breton was largely incorporated into the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian palatalization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</guid>
      <description>In this talk we argue that the traditional view of vowel-driven palatalization in Russian is inadequate, at least for two reasons. First, it relies on a six-vowel interpretation of the Russian inventory that is not adequate from a phonetic perspective. Second, and more importantly, it undergenerates the range of alternations found in Modern Standard Russian. Instead, we argue that palatalization must be driven by a floating feature attached to the left edge of suffixes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
      <description>This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see this talk and this paper). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fonetikk versus fonologi</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</guid>
      <description>Dette er det fyrste føredraget i prosjektet om russisk vokalreduksjon. Sluttversjonen kan ein finne i denne artikkelen.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>