<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dialectology on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/dialectology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dialectology on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/dialectology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dialect variation in Scottish Gaelic nominal morphology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-morphology-glossa/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents a dialectometric analysis of Scottish Gaelic morphology, with a focus on the noun phrase, using previously unpublished data from the Linguistic Survey of Scotland. Fifty-five morphological features were extracted across 201 survey points, and the data subjected to a variety of analyses, including cluster analysis, regression, and correlation analysis. We establish that the Gaelic noun system shows robust diatopic (i. e. geographical) variation; this challenges previous assertions in the literature, which describe Gaelic morphosyntax as geographically uniform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphology and dialectology: A quantitative approach</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</guid>
      <description>We present a study of Gaelic dialectal variation based on the unpublished, morphological section of the Linguistic Survey of Scotland (Gaelic). Our findings indicate that a quantitative (dialectometric) approach can yield important insights into the range of internal variation in Gaelic and elucidate certain issues of language structure. Here, we focus on two questions:
 What patterns of spatial variation are observed in the morphological data? How are different morphological features in the dialects correlated?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>