<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Russian on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/russian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Russian on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/russian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Per aspera ad astra</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</guid>
      <description>In this brief paper, I suggest that, contrary to much previous literature, the quality of the yer vowels in Modern Russian is predictable, and does not have to be encoded in the underlying representation. This is a consequence of an approach that rejects the long-standing tradition of positing highly abstract underlying representations, and in particular derives the palatalization of consonants from the backness of following vowels. I argue that the quality of yers is predictable from the context, particularly from the palatalization of preceding consonants and from whether the morphological context drives the otherwise well-known e ~ ’o alternation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Морфонологическая стратификация в русском языке | Stratal phonology and Russian morphophonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</guid>
      <description>В работе предлагается анализ фрагмента русской морфонологии – чередования e~’o и некоторых связанных с ним явлений – в духе порождающих стратификационных подходов наподобие лексической фонологии. Цель работы – показать, что это чередование обладает целым рядом свойств, обычно характерных для основообразующих фонологических правил. Таким образом, утверждается, что, с одной стороны, русский материал поддерживает модель, предполагающую стратификацию морфонологических систем, а с другой – стратификационные модели открывают продуктивные подходы к анализу русской морфонологии, эксплицитно связывающие морфонологическую структуру как с фонологическими закономерностями, так и с морфологической и семантической структурой русских слов.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bringing it all together</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/farl3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/farl3/</guid>
      <description>Palatalization processes and the e ~ ’o alternation are both classic problems in Russian (morpho)phonology. It is now widely recognized that there is a relationship between the two: where suffixes are relevant to the e ~ ’o alternation, palatalizing suffixes require the front vowel in the preceding morpheme, and non-palatalizing suffixes require the back vowel (see particularly Itkin 1994). This strongly suggests a phonological analysis of the e ~ ’o alternation, which has hitherto proven elusive, primarily since there is no principled, non-circular account of apparent lexical exceptions and of suffixes that are neutral for the purposes of the alternation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Stratal Phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I discuss the nature of evidence for the stratal organization of morphophonological grammar. Much — of course by no means all — of the currently available evidence in favour a stratal approach to morphology-phonology interactions comes from languages such as English, where the stratification of the lexicon has a strong historical rationale, or the Romance languages, where one can often easily observe morphological constituency at the level below the word.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There is no problem of /v/ in Russian phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</guid>
      <description>The dual behaviour of /v/ has been a notorious crux in Russian phonology since at least Jakobson (1956). The basic problem is that /v/ fails to trigger voicing assimilation, like sonorants, but undergoes both assimilation to following obstruents and final devoicing, like obstruents.
The commonest solution in the literature is representational: [v] is treated as a sonorant, either an underlying /w/ (Lightner 1972, Hayes 1984, Kiparsky 1985) or some labial non-glide (Coats &amp;amp; Harshenin 1971, Padgett 2002).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A bad case of excessive computation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</guid>
      <description>I use the analysis of palatalization in Modern Standard Russian offered here to argue that these data do not provide a watertight argument for multilevel phonological computation, and that phonological analysis must be combined with a theory of ordering (such as Stratal OT) if the hypothesis of parallel computation is to be challenged.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How good is the internal evidence for multiple-level phonological computation? A view from Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</guid>
      <description>Relying in part on the analysis of palatalization offered here, I argue that Russian does not provide strong phonology-internal evidence for level ordering, contra suggestions by authors such as Morris Halle and Jerzy Rubach. A more focused argument to the same effect is offered here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian palatalization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</guid>
      <description>In this talk we argue that the traditional view of vowel-driven palatalization in Russian is inadequate, at least for two reasons. First, it relies on a six-vowel interpretation of the Russian inventory that is not adequate from a phonetic perspective. Second, and more importantly, it undergenerates the range of alternations found in Modern Standard Russian. Instead, we argue that palatalization must be driven by a floating feature attached to the left edge of suffixes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fonetikk versus fonologi</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</guid>
      <description>Dette er det fyrste føredraget i prosjektet om russisk vokalreduksjon. Sluttversjonen kan ein finne i denne artikkelen.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>