<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Presentations on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Presentations on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Livssyklusmodellen for fonologiske mønster i norsk og nordisk</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/mons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/mons/</guid>
      <description>[The conference has been rescheduled from November 2021 to November 2022]
I føredraget set eg fram nokre resultat frå ei gransking av fleire fonologiske mønster i norsk (og i den breiare vestnordiske konteksten), med utgangspunkt i livssyklusmodellen for lydendring. I denne modellen skjer lydendring ved at automatisk fonetisk variasjon vert til fonetiske reglar, deretter til kategoriske fonologiske reglar og vidare til sykliske fonologiske reglar i samspel med morfologien. Eg viser korleis denne modellen kastar nytt lys over fleire velkjende mønster i norsk fonologi og morfologi, frå både strukturelle, historiske og dialektologiske standpunkt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical linguistics in schools</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Knowledge about language (KAL) is frequently cited as an important component of literacy strategies, but there is considerable debate about what that knowledge is, how it should be communicated, and how understanding of KAL should be assessed. At advanced levels in the English school system, the topic of language change is often a specified component of particular assessments of KAL (e.g. the AQA A-level in English Language has an area of study in which candidates “explore processes of language change”) and assessment of classical languages involves specific questions on grammatical terminology (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The life cycle of phonological patterns explains drift in sound change</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/ichl25/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I address the nature of ‘drift’ (Sapir 1921) in phonological change from the perspective of the life cycle of phonological processes (Kiparsky 1995; Bermúdez-Otero 2007; 2015; Bermúdez-Otero &amp;amp; Trousdale 2012). I support the basic account of drift offered by Joseph (2013); Natvig &amp;amp; Salmons (2020), in which parallel changes arise from shared patterns of phonetic and phonological variation inherited from the proto-language. Specifically, I propose that a complete account of drift can be provided if we complement the insight that parallel changes draw on the inherited pool of variation with the proposition that change proceeds along the trajectory guided by the life cycle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metrical structure and Stratal Phonology provide a complete account of Danish stød</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</guid>
      <description>In this paper we demonstrate that the patterning of stød in Standard Danish submits to a complete, non-stipulative account within an approach that embraces metrical structure as the mechanism behind accentual contrasts (Köhnlein 2019), and the main tenets of Stratal Phonology (Bermúdez- Otero 2018). Our approach maintains the empirical coverage of the ‘Non-Stød Model’ developed by Basbøll (2005 et passim), but builds on widely accepted principles of morphology-phonology interaction instead of a proliferation of bespoke domains, in addition to incorporating insights from other approaches (notably Itô &amp;amp; Mester 2015).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The origin of West Jutland stød</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I offer a reconstruction of the history of the so-called West Jutland stød that reaffirms the proposition that it is a reflex of Proto-Nordic preaspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic correlates of the fortis/lenis distinction in early 20th century Donegal Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/tionol21/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/tionol21/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic correlates of the fortis/lenis distinction in early 20th century Donegal Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/frlsu2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/frlsu2021/</guid>
      <description>In this paper we address the long-standing question of how the distinction between fortis and lenis consonants arose and functioned in Old Irish, and how it is reflected in the present-day Gaelic languages. We report an empirical study of early-twentieth-century Donegal Irish recordings from the Doegen collection. The results show that fortis sonorants (traditionally written /L/ and /N/) displayed significantly greater duration than the equivalent lenis sonorants (/l/ and /n/) both word-medially and word-finally, suggesting that the fortis/lenis distinction did correspond to a duration distinction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonological convergence in north-western Europe</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</guid>
      <description>I offer a framework for understanding convergent diachronic developments in the phonological systems of unrelated languages, informed by the life cycle of phonological processes. I focus on preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the traditional /p t k/ series) in several languages of north-west Europe where preaspiration cannot be due to shared inheritance, including the North Germanic languages, varieties of English, the Gaelic languages, Welsh, and the Sámi languages. Preaspiration is often claimed to be typologically rare and diachronically unstable (Silverman 2003, Blevins 2017); hence, its appearance in unrelated languages with a history of contact is often ascribed to that contact (Marstrander 1932, Posti 1954, Wagner 1964, Borgstrøm 1974, Salmons 1992, Gunnar Ólafur Hansson 2001, Rießler 2008, McKenna 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Жизненный цикл морфонологических процессов в русском языке</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</guid>
      <description>Характерное свойство динамических подходов к русской фонологии и морфонологии — как выполненных в духе порождающих фонологических теорий, так и (пост)структуралистских — обширное использование правил, обязательно применяемых в определенном порядке. Обоснование этого порядка — важнейшая задача для теоретического осмысления фактов русского языка, без решения которой динамические подходы являются по сути нефальсифицируемыми: в отсутствие четких ограничений на количество правил и порядок их применения любое чередование можно подвергнуть сколь угодно абстрактному анализу с произвольным количеством правил.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Конвергенция фонологических систем в Северной Европе</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/zvegincev-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/zvegincev-conference/</guid>
      <description>This is a Russian summary of the work that I presented, among other places, at the Edinburgh Symposium on Historical Phonology
В докладе предлагается подход к диахронической конвергенции фонологических систем в неродственных языках, основанный на теории «жизненного цикла фонологических процессов» [Bermúdez-Otero 2007], на примере развития преаспирациии сильных («глухих») взрывных в нескольких языках северной Европы. Преаспирация обычно считается явлением типологически редким и диахронически нестабильным [Silverman 2003]. Тем более удивительным кажется ее наличие в таких географически, но не генеалогически, близких языках, как северогерманские, английский (несколько разновидностей), гойдельские языки (ирландский и шотландский), валлийский и саамские языки.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebooting Slavic phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/abralin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/abralin/</guid>
      <description>The Slavic languages have historically played a very prominent role in the development of Western phonological theory, from some of the earliest pioneers of phonemic theory such as Jan Baudouin de Courtenay, Mikołaj Kruszewski and Lev Shcherba, through the Praguian structuralism of Nikolai Trubetzkoy and (early) Roman Jakobson, and to some of the foundational work of generative phonology. In particular, Morris Halle and Theodore Lightner offered comprehensive analyses of Russian phonology that relied heavily on multi-level derivations, abstract underlying representations and a suite of rules that largely recapitulated diachronic developments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drift revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/eshp4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/eshp4/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I offer a framework for understanding convergent diachronic developments in the phonological systems of unrelated languages, informed by the life cycle of phonological processes. I focus on preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the traditional /p t k/ series) in several languages of north-western Europe that are either unrelated, or not related closely enough for preaspiration to be inherited: they include the North Germanic languages, varieties of English, the Gaelic languages, Welsh, and the Sámi languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bringing it all together</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/farl3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/farl3/</guid>
      <description>Palatalization processes and the e ~ ’o alternation are both classic problems in Russian (morpho)phonology. It is now widely recognized that there is a relationship between the two: where suffixes are relevant to the e ~ ’o alternation, palatalizing suffixes require the front vowel in the preceding morpheme, and non-palatalizing suffixes require the back vowel (see particularly Itkin 1994). This strongly suggests a phonological analysis of the e ~ ’o alternation, which has hitherto proven elusive, primarily since there is no principled, non-circular account of apparent lexical exceptions and of suffixes that are neutral for the purposes of the alternation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in sonorant-consonant clusters in areal perspective</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation and (presumed) change in Norwegian preaspiration</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/ucl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/ucl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can language areas arise by drift?</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/stirling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/stirling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Stratal Phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I discuss the nature of evidence for the stratal organization of morphophonological grammar. Much — of course by no means all — of the currently available evidence in favour a stratal approach to morphology-phonology interactions comes from languages such as English, where the stratification of the lexicon has a strong historical rationale, or the Romance languages, where one can often easily observe morphological constituency at the level below the word.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A metrical analysis of Scottish Gaelic tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/rnag/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/rnag/</guid>
      <description>I provide a new analysis of the ‘tonal accent’ opposition in Gaelic, conceptualizing it as involving lexically specified metrical — in particular foot — structure. As discussed among others by Ternes (1980, 2006), many Gaelic varieties use suprasegmental features such as pitch (e.g. Lewis, Wester Ross) or glottalization (e.g. Jura, Colonsay) to make two kinds of distinctions: disyllabic hiatus vs. heavy syllables (àth vs. atha); and disyllabic vs. svarabhakti words (balg vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in lC and rC clusters</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</guid>
      <description>The insertion of an unstressed vowel in lC and rC clusters of non-rising sonority (fil[ə]m), is widely known as characteristic of Irish English. It is frequently cited as a substrate feature carried over from Irish, where this process is productive (Ní Chiosáin 1999), as it is in the related Scottish Gaelic. However, this feature is also known from Older Scots, modern Scots dialects (Maguire 2017), and traditional varieties of English. Therefore, it might be an areal effect in the British and Irish Isles; notably, a similar phenomenon is also attested in Welsh (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The influence of Norse on Scottish Gaelic, 85 years on</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/frlsu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/frlsu/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose (yet another) reappraisal of the arguments regarding the relationship between Norse and Gaelic in the North Atlantic world, focusing on the development of preaspiration. There is significant controversy in the literature as to whether this feature, along with others such as tonal accent, represents Norse influence on Gaelic (e.g. Marstrander 1932; Borgstrøm 1974; Gunnar Ólafur Hansson 2001), an independent development in Gaelic (e.g. Ó Baoill 1980; Ó Murchú 1985; Ó Maolalaigh 2010), or even Gaelic influence on Norse (McKenna 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There is no problem of /v/ in Russian phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/26mfm/</guid>
      <description>The dual behaviour of /v/ has been a notorious crux in Russian phonology since at least Jakobson (1956). The basic problem is that /v/ fails to trigger voicing assimilation, like sonorants, but undergoes both assimilation to following obstruents and final devoicing, like obstruents.
The commonest solution in the literature is representational: [v] is treated as a sonorant, either an underlying /w/ (Lightner 1972, Hayes 1984, Kiparsky 1985) or some labial non-glide (Coats &amp;amp; Harshenin 1971, Padgett 2002).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norwegian preaspiration in traditional and modern sources</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/fgls/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/fgls/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I survey traditional descriptions of Norwegian dialects with particular attention to their discussion of voiceless stop preaspiration, and conclude that it is highly probable preaspiration has been consistently under-reported in these sources. As surveyed in detail by Pétur Helgason (2002), preaspiration in Norwegian has been reported most prominently for northern Gudbrandsdalen (Ross 1907; Horne 1917), Rogaland (Oftedal 1947; Wolter 1965), and for Senja by Iversen (1913). To Helgason’s list should be added Vestvågøya (Elstad 1982) and contact varieties in Northern Norway (Jahr 2008).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards a history of the tenseness contrast in Brythonic vowels</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3/</guid>
      <description>Modern Welsh is similar to many modern Germanic languages such as English, German and Dutch in showing an association between &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; vowel quality and phonological length. Specifically, long vowels tend to be tense in quality and short vowels tend to be lax, with concomitant alternations. As in the Germanic case, there is some disagreement in the literature on whether quality or quantity (or both) is phonologically relevant in Modern Welsh. In this paper I aim to add to this debate via an overview of the diatopic variation in the relationship between vowel quantity and quality in Welsh and more broadly in the Brythonic languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pre-sonorant voicing and language contact</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3-fringe/</guid>
      <description>I draw attention to the fact that whilst pre-sonorant voicing of fricatives across a word boundary appears to be fairly widely spread (at least in Europe), pre-sonorant voicing of all obstruents appears to cluster in areas where &amp;lsquo;aspirating&amp;rsquo; languages are in contact with &amp;lsquo;voice&amp;rsquo; languages: the languages involved are Breton (Celtic/Gallo-Romance), Franconian/Netherlandic (e.g. Limburg Dutch, Luxembourgish), Western Polish and Slovak (Slavic/Germanic).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the gap</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/dias/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/dias/</guid>
      <description>I focus on reconstructing the development of vowel quality distinctions in Brythonic and their connection with the history of vowel quantity between the establishment of the ‘standard’ Brythonic penultimate-stress system and the present day. In the received picture of Modern Welsh phonology, ‘tense’ quality of non-low vowels ([i u e o]) is strongly associated with length and, conversely, ‘lax’ quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ]) is associated with shortness, at least in contrastive, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microvariation in laryngeal realism</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I consider the range of microvariation in the expression of laryngeal contrast, focusing on (voiceless) preaspiration in North Germanic. On the basis of an acoustic study, I suggest that both the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization have been under-reported in existing descriptions. This, in turn, has important consequences for our understanding of the phonology of laryngeal contrast. Specifically, I argue that the observed variation in laryngeal phenomena is incompatible with a version of &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; that produces inferences about phonological specifications on the basis of phonetic implementation; instead, I advocate a more abstract approach that gives primacy to phonological behaviour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation in North Germanic preaspiration</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</guid>
      <description>I consider the extent of cross-dialectal variation in the expression of laryngeal contrast within North Germanic, with a focus on (voiceless) preaspiration, and suggest that the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization across the North Germanic area have been significantly under-reported in the past.
As discussed by Pétur Helgason (2002), whilst preaspiration and sonorant devoicing in Insular Nordic have long been recognized by the scholarship, their distribution and behaviour in mainland varieties have been less well understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making sense of consonant palatalization vowel backness in Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</guid>
      <description>Despite its status as a minority language, Modern Irish has a rich body of phonetic and phonological descriptions, based on (near-)native fieldworker knowledge and traditional auditory methods. In this paper, we draw on a range of up-to-date instrumental and quantitative methods in order to verify and expand the traditional findings regarding the nature and status of the interaction between consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish.
According to the descriptive literature, there are several types of consonant-to-vowel coarticulation in Modern Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short vowel allophones in Modern Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/tionol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/tionol/</guid>
      <description>We present the results of a study of the acoustic properties of short vowels in Modern Irish, building on data from all three major dialect groupings. It is well known that short vowels in Irish are realized as back or front depending on the palatalization of the surrounding consonants (thus liom [u] but linn [i]). In addition, traditional descriptions also recognize that vowels can also have a number of distinct allophones whose distribution also depends on surrounding consonants: for instance, De Bhaldraithe (1945) describes four distinct varieties of [a] in Cois Fhairrge Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European phonological area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</guid>
      <description>This is a local colloquium talk with some preliminary ideas on the topic. If you have any kind of feedback, do please get in touch!
I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems of phonemicization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/clc9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/clc9/</guid>
      <description>We address a long-standing issue in the phonology of Modern Irish: the phonological status of the distinction between front and back short vowels. We argue that the approach inherent in most theoretical work on the topic, which privileges traditional &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; criteria such as predictability of distribution, misses important generalizations and cannot be sustained. Instead, we suggest that front and back (non-low) vowels in Irish are best thought of as phonologically &amp;lsquo;distinctive&amp;rsquo;, but not (significantly) &amp;lsquo;contrastive&amp;rsquo; units.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphology and dialectology: A quantitative approach</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/rnag2016/</guid>
      <description>We present a study of Gaelic dialectal variation based on the unpublished, morphological section of the Linguistic Survey of Scotland (Gaelic). Our findings indicate that a quantitative (dialectometric) approach can yield important insights into the range of internal variation in Gaelic and elucidate certain issues of language structure. Here, we focus on two questions:
 What patterns of spatial variation are observed in the morphological data? How are different morphological features in the dialects correlated?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel length in Shetland Norn</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/amc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/amc/</guid>
      <description>One of the areas in which Scandinavian influence is apparent in the traditional Shetland Scots dialect is the distribution of vowel length: Shetland Scots generally follows the Scottish Vowel Length Rule, but also shows the complementary distribution of consonant and vowel length known from modern North Germanic languages.
During the earliest development of Shetland Scots, three different systems of vowel length can be argued to have been in contact:
 (Nearly) unconstrained vowel length, as in Old Norse Scandinavian combinatory vowel length The Scottish Vowel Length Rule  All these systems were in the process of change in our time period, with System 1 giving way to System 2 across Scandinavia, and the SVLR also developing at about the same time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European linguistic area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/uit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/uit/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels: phonology and/or coarticulation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents much the same material as our presentation at OCP13</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel backness and palatalization in Irish and Scottish Gaelic: A study in rule scattering</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</guid>
      <description>We present the results of an acoustic study of the interaction of consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels. Previous descriptions of Irish (but usually not of Scottish Gaelic) often describe the distribution of front vs. back nonlow vowels as predictable (allophonic). This makes Irish a potential example of a vertical vowel system. However, the sources are mostly impressionistic, and also tend to underplay the extent of variation within and across lexical items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonetic (non-)explanation in historical phonology: Duration, harmony, and dissimilation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</guid>
      <description>We consider the value of phonetically based explanations for phonological change by tracing the phonologization paths of durational asymmetries between vowels. The literature on phonetic motivations for phonological change identifies relative shortness of one vowel with respect to another as an important precursor to vowel reduction, which, in turn, may feed hypercorrection of the reduced vowel to give rise to vowel harmony phenomena. We examine such a case from Nivkh in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic and its contribution to prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports the preliminary results of an acoustic study of preaspiration in the Gaelic of North Argyll. Existing descriptions identify this area as reflecting Old Irish and Old Norse &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; geminates as [xp xt xk] clusters (&amp;lsquo;pre-affricates&amp;rsquo;), but, to our knowledge, no targeted acoustic study of these varieties had been performed to date. Our results confirm that the preaspiration found in other varieties corresponds to dorsal (velar or uvular) frication in North Argyll, rather than other conceivable interpretations of the impressionistic descriptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspiration and tonal accents as Northern Gaelic features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</guid>
      <description>I argue that the origin of both pitch accents and preaspiration in Gaelic is best understood in the context of a &amp;lsquo;Northern Gaelic&amp;rsquo; area covering Ulster and Scotland, as opposed to Connacht and Munster. Within this area, both preaspiration and pitch accents show the classic pattern of peripheral archaisms, with Lewis and West Ulster as remnant areas and Argyll as the most innovative zone. This suggests that the stronger Norse presence in the Hebrides does not correlate with a denser distribution of potential contact features, and thus the developments in both cases need not have been triggered by contact &amp;mdash; even though a reinforcing role for contact is very difficult (and probably undesirable) to exclude.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free and not so free</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</guid>
      <description>I offer an analysis of &amp;lsquo;length&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;tenseness&amp;rsquo; found in an acoustic study of eight speakers. The results confirm the existence of a categorical pattern whereby the quality of long mid vowels in penults depends on the phonological height of the following vowel (Awbery 1984, Wmffre 2003). One speaker shows a distribution of tenseness that categorically tracks length in penults, much as described in the literature and shown for monosyllables by Mayr &amp;amp; Davies (2011).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantity-quality interactions in Welsh vowels</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</guid>
      <description>I present the results of a phonetic study of the relationship between vowel quality and vowel quantity. The results confirm that the descriptions are correct in setting up a categorical distinction between two varieties of long mid vowels (tense [eː oː] and lax [ɛː ɔː]) in South-West Welsh. This system plausibly arose as the enhancement of a pattern where there is no quality distinctions between short and long vowels, with continuous variation in height in both prosodic contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An echoing tone</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the Nordic Research Network 2015 conference at the University of Edinburgh.
In this talk, I consider the origins of pitch accents in North Germanic and in Scottish Gaelic. I argue that in both cases the more plausible hypothesis involves the realization of an identical tonal melody over different temporal domains, particularly by the mechanism of peak delay. This is not a new idea, but I support it by a consideration of the interaction of tone and apocope in Zealand Danish and in Central Scandinavian.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Length and tenseness across Welsh dialects</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the First Conference on Linguistic Diversity in Wales at the National Library of Wales in Aberystwyth.
This talk is about the interaction of vowel quantity and quality in different dialects of Welsh. According to existing descriptions, Welsh is a bit like English in that its short vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; in quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ ə]) and its long vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; ([iː uː eː oː]).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress and consonant length in Welsh revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</guid>
      <description>I</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ареальные схождения в фонологии языков Северной Европы</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</guid>
      <description>This is the Russian-language version of this talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonologization of redundant contrasts and the Contrastivist Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</guid>
      <description>I consider two cases of predictable distributions of phonological categories: &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; long vowels in South-West Welsh and the two varieties of the FACE vowel in Ulster English. Their predictable (&amp;lsquo;non-phonemic&amp;rsquo;) distribution is a challenge to the Contrastivist Hypothesis, but I argue that it can be accommodated if we assume that learning, including category formation, proceeds bottom-up, and that learners do not unlearn predictably distributed categories unless compelled to do so by alternations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The [ATR]/laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</guid>
      <description>I offer a preliminary analysis of the phenomenon of calediad (&amp;lsquo;provection&amp;rsquo;) in South-Eastern Welsh, whereby &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (lenis) stops become &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; after a stressed vowel. I argue that since vowels before lenis stops are generally long &amp;mdash; and, given the phonology of South Welsh &amp;mdash; tense, provection is an example of vowel-consonant interaction, where the same feature is used for the tense/lax contrast in vowels and laryngeal contrast in consonants. I interpret this as supporting emergent feature theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nordeuropäische Lautgeographie revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</guid>
      <description>This presents some work in progress on common phonological features in Northern Europe (preaspiration, pitch accents, sonorant pre-occlusion). Email me if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the handout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the dots</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/hxphon2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/hxphon2014/</guid>
      <description>This poster considers the status of the &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo;/&amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; contrasts across Welsh dialects and argues that it was originally an enhancement of quantity, but becomes phonologized in different ways across different dialect. For the latest in this project, see the 23mfm paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In search of lost phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/ncl-svarabhakti-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/ncl-svarabhakti-talk/</guid>
      <description>This covers much the same ground as this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonemicization vs. phonologization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</guid>
      <description>We consider the status of &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (really lenis) fricatives in Old English and in Brythonic Celtic. In the received view, they are not &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; in Old English, yet their distribution is clearly sensitive to phonological structure. We propose that they are distinct phonological symbols, coerced into predictable distributions by the phonological computation. We also offer a similar analysis for Brythonic Celtic. The situation is argued to result as a predictable consequence of the life cycle of phonological processes rather than from language contact, contra previous suggestions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge talk to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving segments, but instead features attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glottal stop insertion in Scottish Gaelic and contrastive syllabification</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</guid>
      <description>Gaelic dialects, mostly in Argyll, show a process of glottal stop epenthesis in stressed light syllables. This has been analysed as a stress-to-weight effect, and I review the evidence to show that this analysis is likely correct, and also that glottal stop insertion is a live phonological process rather than a lexicalized artefact of history. If this is correct, Argyll Gaelic shows an example of lexical storage of syllable structure, sometimes argued to be impossible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonological endgame</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</guid>
      <description>I present an analysis of Welsh &amp;lsquo;svarabhakti&amp;rsquo;, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (pwdr &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]). This pattern is said to coexist with a pattern of deleting consonants in such clusters in polysyllables (perygl &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has been argued that the two differing outcomes can be reconciled by appeal to a single constraint on the form of feet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonetic realization is irrelevant for phonological representation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/ulster-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/ulster-seminar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In defence of Richness of the Base</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I briefly present the analysis of mora assignment to consonants in South Welsh. The pattern can be analysed by appeal to the form of the inputs (i.e. with a massive number of accidental gaps, which is undesirable), or by positing a constraint schema with undesirable consequences for factorial typology. I suggest that the latter solution is preferable theoretically, although it may be premature to choose it for that reason alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified account of the behaviour of high vowels in Bothoa Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer an analysis of gliding in Bothoa Breton, as presented in the thesis. I argue that high vowels (especially [i]) either become glides or coalesce with a preceding consonant, in order to avoid hiatus. However, this pattern is disrupted if the high vowel becomes a nucleus at an earlier stage in the cyclic derivation. This provides an argument for stratal models of phonology-morphology interactions, and a strong argument against Output-Output Correspondence, because some of the exceptional non-gliding cases cannot be explained by reference to a free-standing form with transparent non-gliding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconstructing mutation in Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer the analysis of Breton initial mutations found in my thesis. I argue that there is no such thing as a unified &amp;lsquo;mutation&amp;rsquo; mechanism: instead, this labels covers a variety of processes with different places in the overall grammar. The article-length version of the argument is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my Toronto presentation and to a certain extent my talk from the 6th CLC). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</guid>
      <description>I consider the nature of the so-called &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic and argue that the contrast is one of metrical structure rather than lexical tone, at least diachronically, and probably also synchronically. This means that they can be reconstructed with an internal origin, and no recourse to contact with North Germanic is necessary to account for their appearance. The paper has the analysis in detail, and the historical argument is expounded in some detail in later talks here and here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaning licensing mismatches in Welsh</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I propose a new analysis of so-called &amp;lsquo;vowel mutation&amp;rsquo; in Welsh, whereby final syllables (both stressed and unstressed) only allow a reduced inventory (by disallowing [ə]). I argue that these final syllables are specified with something like a suprasegmental feature that triggers a feature co-occurrence effect, and that there is no need for recourse to a mechanism of metrical prominence akin to that borne by stressed syllables (as previously suggested in the literature).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On (some) dimensions of headship in phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/pj-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2011/pj-workshop/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in the north of Italy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents in detail the analysis of Friulian also given at the 18th mfm and later published here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A bad case of excessive computation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</guid>
      <description>I use the analysis of palatalization in Modern Standard Russian offered here to argue that these data do not provide a watertight argument for multilevel phonological computation, and that phonological analysis must be combined with a theory of ordering (such as Stratal OT) if the hypothesis of parallel computation is to be challenged.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How good is the internal evidence for multiple-level phonological computation? A view from Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</guid>
      <description>Relying in part on the analysis of palatalization offered here, I argue that Russian does not provide strong phonology-internal evidence for level ordering, contra suggestions by authors such as Morris Halle and Jerzy Rubach. A more focused argument to the same effect is offered here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started here. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature geometry meets contrastive specification</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the interaction between vowel lengthening before voiced obstruents and final devoicing in two languages: Friulian and Breton. I argue that such interactions are transparent and involve a three-way laryngeal contrast formalized geometrically, with true voiceless obstruents the most structurally complex and devoiced ones least. The Friulian analysis was later published here and the Breton was largely incorporated into the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A good old-fashioned approach to Russian palatalization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/oslo-russian-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/oslo-russian-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian palatalization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</guid>
      <description>In this talk we argue that the traditional view of vowel-driven palatalization in Russian is inadequate, at least for two reasons. First, it relies on a six-vowel interpretation of the Russian inventory that is not adequate from a phonetic perspective. Second, and more importantly, it undergenerates the range of alternations found in Modern Standard Russian. Instead, we argue that palatalization must be driven by a floating feature attached to the left edge of suffixes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure versus prominence</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the stress system of Munster Irish, which evinces a disruption of normal directionality only in words with two initial heavy syllables. The analysis relies on recursion of subsyllable constituents and on a formal distinction between &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;head status&amp;rsquo;. The full version of the analysis can be found in this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian (morpho)phonological palatalization: a holistic approach</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/fdsl8-palatalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/fdsl8-palatalization/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cuique suum: vowel reduction in Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/fdsl8-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/fdsl8-reduction/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tre problemer i russisk fonologi</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/novemberseminaret-palatalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/novemberseminaret-palatalization/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian palatalization in substance-free phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/castl-colloquium-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/castl-colloquium-russian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
      <description>This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see this talk and this paper). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russian vowel reduction without functional motivation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/bergen-russian-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/bergen-russian-reduction/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cuique suum: vowel reduction in Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/tromso-russian-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/tromso-russian-reduction/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fonetikk versus fonologi</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</guid>
      <description>Dette er det fyrste føredraget i prosjektet om russisk vokalreduksjon. Sluttversjonen kan ein finne i denne artikkelen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Too many levels, too few solutions</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/16mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/16mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk is largely of historic interest, superseded in particular by this talk, also at the mfm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All that glistens is not gold</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I argue that purely phonological (e.g. autosegmental) approaches to initial consonant mutations in languages such as Fula and Irish are insufficient to account for the facts fully. In many ways this does not represent my current thinking on these matters, as can be established by looking, for instance, at this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liquids and spirants</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-liquids/</guid>
      <description>Here, I consider some cases of fricatives phonologically patterning with liquids, and argue that this phenomenon is merely the extension of the well-known cross-linguistic diversity in the representation of the former. I interpret this as providing support for substance-free representations with a non-trivial phonology-phonetics mapping. I provide a concrete analysis of initial mutations involving sonorants in Scottish Gaelic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Against autosegmental approaches to initial consonant mutation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/castl-colloquium-mutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/castl-colloquium-mutations/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial consonant mutation and information flow in Mende</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/ocp5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/ocp5/</guid>
      <description>I reanalyse the pattern of initial consonant mutation in Mende by arguing that the so-called &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade, usually assumed to be the derive one, is the default case morphosyntactically, and thus that the consonant mutation mechanism must derive the &amp;lsquo;strong&amp;rsquo; rather than the &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade. This is problematic for autosegmental, or probably any purely phonological, accounts of mutation, since the relationship between the weak and strong grades is one-to-many, so I suggest the choice between the two grades is made outside of phonology, with direct reference to the morphosyntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Лексикализованные вершины в валлийском синтаксисе</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I attempt to extend Nigel Duffield&amp;rsquo;s idea of &amp;lsquo;lexicalized heads&amp;rsquo; playing a rôle in the triggering of initial mutations, originally proposed for Irish, to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonological processes as lexical insertion: more evidence from Welsh and elsewhere</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2007/ocp4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2007/ocp4/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Валлийский язык и типология чередований начальных согласных</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/spb-welsh-mutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/spb-welsh-mutation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brythonic ‘second lenition’ revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I evaluate the arguments for two competing reconstructions regarding the laryngeal phonology of Proto-Brythonic. I defend the &amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo; interpretation which underplays the role of a &amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo; contrast and instead relies on two separate lenition processes (due to authors such as David Greene and Patrick Sims-Williams), against the &amp;lsquo;classical&amp;rsquo; one due to Kenneth Jackson and defended by John Koch and Graham Isaac, which emphasizes the rôle of aspiration in Proto-Brythonic &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; stops.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Грамматикализация начальных чередований в валлийском языке</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/mscl2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/mscl2006/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I suggest that some cases of the historical extension of initial mutation in Welsh to some contexts where they are not explainable with reference to sandhi in Proto-Brythonic, such as the &amp;lsquo;direct object mutation&amp;rsquo;, may have been driven by the interpretation of lenition (&amp;lsquo;soft mutation&amp;rsquo;) as a non-prototypicality marker.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Right at the left edge: Initial consonant mutations in the world’s languages</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/rara-rarissima/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/rara-rarissima/</guid>
      <description>This talk was an attempt at documenting initial consonant mutations in as wide a range of languages as possible, together with an attempt at a typology. It formed the basis for the paper published in the proceedings of the conference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>К морфонологической типологии: «рерадикализация» в языках мира</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2005/sp-reradicalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2005/sp-reradicalization/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Типологически значимые параметры глагольной лексики: имперфективирующие деривации ненецкого языка</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2005/nenets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2005/nenets/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>