<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Irish on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/irish/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Irish on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/irish/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Stratal Phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I discuss the nature of evidence for the stratal organization of morphophonological grammar. Much — of course by no means all — of the currently available evidence in favour a stratal approach to morphology-phonology interactions comes from languages such as English, where the stratification of the lexicon has a strong historical rationale, or the Romance languages, where one can often easily observe morphological constituency at the level below the word.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making sense of consonant palatalization vowel backness in Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/ldlt5/</guid>
      <description>Despite its status as a minority language, Modern Irish has a rich body of phonetic and phonological descriptions, based on (near-)native fieldworker knowledge and traditional auditory methods. In this paper, we draw on a range of up-to-date instrumental and quantitative methods in order to verify and expand the traditional findings regarding the nature and status of the interaction between consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish.
According to the descriptive literature, there are several types of consonant-to-vowel coarticulation in Modern Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short vowel allophones in Modern Irish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/tionol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/tionol/</guid>
      <description>We present the results of a study of the acoustic properties of short vowels in Modern Irish, building on data from all three major dialect groupings. It is well known that short vowels in Irish are realized as back or front depending on the palatalization of the surrounding consonants (thus liom [u] but linn [i]). In addition, traditional descriptions also recognize that vowels can also have a number of distinct allophones whose distribution also depends on surrounding consonants: for instance, De Bhaldraithe (1945) describes four distinct varieties of [a] in Cois Fhairrge Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems of phonemicization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/clc9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/clc9/</guid>
      <description>We address a long-standing issue in the phonology of Modern Irish: the phonological status of the distinction between front and back short vowels. We argue that the approach inherent in most theoretical work on the topic, which privileges traditional &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; criteria such as predictability of distribution, misses important generalizations and cannot be sustained. Instead, we suggest that front and back (non-low) vowels in Irish are best thought of as phonologically &amp;lsquo;distinctive&amp;rsquo;, but not (significantly) &amp;lsquo;contrastive&amp;rsquo; units.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels: phonology and/or coarticulation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/backness-in-irish-and-scottish-gaelic-short-vowels-phonology-and-or-coarticulation/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents much the same material as our presentation at OCP13</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel backness and palatalization in Irish and Scottish Gaelic: A study in rule scattering</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/vowel-backness-and-palatalization-in-irish-scottish-gaelic-study-in-rule-scattering/</guid>
      <description>We present the results of an acoustic study of the interaction of consonant palatalization and vowel backness in Irish and Scottish Gaelic short vowels. Previous descriptions of Irish (but usually not of Scottish Gaelic) often describe the distribution of front vs. back nonlow vowels as predictable (allophonic). This makes Irish a potential example of a vertical vowel system. However, the sources are mostly impressionistic, and also tend to underplay the extent of variation within and across lexical items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonetic (non-)explanation in historical phonology: Duration, harmony, and dissimilation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</guid>
      <description>We consider the value of phonetically based explanations for phonological change by tracing the phonologization paths of durational asymmetries between vowels. The literature on phonetic motivations for phonological change identifies relative shortness of one vowel with respect to another as an important precursor to vowel reduction, which, in turn, may feed hypercorrection of the reduced vowel to give rise to vowel harmony phenomena. We examine such a case from Nivkh in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers the origin of &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic with a view to evaluating the hypothesis that this feature was borrowed from North Germanic varieties spoken by Norse settlers in medieval Scotland. It is shown that the &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; system in Gaelic is tightly bound with metrical structure (more precisely syllable count), certainly diachronically, and probably (at least in some varieties) synchronically. Gaelic &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; is argued to be a plausible internal development, parallel to similar phenomena in other branches of Celtic (specifically in Breton), as well as in Germanic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Head-dependent asymmetries in Munster Irish prosody</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/munster-irish-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/munster-irish-stress/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I propose an analysis of stress in Munster Irish which builds on two important premises. First, I argue for a distinction between the notion &amp;lsquo;head of a constituent&amp;rsquo; and the notion of &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo;: these are separate entities, and the typologically frequent isomorphic distribution of the two is just one possible outcome of the phonological computation. Second, I propose to employ a particular family of constraints requiring head-dependent asymmetries (Dresher and van der Hulst 1998) to account for the mismatch between the placement of foot heads and stress in Munster Irish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure versus prominence</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the stress system of Munster Irish, which evinces a disruption of normal directionality only in words with two initial heavy syllables. The analysis relies on recursion of subsyllable constituents and on a formal distinction between &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;head status&amp;rsquo;. The full version of the analysis can be found in this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All that glistens is not gold</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I argue that purely phonological (e.g. autosegmental) approaches to initial consonant mutations in languages such as Fula and Irish are insufficient to account for the facts fully. In many ways this does not represent my current thinking on these matters, as can be established by looking, for instance, at this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
