<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Welsh on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/welsh/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Welsh on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/welsh/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Stratal Phonology</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards a history of the tenseness contrast in Brythonic vowels</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/esohph3/</guid>
      <description>Modern Welsh is similar to many modern Germanic languages such as English, German and Dutch in showing an association between &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; vowel quality and phonological length. Specifically, long vowels tend to be tense in quality and short vowels tend to be lax, with concomitant alternations. As in the Germanic case, there is some disagreement in the literature on whether quality or quantity (or both) is phonologically relevant in Modern Welsh. In this paper I aim to add to this debate via an overview of the diatopic variation in the relationship between vowel quantity and quality in Welsh and more broadly in the Brythonic languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the gap</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/dias/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2017/dias/</guid>
      <description>I focus on reconstructing the development of vowel quality distinctions in Brythonic and their connection with the history of vowel quantity between the establishment of the ‘standard’ Brythonic penultimate-stress system and the present day. In the received picture of Modern Welsh phonology, ‘tense’ quality of non-low vowels ([i u e o]) is strongly associated with length and, conversely, ‘lax’ quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ]) is associated with shortness, at least in contrastive, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welsh svarabhakti as stem allomorphy</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/svarabhakti/</guid>
      <description>This paper develops the analysis in this presentation. I offer an analysis of Welsh epenthesis, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (pwdr &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]) and deletion in such clusters in polysyllables (perygl &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has previously been argued that both processes can be analysed in a single phonological grammar. I show that this is not tenable for South Welsh dialects, and propose an analysis in terms of part-of-speech-specific allomorphy, formalized as lexical storage of POS-characterized stems rather than roots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonologization of redundancy</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/welsh-vowels-phonologization/</guid>
      <description>‘Phonologization’ is a process whereby a phonetic phenomenon enters the phonological grammar and becomes conceptualized as the result of categorical manipulation of phonological symbols. I analyse the phonologization of a predictable phonological pattern in Welsh, with particular attention to identifying criteria for whether phonologization has occurred. I argue for a model where phonologization experiences bottom-up and top-down biases. From the bottom up, there is pressure to phonologize phenomena with a categorical distribution; from the top down, there exist formal constraints on featural specification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ATR/Laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/calediad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/calediad/</guid>
      <description>I consider an unusual sound change and synchronic alternation in south-eastern dialects of Welsh, traditionally referred to as ‘provection’ (Welsh calediad). This phenomenon involves the ‘devoicing’ of stops following stressed vowels. I suggest that it may be the result of a typologically rare sort of vowel-consonant featural interaction, where ‘devoicing’ is triggered by tense vowels. This is unexpected typologically, since tongue root advancement — often a correlate of ‘tense’ vowel quality — is more frequently associated with voicing rather than devoicing in obstruents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European phonological area</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</guid>
      <description>This is a local colloquium talk with some preliminary ideas on the topic. If you have any kind of feedback, do please get in touch!
I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonetic (non-)explanation in historical phonology: Duration, harmony, and dissimilation</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</guid>
      <description>We consider the value of phonetically based explanations for phonological change by tracing the phonologization paths of durational asymmetries between vowels. The literature on phonetic motivations for phonological change identifies relative shortness of one vowel with respect to another as an important precursor to vowel reduction, which, in turn, may feed hypercorrection of the reduced vowel to give rise to vowel harmony phenomena. We examine such a case from Nivkh in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free and not so free</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/free-not-so-free-dialect-variation-quantity-quality-interactions-welsh-vowels/</guid>
      <description>I offer an analysis of &amp;lsquo;length&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;tenseness&amp;rsquo; found in an acoustic study of eight speakers. The results confirm the existence of a categorical pattern whereby the quality of long mid vowels in penults depends on the phonological height of the following vowel (Awbery 1984, Wmffre 2003). One speaker shows a distribution of tenseness that categorically tracks length in penults, much as described in the literature and shown for monosyllables by Mayr &amp;amp; Davies (2011).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantity-quality interactions in Welsh vowels</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/quantity-quality-interactions-in-welsh-vowels-phonologization-across-dialects/</guid>
      <description>I present the results of a phonetic study of the relationship between vowel quality and vowel quantity. The results confirm that the descriptions are correct in setting up a categorical distinction between two varieties of long mid vowels (tense [eː oː] and lax [ɛː ɔː]) in South-West Welsh. This system plausibly arose as the enhancement of a pattern where there is no quality distinctions between short and long vowels, with continuous variation in height in both prosodic contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Length and tenseness across Welsh dialects</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/length-and-tenseness-across-welsh-dialects/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the First Conference on Linguistic Diversity in Wales at the National Library of Wales in Aberystwyth.
This talk is about the interaction of vowel quantity and quality in different dialects of Welsh. According to existing descriptions, Welsh is a bit like English in that its short vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; in quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ ə]) and its long vowels are consistently &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; ([iː uː eː oː]).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress and consonant length in Welsh revisited</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/gregynog-2014/</guid>
      <description>I</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonologization of redundant contrasts and the Contrastivist Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</guid>
      <description>I consider two cases of predictable distributions of phonological categories: &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; long vowels in South-West Welsh and the two varieties of the FACE vowel in Ulster English. Their predictable (&amp;lsquo;non-phonemic&amp;rsquo;) distribution is a challenge to the Contrastivist Hypothesis, but I argue that it can be accommodated if we assume that learning, including category formation, proceeds bottom-up, and that learners do not unlearn predictably distributed categories unless compelled to do so by alternations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The [ATR]/laryngeal connection and emergent features</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/the-atr-laryngeal-connection-and-emergent-features/</guid>
      <description>I offer a preliminary analysis of the phenomenon of calediad (&amp;lsquo;provection&amp;rsquo;) in South-Eastern Welsh, whereby &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (lenis) stops become &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; after a stressed vowel. I argue that since vowels before lenis stops are generally long &amp;mdash; and, given the phonology of South Welsh &amp;mdash; tense, provection is an example of vowel-consonant interaction, where the same feature is used for the tense/lax contrast in vowels and laryngeal contrast in consonants. I interpret this as supporting emergent feature theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the dots</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/hxphon2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2014/hxphon2014/</guid>
      <description>This poster considers the status of the &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo;/&amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; contrasts across Welsh dialects and argues that it was originally an enhancement of quantity, but becomes phonologized in different ways across different dialect. For the latest in this project, see the 23mfm paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In search of lost phonology</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/ncl-svarabhakti-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/ncl-svarabhakti-talk/</guid>
      <description>This covers much the same ground as this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonological endgame</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</guid>
      <description>I present an analysis of Welsh &amp;lsquo;svarabhakti&amp;rsquo;, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (pwdr &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]). This pattern is said to coexist with a pattern of deleting consonants in such clusters in polysyllables (perygl &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has been argued that the two differing outcomes can be reconciled by appeal to a single constraint on the form of feet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In defence of Richness of the Base</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I briefly present the analysis of mora assignment to consonants in South Welsh. The pattern can be analysed by appeal to the form of the inputs (i.e. with a massive number of accidental gaps, which is undesirable), or by positing a constraint schema with undesirable consequences for factorial typology. I suggest that the latter solution is preferable theoretically, although it may be premature to choose it for that reason alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaning licensing mismatches in Welsh</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2011/explaining-licensing-mismatches-in-welsh/</guid>
      <description>I propose a new analysis of so-called &amp;lsquo;vowel mutation&amp;rsquo; in Welsh, whereby final syllables (both stressed and unstressed) only allow a reduced inventory (by disallowing [ə]). I argue that these final syllables are specified with something like a suprasegmental feature that triggers a feature co-occurrence effect, and that there is no need for recourse to a mechanism of metrical prominence akin to that borne by stressed syllables (as previously suggested in the literature).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Лексикализованные вершины в валлийском синтаксисе</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2007/syntactic-structures/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I attempt to extend Nigel Duffield&amp;rsquo;s idea of &amp;lsquo;lexicalized heads&amp;rsquo; playing a rôle in the triggering of initial mutations, originally proposed for Irish, to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Грамматикализация начальных чередований в валлийском языке</title>
      <link>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/mscl2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/mscl2006/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I suggest that some cases of the historical extension of initial mutation in Welsh to some contexts where they are not explainable with reference to sandhi in Proto-Brythonic, such as the &amp;lsquo;direct object mutation&amp;rsquo;, may have been driven by the interpretation of lenition (&amp;lsquo;soft mutation&amp;rsquo;) as a non-prototypicality marker.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>