<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Celtic on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/celtic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Celtic on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/celtic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of quantitative contrast by place as fortition</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2025/fino2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2025/fino2025/</guid>
      <description>(Poster presentation)
In this paper I consider multiple cases where a consonant quantity contrast is enhanced by place specifications. Focusing on coronal non-glide sonorants, I argue that this process should be analysed as the counterpart of manner changes that are involved in the fortition of glides, as described by Bybee &amp;amp; Easterday (2019).
I consider several cases where a historical distinction between short and long (singleton and geminate) sonorants, especially laterals and coronal nasals, and in some cases also rhotics, is reflected as a qualitative distinction, usually involving place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Length in strange places</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/eshp6/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/eshp6/</guid>
      <description>(Poster presentations)
Present-day Celtic languages are characterized by a typologically relatively unusual contrast between &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; coronal sonorants. It is especially developed in the Gaelic languages. Here, &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; nn ll rr contrast with &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; l n r in postvocalic position (Irish geal &amp;lsquo;bright&amp;rsquo; vs. geall &amp;lsquo;promise&amp;rsquo;). Furthermore, they participate in the initial mutation system, where the &amp;ldquo;fortis&amp;rdquo; sonorants generally occur in the unmutated (&amp;ldquo;radical&amp;rdquo;) grade, and &amp;ldquo;lenis&amp;rdquo; ones in the &amp;ldquo;lenited&amp;rdquo; grade, which historically corresponds to postvocalic contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/celtic-mutations-companion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/celtic-mutations-companion/</guid>
      <description>The Celtic languages are characterized by an elaborate system of alternations of word-initial segments, traditionally known as ‘consonant mutations’. Although historically they arose from across-the-board phonological sandhi, they are now deeply embedded in morphosyntactic processes. They are relatively phonologically coherent, but also non-concatenative, and sensitive to a wide range of lexical, morphological, syntactic and semantic factors. As a result, Celtic mutations present an important test bed for theories of word structure and its interactions with both phonology and syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonological convergence in north-western Europe</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/icngl12/</guid>
      <description>I offer a framework for understanding convergent diachronic developments in the phonological systems of unrelated languages, informed by the life cycle of phonological processes. I focus on preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the traditional /p t k/ series) in several languages of north-west Europe where preaspiration cannot be due to shared inheritance, including the North Germanic languages, varieties of English, the Gaelic languages, Welsh, and the Sámi languages. Preaspiration is often claimed to be typologically rare and diachronically unstable (Silverman 2003, Blevins 2017); hence, its appearance in unrelated languages with a history of contact is often ascribed to that contact (Marstrander 1932, Posti 1954, Wagner 1964, Borgstrøm 1974, Salmons 1992, Gunnar Ólafur Hansson 2001, Rießler 2008, McKenna 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in sonorant-consonant clusters in areal perspective</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/newcastle/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>English epenthesis in lC and rC clusters</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/icehl/</guid>
      <description>The insertion of an unstressed vowel in lC and rC clusters of non-rising sonority (fil[ə]m), is widely known as characteristic of Irish English. It is frequently cited as a substrate feature carried over from Irish, where this process is productive (Ní Chiosáin 1999), as it is in the related Scottish Gaelic. However, this feature is also known from Older Scots, modern Scots dialects (Maguire 2017), and traditional varieties of English. Therefore, it might be an areal effect in the British and Irish Isles; notably, a similar phenomenon is also attested in Welsh (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the gap</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/dias/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/dias/</guid>
      <description>I focus on reconstructing the development of vowel quality distinctions in Brythonic and their connection with the history of vowel quantity between the establishment of the ‘standard’ Brythonic penultimate-stress system and the present day. In the received picture of Modern Welsh phonology, ‘tense’ quality of non-low vowels ([i u e o]) is strongly associated with length and, conversely, ‘lax’ quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ]) is associated with shortness, at least in contrastive, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celtic mutations</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/mutations-bibliography/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/mutations-bibliography/</guid>
      <description>This is an annotated and commented bibliography of works related to the initial consonant mutations of Celtic languages, available by subscription via Oxford Bibliographies Online. Here is the table of contents:
 Introduction General overviews  Descriptions of individual languages  Welsh Breton Cornish Irish Scottish Gaelic Manx Ancient Celtic languages   General bibliographic resources The phonology of mutations  Structuralist approaches Rule-based phonology Nonlinear phonology Optimality Theory  The syntax of mutation  The triggering of mutation Direct object mutation in Welsh  Mutations and morphology Mutations and interfaces  Mutations and other components of grammar Language variation and change Mutation in &amp;lsquo;non-traditional&amp;rsquo; varieties Acquisition and psycholinguistics  Diachrony of mutations  The origins of mutations The historical development of mutations  Typological comparison  Since the published version does not have an acknowledgements facility, I would like to thank here two anonymous reviewers, Peadar Ó Muircheartaigh, Máire Ní Chiosáin, and Christopher Lewin for valuable criticisms and suggestions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European phonological area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</guid>
      <description>This is a local colloquium talk with some preliminary ideas on the topic. If you have any kind of feedback, do please get in touch!
I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European linguistic area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/uit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/uit/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ареальные схождения в фонологии языков Северной Европы</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</guid>
      <description>This is the Russian-language version of this talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nordeuropäische Lautgeographie revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</guid>
      <description>This presents some work in progress on common phonological features in Northern Europe (preaspiration, pitch accents, sonorant pre-occlusion). Email me if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the handout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minority languages, microvariation, minimalism and meaning</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/infl-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/infl-book/</guid>
      <description>This books is a collection of papers presented at the inaugural conference of the Irish Network in Formal Linguistics. To see the table of contents and the editors&amp;rsquo; introduction, go here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonemicization vs. phonologization</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</guid>
      <description>We consider the status of &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (really lenis) fricatives in Old English and in Brythonic Celtic. In the received view, they are not &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; in Old English, yet their distribution is clearly sensitive to phonological structure. We propose that they are distinct phonological symbols, coerced into predictable distributions by the phonological computation. We also offer a similar analysis for Brythonic Celtic. The situation is argued to result as a predictable consequence of the life cycle of phonological processes rather than from language contact, contra previous suggestions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Right at the left edge</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/rara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/rara/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I offer an overview of systems of initial consonant mutations found in the world&amp;rsquo;s languages and attempt to propose a preliminary typology. Many of these phenomena can probably be subsumed under a general theory of nonconcatenative morphology and phonology, but in some cases (notably some of the Celtic ones) the mutations&amp;rsquo; place in the grammar is less clear. For another, more detailed take on this architectural issue in the specific case of Breton, see also this later paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brythonic ‘second lenition’ revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I evaluate the arguments for two competing reconstructions regarding the laryngeal phonology of Proto-Brythonic. I defend the &amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo; interpretation which underplays the role of a &amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo; contrast and instead relies on two separate lenition processes (due to authors such as David Greene and Patrick Sims-Williams), against the &amp;lsquo;classical&amp;rsquo; one due to Kenneth Jackson and defended by John Koch and Graham Isaac, which emphasizes the rôle of aspiration in Proto-Brythonic &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; stops.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>