<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Breton on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/breton/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Breton on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/breton/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Towards a history of the tenseness contrast in Brythonic vowels</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/esohph3/</guid>
      <description>Modern Welsh is similar to many modern Germanic languages such as English, German and Dutch in showing an association between &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; vowel quality and phonological length. Specifically, long vowels tend to be tense in quality and short vowels tend to be lax, with concomitant alternations. As in the Germanic case, there is some disagreement in the literature on whether quality or quantity (or both) is phonologically relevant in Modern Welsh. In this paper I aim to add to this debate via an overview of the diatopic variation in the relationship between vowel quantity and quality in Welsh and more broadly in the Brythonic languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the gap</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/dias/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/dias/</guid>
      <description>I focus on reconstructing the development of vowel quality distinctions in Brythonic and their connection with the history of vowel quantity between the establishment of the ‘standard’ Brythonic penultimate-stress system and the present day. In the received picture of Modern Welsh phonology, ‘tense’ quality of non-low vowels ([i u e o]) is strongly associated with length and, conversely, ‘lax’ quality ([ɪ ʊ ɛ ɔ]) is associated with shortness, at least in contrastive, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A substance-free framework for phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-book/</guid>
      <description>The book is a revised and updated version of parts of my PhD thesis. From the publisher&amp;rsquo;s blurb:
 What is the relationship between phonetics and phonology? Are phonological features innate and universal, and do they have fixed phonetic correlates? These questions have recently received renewed prominence in theoretical debates, and this book explores them from a modular, substance-free perspective.
  This in-depth analysis of Breton serves not only to introduce previously underused data into the theoretical landscape but also to demonstrate the viability of a modular framework for phonology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers the origin of &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic with a view to evaluating the hypothesis that this feature was borrowed from North Germanic varieties spoken by Norse settlers in medieval Scotland. It is shown that the &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; system in Gaelic is tightly bound with metrical structure (more precisely syllable count), certainly diachronically, and probably (at least in some varieties) synchronically. Gaelic &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; is argued to be a plausible internal development, parallel to similar phenomena in other branches of Celtic (specifically in Breton), as well as in Germanic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonology and morphosyntax of Breton mutation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</guid>
      <description>I analyse of initial consonant mutation in a Breton dialect, with a focus on establishing the division of labour between phonology and morphology in the triggering of mutation and its phonological expression. I argue that different types of mutation have different status in the grammar: some are purely phonological, others involve subsegmental morphemes with a clear morphosyntactic rationale, and for some the phonological aspects are clear but the morphosyntactic motivation remains obscure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified account of the behaviour of high vowels in Bothoa Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer an analysis of gliding in Bothoa Breton, as presented in the thesis. I argue that high vowels (especially [i]) either become glides or coalesce with a preceding consonant, in order to avoid hiatus. However, this pattern is disrupted if the high vowel becomes a nucleus at an earlier stage in the cyclic derivation. This provides an argument for stratal models of phonology-morphology interactions, and a strong argument against Output-Output Correspondence, because some of the exceptional non-gliding cases cannot be explained by reference to a free-standing form with transparent non-gliding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconstructing mutation in Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer the analysis of Breton initial mutations found in my thesis. I argue that there is no such thing as a unified &amp;lsquo;mutation&amp;rsquo; mechanism: instead, this labels covers a variety of processes with different places in the overall grammar. The article-length version of the argument is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my Toronto presentation and to a certain extent my talk from the 6th CLC). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started here. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature geometry meets contrastive specification</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</guid>
      <description>I propose an analysis of the interaction between vowel lengthening before voiced obstruents and final devoicing in two languages: Friulian and Breton. I argue that such interactions are transparent and involve a three-way laryngeal contrast formalized geometrically, with true voiceless obstruents the most structurally complex and devoiced ones least. The Friulian analysis was later published here and the Breton was largely incorporated into the thesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
      <description>This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see this talk and this paper). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Too many levels, too few solutions</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/16mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/16mfm/</guid>
      <description>This talk is largely of historic interest, superseded in particular by this talk, also at the mfm.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
