<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 09:50:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Language is only as divisive as you make it</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2017/language-divisive-as-you-make-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 09:50:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2017/language-divisive-as-you-make-it/</guid>
      <description>It gives me no pleasure but the recent opinion in The Times by the highly respected journalist Magnus Linklater really deserves a response. In a handy 899 words, it shows all the blind spots of a majority establishment that simply does not see what the deal is with minority languages. I can see where this position is coming from (Russia is not the most progressive country for awareness of its minority languages among the majority population), but really, one expects better &amp;mdash; not just as far as the policy proposals go (we can surely disagree on that) but even in terms of basic journalism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The government has a plan for Gaelic, and you won&#39;t believe what it is</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2017/dastardly-plan-gaelic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2017/dastardly-plan-gaelic/</guid>
      <description>An important dimension that&amp;rsquo;s often missing from the debates about whether it&amp;rsquo;s worthwhile to support Gaelic or promote Scots in Scotland is why one would do such a thing in the first place. In today&amp;rsquo;s feverish political environment these things slide all too often into outright constitutional mudslinging or at least a debate that foregrounds the essential Scottishness of the country&amp;rsquo;s languages, either as a good thing or a bad thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Gaelic should belong to us all</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2016/gaelic-belongs-to-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 10:24:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2016/gaelic-belongs-to-all/</guid>
      <description>Another day, another stooshie on Scottish Twitter. This time it&amp;rsquo;s Paul Kavanagh sharing some really lovely maps of Lowland areas with Gaelic placenames that he&amp;rsquo;s made.
I&amp;#39;m drawing Gaelic maps cos Scotland has 2 national languages of its own, yet all our maps are in English. pic.twitter.com/uBN0hXsD9U
&amp;mdash; Paul Kavanagh (@weegingerdug) September 26, 2016 
Cue some really rather unenlightened comments with all the usual accusations and allegations (&amp;lsquo;never spoken here&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;pushing it down our throats&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;dead language&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;spend it on hospitals instead&amp;rsquo;), and equally noisy pushback.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scots not a language? They said that in Ukraine too</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2016/scots-not-language-they-said-that-in-ukraine-too/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2016 22:42:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2016/scots-not-language-they-said-that-in-ukraine-too/</guid>
      <description>It seems that the Twitter mocking of the weekly Scots column in The National has assumed the quality of a ritual. There is a lot to be said about this (I said a bit when the whole thing just launched). Today&amp;rsquo;s post is on a fairly narrow topic: how the debate about whether Scots &amp;lsquo;is a language&amp;rsquo; has a nice parallel in the history of the East Slavic languages Ukrainian and Belarusian.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book review: Pam na fu Cymru</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/pam-na-fu-cymru/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 18:49:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/pam-na-fu-cymru/</guid>
      <description>What follows is a short(ish) review of an excellently provocative new(ish) book by Simon Brooks, Pam na fu Cymru: Methiant cenedlaetholdeb Cymraeg (&amp;lsquo;Why Wales wasn&amp;rsquo;t: The failure of Welsh nationalism&amp;rsquo;).1 It is, as the author notes, the second part of what may be deemed a trilogy, following from the no less interesting collection Pa beth yr aethoch chi allan i&amp;rsquo;w achub? (&amp;lsquo;What did you go out to save?&amp;rsquo;), which also posed some rather less comfortable questions for the Welsh language (re)vitalization movement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching language in schools: beyond foreign languages</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/language-in-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/language-in-schools/</guid>
      <description>An excellent piece by Dani Garavelli in Scotland on Sunday on the state of modern foreign languages in Scottish schools includes a familiar litany of failings: a relatively early end of compulsory language study, staffing issues, teaching methods, differences between schools with more opportunities for pupils from more privileged backgrounds, and so on, and on, and on. One of the points strikes a bit closer to home for me:
 One [factor] is that our children are taught very little English grammar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irish isn’t ‘compromised’ — it just needs more support</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/irish-isnt-compromised-it-just-needs-more-support/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/irish-isnt-compromised-it-just-needs-more-support/</guid>
      <description>There is a very interesting article now up on Slugger O&amp;rsquo;Toole, based around an interview with Dr Diarmuid Johnson: Do urban Gaeltachts produce a compromised Irish?. Go read it now &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s well written and very well informed, especially if you compare it to the general level of debate around in the Irish language in Northern Ireland (as some &amp;mdash; though by no means all &amp;mdash; comments demonstrate).
Full disclosure &amp;mdash; I&amp;rsquo;m an admirer of Diarmuid Johnson, and I owe him a debt of gratitude for the kind assistance I received from him in the course of my own research in West Wales.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Emacs hold your hand: don&#39;t edit a TeX file when you don&#39;t mean to</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/making-emacs-hold-your-hand-dont-edit-a-tex-file-when-you-dont-mean-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 20:18:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/making-emacs-hold-your-hand-dont-edit-a-tex-file-when-you-dont-mean-to/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a user of LaTeX, R and Emacs, I naturally write up my research in &lt;code&gt;.Rnw&lt;/code&gt; files, using &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name/knitr&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt; to produce &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; sources. With Emacs, this means I have access to both the awesome AUCTeX for writing LaTeX and the excellent ESS environment for the statistics at the same time. However, being the absent-minded academic that I am, I sometimes end up opening the woven &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file instead of the &lt;code&gt;.Rnw&lt;/code&gt; and make edits to that, which means it gets overwritten and lost the next time I run &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt;. This is suboptimal, but of course Emacs allows us to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why teach the kids Gaelic if you can teach them Mandarin?</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/why-teach-the-kids-gaelic-if-you-can-teach-them-mandarin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/why-teach-the-kids-gaelic-if-you-can-teach-them-mandarin/</guid>
      <description>This question, asked by the STV journalist Stephen Daisley, caused a bit of a stooshie on Twitter a couple of days back:
Is there a strong, non-heritage case for spending taxpayers&amp;#39; money promoting Gaelic instead of thriving, globally-spoken languages?
&amp;mdash; Stephen Daisley (@JournoStephen) March 24, 2015 
This is an important debate, and no points for guessing where I stand on this. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to rehearse why I think minority languages are important – check some of the replies for good ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humidity causes complex tones?</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/humidity-causes-complex-tones/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2015/humidity-causes-complex-tones/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.koensebregts.nl&#34;&gt;Koen Sebregts&lt;/a&gt;  points out that the title of my post is misleading, since the authors explicitly state they do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; predict humidity to cause complex tones. I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it unchanged as a warning to myself.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a new &amp;lsquo;geophonetics&amp;rsquo; paper out at PNAS this morning &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1417413112&#34;&gt;Climate, vocal folds, and tonal languages: Connecting the physiological and geographic dots&lt;/a&gt; by Caleb Everett, Damián Blasi, and Seán Roberts. In a nutshell, the claim, as I understand it, is that since low humidity is inimical to precise manipulation of vocal folds, languages with &amp;lsquo;complex tone&amp;rsquo; (understood as having a more than two-way pitch-based contrast) are unlikely to thrive in regions with low humidity (i.e. hot and arid, and all types of cold). This hypothesis appears to explain the areal patterns in the prevalence of tone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching slides with pandoc and reveal.js</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/teaching-slides-with-pandoc-and-reveal-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/teaching-slides-with-pandoc-and-reveal-js/</guid>
      <description>This past semester I taught a new course entitled Phonological Theory. Apart from the content, I decided to experiment a bit with the technical details, specifically using pandoc and reveal.js to do the slides and lecture notes.
I&amp;rsquo;m a pretty consistent LaTeX user, so to the extent I do slides I do them in beamer. There is nothing inherently problematic with this, and AUCTeX saves typing a lot of the boilerplate, but writing two–three presentations per week is still time-consuming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norsemen in Scotland: A linguistic view, part 2</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/norsemen-in-scotland-a-linguistic-view-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/norsemen-in-scotland-a-linguistic-view-part-2/</guid>
      <description>(Part 1 is here)
We will now zoom in on the linguistic features that have been identified as showing evidence of Norse-Gaelic contacts: the lexicon, preaspiration, and pitch accents. As a phonologist, I won&amp;rsquo;t have very much to say about the lexicon, but the other two concern me quite a bit. So I&amp;rsquo;ll start with them.
Preaspiration We start some way off our destination: in English. (If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever taken an introductory linguistics course, feel free to skip the rest of this paragraph.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norsemen in Scotland: A linguistic view, part 1</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/norsemen-in-scotland-a-linguistic-view-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/norsemen-in-scotland-a-linguistic-view-part-1/</guid>
      <description>It is quite common knowledge that the history of English has been significantly influenced by the settlement of North Germanic speakers in the north-eastern part of what is now England. From relatively trivial words like skirt and window to the less commonly borrowed items like they and all the way to the general simplification of the Old English system of inflections (e.g. case in nouns) in the Middle English period: you name it, the Vikings have been blamed for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting ESS and AUCTeX to play nicely with knitr</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/getting-ess-and-auctex-to-play-nicely-with-knitr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/getting-ess-and-auctex-to-play-nicely-with-knitr/</guid>
      <description>Although my job title is &amp;lsquo;Lecturer in Theoretical Phonology&amp;rsquo; (no, really, I&amp;rsquo;ve been getting into more empirical work. I went on a data collection trip to South Wales in February to work with Welsh, and only early this week we had two great days collecting Gaelic data in North Argyll – not an area readily associated with Gaelic these days, but in fact we found quite a few very good speakers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emacs: give a DOI, get a BibTeX entry</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/emacs-give-a-doi-get-a-bibtex-entry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/emacs-give-a-doi-get-a-bibtex-entry/</guid>
      <description>One of my enduring frustrations with the various academic publishing platforms (CJO, ScienceDirect, JSTOR and their ilk) is the wildly inconsistent way in which they export BibTeX entries for articles. Sometimes they put them right on the browser page for easy copy-and-paste; sometimes it comes up after a few clicks in a new window; sometimes you end up downloading a file with an impossibly long or counterintuitive name, or called something like science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A nynorsk for Scotland?</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/a-nynorsk-for-scotland/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/a-nynorsk-for-scotland/</guid>
      <description>With the Scottish independence debate we hear a lot about the Scandinavian connections and (dis)similarities. I do have my opinions on many of those despite being completely unqualified, but here&amp;rsquo;s one thing that strikes me and that I do know something about: how many people (apart from Guy Puzey and Øystein Vangsnes) have commented on the parallels between Norway and Scotland with regard to their linguistic landscape?
Norway The official position is that there are two written forms of the (single) Norwegian language, bokmål and nynorsk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/blog/2014/first-post/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t know what, if anything, will be happening here, but I do sometimes get the urge to rant about things that tweets are too short for. So I&amp;rsquo;ve just this up for now, and hopefully its existence will motivate me to write a bit more.
Wait and see, in other words.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>