<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prosodic structure on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Prosodic structure on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/prosodic-structure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Suprasegmental phenomena in Germanic: Tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/oxfordre-germanic-accents/</guid>
      <description>Several Germanic varieties possess a phonological contrast usually referred to as “tonal accent.” They demonstrate phonological contrasts between words that are otherwise identical in their segmental make-up and the location of stress, as in (Urban East) Norwegian bønder ‘farmers’ and bønner ‘beans’, both segmentally [ˈbønːər]. Usually, the contrast is treated as implemented by pitch trajectories; hence, the name &amp;lsquo;tonal accent.&amp;rsquo; Within Germanic, tonal accent contrasts are found in three (historically, perhaps four) areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The moraic mess that is Danish</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/fino2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2024/fino2024/</guid>
      <description>In moraic theory, particular syllables of a languages are typically defined as either heavy of light for all phonological rules (Hyman 1985). However, some languages seem to treat the same syllables as light for some rules and heavy for others (e.g. Davis 2011:129-132). To account for such behaviour, Hayes (1995) proposes that moraic structure can be organized as a layered grid, where the bottom layer, typically involved in syllable-internal patterns, underlies the top layer, typically involved in higher-level prosodic structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A metrical approach to ternarity in Northern European accentual contrasts</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/30mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2023/30mfm/</guid>
      <description>Many languages of Northern Europe possess typologically non-trivial systems of prosodic con- trasts, analysed variously as ‘tonal/pitch accent’ (North and West Germanic, Gaelic, Baltic), laryngeal accent/stød (North Germanic, Baltic, Finnic, Gaelic), and ternary quantity distinctions (Finnic, Sámi, Gaelic). In this paper, I show that despite the diversity of phonetic correlates, the fundamental structure of these systems is almost perfectly isomorphic. Specifically, they are often three-way contrasts between stressed syllables that lack the segmental material to support the accentual contrast, and two kinds of stressed syllables that do have such segmental content: one bearing some marked accentual specification and one lacking it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metrical structure and Stratal Phonology provide a complete account of Danish stød</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</guid>
      <description>In this paper we demonstrate that the patterning of stød in Standard Danish submits to a complete, non-stipulative account within an approach that embraces metrical structure as the mechanism behind accentual contrasts (Köhnlein 2019), and the main tenets of Stratal Phonology (Bermúdez- Otero 2018). Our approach maintains the empirical coverage of the ‘Non-Stød Model’ developed by Basbøll (2005 et passim), but builds on widely accepted principles of morphology-phonology interaction instead of a proliferation of bespoke domains, in addition to incorporating insights from other approaches (notably Itô &amp;amp; Mester 2015).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The origin of West Jutland stød</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I offer a reconstruction of the history of the so-called West Jutland stød that reaffirms the proposition that it is a reflex of Proto-Nordic preaspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonology of Gaelic tonal accent</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gaelic-tonal-accent-rnag2018/</guid>
      <description>It is well known that many varieties of Gaelic show an opposition between two classes of words that is implemented by suprasegmental means such as pitch and glottalization. These phenomena have been compared to the ‘tonal accents’ of the North and West Germanic languages (notably by Ternes 1980, 2006), and a number of analyses have been proposed in the theoretical linguis- tics literature. In this paper, I summarize the patterns found across traditional varieties of Scottish Gaelic, and focus on the (limited number of) synchronic alternations that involve accent-related phenomena.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tonal stability and tonogenesis in North Germanic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/nrn-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/nrn-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>The origin of North Germanic tonal accents is a question with a long history and a range of available answers. Although the basic facts are not in dispute, the accents&amp;rsquo; historical development remains controversial. In this paper, I aim to contribute an argument in favour of the view that tonal accent arose in post-Viking Age North Germanic in connection with changes in syllable count (Oftedal 1952; Elstad 1980; Bye 2004, 2011; Hognestad 2012).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European phonological area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</guid>
      <description>This is a local colloquium talk with some preliminary ideas on the topic. If you have any kind of feedback, do please get in touch!
I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosodic structure and suprasegmental features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stod/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stod/</guid>
      <description>This paper sets out in detail the analysis first offered in my 21mfm presentation. I examine the so-called &amp;lsquo;short-vowel stød&amp;rsquo; (kortvokalstød) found in certain island dialects of Danish, which differs from the &amp;lsquo;common Danish&amp;rsquo; stød in that it is associated with light syllables (open syllable with short vowels or closed syllables with low-sonority codas) rather than heavy ones. I argue that it is best represented as a [constricted glottis] feature associated with a segmentally empty mora, which is projected due to top-down requirements on the internal structure of suprasegmental constituents.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>