<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prosodic Structure on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/prosodic-structure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Prosodic Structure on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/prosodic-structure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tonal stability and tonogenesis in North Germanic</title>
      <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/nrn-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/nrn-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>The origin of North Germanic tonal accents is a question with a long history and a range of available answers. Although the basic facts are not in dispute, the accents&amp;rsquo; historical development remains controversial. In this paper, I aim to contribute an argument in favour of the view that tonal accent arose in post-Viking Age North Germanic in connection with changes in syllable count (Oftedal 1952; Elstad 1980; Bye 2004, 2011; Hognestad 2012).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European phonological area</title>
      <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</guid>
      <description>This is a local colloquium talk with some preliminary ideas on the topic. If you have any kind of feedback, do please get in touch!
I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosodic structure and suprasegmental features</title>
      <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/stod/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/stod/</guid>
      <description>This paper sets out in detail the analysis first offered in my 21mfm presentation. I examine the so-called &amp;lsquo;short-vowel stød&amp;rsquo; (kortvokalstød) found in certain island dialects of Danish, which differs from the &amp;lsquo;common Danish&amp;rsquo; stød in that it is associated with light syllables (open syllable with short vowels or closed syllables with low-sonority codas) rather than heavy ones. I argue that it is best represented as a [constricted glottis] feature associated with a segmentally empty mora, which is projected due to top-down requirements on the internal structure of suprasegmental constituents.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>