<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>North Germanic on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/north-germanic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in North Germanic on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/north-germanic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/arne-kruse-fs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/arne-kruse-fs/</guid>
      <description>What was the sociolinguistic situation in the North Atlantic in the Viking Age and its aftermath? In the near-total absence of reliable, contemporary historical sources, enquiry into language maintenance and shift in the Northern Isles, the Hebrides, and the Irish Sea basin is a fascinating, multidisciplinary enterprise, to which Arne Kruse has made very significant contributions. In this chapter, I consider how the Western Norse vernacular of the Scandinavian settlers in much of this region was ultimately replaced by the Gaelic languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Livssyklusmodellen for fonologiske mønster i norsk og nordisk</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/mons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/mons/</guid>
      <description>I føredraget set eg fram nokre resultat frå ei gransking av fleire fonologiske mønster i norsk (og i den breiare vestnordiske konteksten), med utgangspunkt i livssyklusmodellen for lydendring. I denne modellen skjer lydendring ved at automatisk fonetisk variasjon vert til fonetiske reglar, deretter til kategoriske fonologiske reglar og vidare til sykliske fonologiske reglar i samspel med morfologien. Eg viser korleis denne modellen kastar nytt lys over fleire velkjende mønster i norsk fonologi og morfologi, frå både strukturelle, historiske og dialektologiske standpunkt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metrical structure and Stratal Phonology provide a complete account of Danish stød</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2022/29mfm/</guid>
      <description>In this paper we demonstrate that the patterning of stød in Standard Danish submits to a complete, non-stipulative account within an approach that embraces metrical structure as the mechanism behind accentual contrasts (Köhnlein 2019), and the main tenets of Stratal Phonology (Bermúdez- Otero 2018). Our approach maintains the empirical coverage of the ‘Non-Stød Model’ developed by Basbøll (2005 et passim), but builds on widely accepted principles of morphology-phonology interaction instead of a proliferation of bespoke domains, in addition to incorporating insights from other approaches (notably Itô &amp;amp; Mester 2015).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The origin of West Jutland stød</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/aarhus/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I offer a reconstruction of the history of the so-called West Jutland stød that reaffirms the proposition that it is a reflex of Proto-Nordic preaspiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drift revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/eshp4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/eshp4/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I offer a framework for understanding convergent diachronic developments in the phonological systems of unrelated languages, informed by the life cycle of phonological processes. I focus on preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the traditional /p t k/ series) in several languages of north-western Europe that are either unrelated, or not related closely enough for preaspiration to be inherited: they include the North Germanic languages, varieties of English, the Gaelic languages, Welsh, and the Sámi languages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspirasjon i norsk i nye og gamle kjelder</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gjert-kristoffersen-fs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/gjert-kristoffersen-fs/</guid>
      <description>This paper (in Norwegian) contains an overview of traditional and modern sources of information regarding preaspiration of |fortis| stops (the /p t k/ series) in Norwegian vernaculars. Traditional sources note them in the dialects of North Gudbrandsdalen, Härjedalen, Rogaland, and a few in Northern Norway. However, I argue that preaspiration is much more widespread than that: I collect evidence from more recent instrumental studies, from dialect corpora, and from an original acoustic study with a focus on Northern Norwegian varieties, and argue, following scholars such as Gunnar Ólafur Hansson and Pétur Helgason, that preaspiration is pervasive in North Germanic vernaculars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation and (presumed) change in Norwegian preaspiration</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/ucl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/ucl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norwegian preaspiration in traditional and modern sources</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/fgls/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/fgls/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I survey traditional descriptions of Norwegian dialects with particular attention to their discussion of voiceless stop preaspiration, and conclude that it is highly probable preaspiration has been consistently under-reported in these sources. As surveyed in detail by Pétur Helgason (2002), preaspiration in Norwegian has been reported most prominently for northern Gudbrandsdalen (Ross 1907; Horne 1917), Rogaland (Oftedal 1947; Wolter 1965), and for Senja by Iversen (1913). To Helgason’s list should be added Vestvågøya (Elstad 1982) and contact varieties in Northern Norway (Jahr 2008).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microvariation in laryngeal realism</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/25mfm/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I consider the range of microvariation in the expression of laryngeal contrast, focusing on (voiceless) preaspiration in North Germanic. On the basis of an acoustic study, I suggest that both the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization have been under-reported in existing descriptions. This, in turn, has important consequences for our understanding of the phonology of laryngeal contrast. Specifically, I argue that the observed variation in laryngeal phenomena is incompatible with a version of &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; that produces inferences about phonological specifications on the basis of phonetic implementation; instead, I advocate a more abstract approach that gives primacy to phonological behaviour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation in North Germanic preaspiration</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2017/variation-north-germanic-preaspiration/</guid>
      <description>I consider the extent of cross-dialectal variation in the expression of laryngeal contrast within North Germanic, with a focus on (voiceless) preaspiration, and suggest that the presence of preaspiration and the diversity of its realization across the North Germanic area have been significantly under-reported in the past.
As discussed by Pétur Helgason (2002), whilst preaspiration and sonorant devoicing in Insular Nordic have long been recognized by the scholarship, their distribution and behaviour in mainland varieties have been less well understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tonal stability and tonogenesis in North Germanic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/nrn-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/nrn-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>The origin of North Germanic tonal accents is a question with a long history and a range of available answers. Although the basic facts are not in dispute, the accents&amp;rsquo; historical development remains controversial. In this paper, I aim to contribute an argument in favour of the view that tonal accent arose in post-Viking Age North Germanic in connection with changes in syllable count (Oftedal 1952; Elstad 1980; Bye 2004, 2011; Hognestad 2012).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European phonological area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/linguistic-circle/</guid>
      <description>This is a local colloquium talk with some preliminary ideas on the topic. If you have any kind of feedback, do please get in touch!
I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel length in Shetland Norn</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/amc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/amc/</guid>
      <description>One of the areas in which Scandinavian influence is apparent in the traditional Shetland Scots dialect is the distribution of vowel length: Shetland Scots generally follows the Scottish Vowel Length Rule, but also shows the complementary distribution of consonant and vowel length known from modern North Germanic languages.
During the earliest development of Shetland Scots, three different systems of vowel length can be argued to have been in contact:
 (Nearly) unconstrained vowel length, as in Old Norse Scandinavian combinatory vowel length The Scottish Vowel Length Rule  All these systems were in the process of change in our time period, with System 1 giving way to System 2 across Scandinavia, and the SVLR also developing at about the same time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The northwest European linguistic area</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/uit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2016/uit/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I discuss the recurrence of several cross-linguistically rare phonological phenomena in unrelated languages spoken in northwestern Europe. Identified already by Jakobson in the 1930s as forming part of a &amp;lsquo;Baltic&amp;rsquo; Sprachbund defined by the use of &amp;lsquo;tonality&amp;rsquo;, the northwest European &amp;lsquo;phonological province&amp;rsquo; is characterized by the presence of features such as preaspiration (North Germanic, Sámi, Scottish Gaelic &amp;mdash; but also Welsh and English), tonal accents and laryngealization (North Germanic, Scottish Gaelic, West Germanic, Baltic &amp;mdash; and some Finnic languages), sonorant pre-occlusion (in North Germanic, Sámi, Cornish, Manx), and excrescent vowels (Sámi, Irish and Scottish Gaelic, some West Germanic varieties).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosodic structure and suprasegmental features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stod/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stod/</guid>
      <description>This paper sets out in detail the analysis first offered in my 21mfm presentation. I examine the so-called &amp;lsquo;short-vowel stød&amp;rsquo; (kortvokalstød) found in certain island dialects of Danish, which differs from the &amp;lsquo;common Danish&amp;rsquo; stød in that it is associated with light syllables (open syllable with short vowels or closed syllables with low-sonority codas) rather than heavy ones. I argue that it is best represented as a [constricted glottis] feature associated with a segmentally empty mora, which is projected due to top-down requirements on the internal structure of suprasegmental constituents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonetic (non-)explanation in historical phonology: Duration, harmony, and dissimilation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/phonetic-non-explanation-in-historical-phonology-duration-harmony-and-dissimilation/</guid>
      <description>We consider the value of phonetically based explanations for phonological change by tracing the phonologization paths of durational asymmetries between vowels. The literature on phonetic motivations for phonological change identifies relative shortness of one vowel with respect to another as an important precursor to vowel reduction, which, in turn, may feed hypercorrection of the reduced vowel to give rise to vowel harmony phenomena. We examine such a case from Nivkh in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preaspiration and tonal accents as Northern Gaelic features</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/</guid>
      <description>I argue that the origin of both pitch accents and preaspiration in Gaelic is best understood in the context of a &amp;lsquo;Northern Gaelic&amp;rsquo; area covering Ulster and Scotland, as opposed to Connacht and Munster. Within this area, both preaspiration and pitch accents show the classic pattern of peripheral archaisms, with Lewis and West Ulster as remnant areas and Argyll as the most innovative zone. This suggests that the stronger Norse presence in the Hebrides does not correlate with a denser distribution of potential contact features, and thus the developments in both cases need not have been triggered by contact &amp;mdash; even though a reinforcing role for contact is very difficult (and probably undesirable) to exclude.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An echoing tone</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/</guid>
      <description>This talk was presented at the Nordic Research Network 2015 conference at the University of Edinburgh.
In this talk, I consider the origins of pitch accents in North Germanic and in Scottish Gaelic. I argue that in both cases the more plausible hypothesis involves the realization of an identical tonal melody over different temporal domains, particularly by the mechanism of peak delay. This is not a new idea, but I support it by a consideration of the interaction of tone and apocope in Zealand Danish and in Central Scandinavian.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/icngl-proceedings/</guid>
      <description>This paper considers the origin of &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic with a view to evaluating the hypothesis that this feature was borrowed from North Germanic varieties spoken by Norse settlers in medieval Scotland. It is shown that the &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; system in Gaelic is tightly bound with metrical structure (more precisely syllable count), certainly diachronically, and probably (at least in some varieties) synchronically. Gaelic &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; is argued to be a plausible internal development, parallel to similar phenomena in other branches of Celtic (specifically in Breton), as well as in Germanic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ареальные схождения в фонологии языков Северной Европы</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/moscow-phonology-seminar/</guid>
      <description>This is the Russian-language version of this talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nordeuropäische Lautgeographie revisited</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/manchester-areal-phonology-talk/</guid>
      <description>This presents some work in progress on common phonological features in Northern Europe (preaspiration, pitch accents, sonorant pre-occlusion). Email me if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the handout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
      <description>I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge talk to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving segments, but instead features attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</guid>
      <description>I consider the nature of the so-called &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic and argue that the contrast is one of metrical structure rather than lexical tone, at least diachronically, and probably also synchronically. This means that they can be reconstructed with an internal origin, and no recourse to contact with North Germanic is necessary to account for their appearance. The paper has the analysis in detail, and the historical argument is expounded in some detail in later talks here and here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>