<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phonology-morphology interface on Pavel Iosad</title>
    <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonology-morphology-interface/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Phonology-morphology interface on Pavel Iosad</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anghyflawn.net/categories/phonology-morphology-interface/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Жизненный цикл морфонологических процессов в русском языке</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2021/otipl-colloquium/</guid>
      <description>Характерное свойство динамических подходов к русской фонологии и морфонологии — как выполненных в духе порождающих фонологических теорий, так и (пост)структуралистских — обширное использование правил, обязательно применяемых в определенном порядке. Обоснование этого порядка — важнейшая задача для теоретического осмысления фактов русского языка, без решения которой динамические подходы являются по сути нефальсифицируемыми: в отсутствие четких ограничений на количество правил и порядок их применения любое чередование можно подвергнуть сколь угодно абстрактному анализу с произвольным количеством правил.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebooting Slavic phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/abralin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2020/abralin/</guid>
      <description>The Slavic languages have historically played a very prominent role in the development of Western phonological theory, from some of the earliest pioneers of phonemic theory such as Jan Baudouin de Courtenay, Mikołaj Kruszewski and Lev Shcherba, through the Praguian structuralism of Nikolai Trubetzkoy and (early) Roman Jakobson, and to some of the foundational work of generative phonology. In particular, Morris Halle and Theodore Lightner offered comprehensive analyses of Russian phonology that relied heavily on multi-level derivations, abstract underlying representations and a suite of rules that largely recapitulated diachronic developments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Per aspera ad astra</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/vaplujub/</guid>
      <description>In this brief paper, I suggest that, contrary to much previous literature, the quality of the yer vowels in Modern Russian is predictable, and does not have to be encoded in the underlying representation. This is a consequence of an approach that rejects the long-standing tradition of positing highly abstract underlying representations, and in particular derives the palatalization of consonants from the backness of following vowels. I argue that the quality of yers is predictable from the context, particularly from the palatalization of preceding consonants and from whether the morphological context drives the otherwise well-known e ~ ’o alternation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Морфонологическая стратификация в русском языке | Stratal phonology and Russian morphophonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/stratal-phonology-russian-morphophonology/</guid>
      <description>В работе предлагается анализ фрагмента русской морфонологии – чередования e~’o и некоторых связанных с ним явлений – в духе порождающих стратификационных подходов наподобие лексической фонологии. Цель работы – показать, что это чередование обладает целым рядом свойств, обычно характерных для основообразующих фонологических правил. Таким образом, утверждается, что, с одной стороны, русский материал поддерживает модель, предполагающую стратификацию морфонологических систем, а с другой – стратификационные модели открывают продуктивные подходы к анализу русской морфонологии, эксплицитно связывающие морфонологическую структуру как с фонологическими закономерностями, так и с морфологической и семантической структурой русских слов.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bringing it all together</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/farl3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2019/farl3/</guid>
      <description>Palatalization processes and the e ~ ’o alternation are both classic problems in Russian (morpho)phonology. It is now widely recognized that there is a relationship between the two: where suffixes are relevant to the e ~ ’o alternation, palatalizing suffixes require the front vowel in the preceding morpheme, and non-palatalizing suffixes require the back vowel (see particularly Itkin 1994). This strongly suggests a phonological analysis of the e ~ ’o alternation, which has hitherto proven elusive, primarily since there is no principled, non-circular account of apparent lexical exceptions and of suffixes that are neutral for the purposes of the alternation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Stratal Phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2018/evidence-for-stratal-phonology/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I discuss the nature of evidence for the stratal organization of morphophonological grammar. Much — of course by no means all — of the currently available evidence in favour a stratal approach to morphology-phonology interactions comes from languages such as English, where the stratification of the lexicon has a strong historical rationale, or the Romance languages, where one can often easily observe morphological constituency at the level below the word.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welsh svarabhakti as stem allomorphy</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/svarabhakti/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/svarabhakti/</guid>
      <description>This paper develops the analysis in this presentation. I offer an analysis of Welsh epenthesis, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (pwdr &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]) and deletion in such clusters in polysyllables (perygl &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has previously been argued that both processes can be analysed in a single phonological grammar. I show that this is not tenable for South Welsh dialects, and propose an analysis in terms of part-of-speech-specific allomorphy, formalized as lexical storage of POS-characterized stems rather than roots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonology and morphosyntax of Breton mutation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/breton-mutation/</guid>
      <description>I analyse of initial consonant mutation in a Breton dialect, with a focus on establishing the division of labour between phonology and morphology in the triggering of mutation and its phonological expression. I argue that different types of mutation have different status in the grammar: some are purely phonological, others involve subsegmental morphemes with a clear morphosyntactic rationale, and for some the phonological aspects are clear but the morphosyntactic motivation remains obscure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phonologization of redundant contrasts and the Contrastivist Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2014/phonologization-of-redundant-contrasts-and-the-contrastivist-hypothesis/</guid>
      <description>I consider two cases of predictable distributions of phonological categories: &amp;lsquo;tense&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;lax&amp;rsquo; long vowels in South-West Welsh and the two varieties of the FACE vowel in Ulster English. Their predictable (&amp;lsquo;non-phonemic&amp;rsquo;) distribution is a challenge to the Contrastivist Hypothesis, but I argue that it can be accommodated if we assume that learning, including category formation, proceeds bottom-up, and that learners do not unlearn predictably distributed categories unless compelled to do so by alternations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In search of lost phonology</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/ncl-svarabhakti-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2013/ncl-svarabhakti-talk/</guid>
      <description>This covers much the same ground as this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The phonological endgame</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</guid>
      <description>I present an analysis of Welsh &amp;lsquo;svarabhakti&amp;rsquo;, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (pwdr &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]). This pattern is said to coexist with a pattern of deleting consonants in such clusters in polysyllables (perygl &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has been argued that the two differing outcomes can be reconciled by appeal to a single constraint on the form of feet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified account of the behaviour of high vowels in Bothoa Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer an analysis of gliding in Bothoa Breton, as presented in the thesis. I argue that high vowels (especially [i]) either become glides or coalesce with a preceding consonant, in order to avoid hiatus. However, this pattern is disrupted if the high vowel becomes a nucleus at an earlier stage in the cyclic derivation. This provides an argument for stratal models of phonology-morphology interactions, and a strong argument against Output-Output Correspondence, because some of the exceptional non-gliding cases cannot be explained by reference to a free-standing form with transparent non-gliding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconstructing mutation in Breton</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</guid>
      <description>I offer the analysis of Breton initial mutations found in my thesis. I argue that there is no such thing as a unified &amp;lsquo;mutation&amp;rsquo; mechanism: instead, this labels covers a variety of processes with different places in the overall grammar. The article-length version of the argument is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A bad case of excessive computation</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</guid>
      <description>I use the analysis of palatalization in Modern Standard Russian offered here to argue that these data do not provide a watertight argument for multilevel phonological computation, and that phonological analysis must be combined with a theory of ordering (such as Stratal OT) if the hypothesis of parallel computation is to be challenged.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How good is the internal evidence for multiple-level phonological computation? A view from Russian</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</guid>
      <description>Relying in part on the analysis of palatalization offered here, I argue that Russian does not provide strong phonology-internal evidence for level ordering, contra suggestions by authors such as Morris Halle and Jerzy Rubach. A more focused argument to the same effect is offered here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Right at the left edge</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/rara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/writing/rara/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I offer an overview of systems of initial consonant mutations found in the world&amp;rsquo;s languages and attempt to propose a preliminary typology. Many of these phenomena can probably be subsumed under a general theory of nonconcatenative morphology and phonology, but in some cases (notably some of the Celtic ones) the mutations&amp;rsquo; place in the grammar is less clear. For another, more detailed take on this architectural issue in the specific case of Breton, see also this later paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All that glistens is not gold</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/glow31-mutations/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I argue that purely phonological (e.g. autosegmental) approaches to initial consonant mutations in languages such as Fula and Irish are insufficient to account for the facts fully. In many ways this does not represent my current thinking on these matters, as can be established by looking, for instance, at this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial consonant mutation and information flow in Mende</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/ocp5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2008/ocp5/</guid>
      <description>I reanalyse the pattern of initial consonant mutation in Mende by arguing that the so-called &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade, usually assumed to be the derive one, is the default case morphosyntactically, and thus that the consonant mutation mechanism must derive the &amp;lsquo;strong&amp;rsquo; rather than the &amp;lsquo;weak&amp;rsquo; grade. This is problematic for autosegmental, or probably any purely phonological, accounts of mutation, since the relationship between the weak and strong grades is one-to-many, so I suggest the choice between the two grades is made outside of phonology, with direct reference to the morphosyntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Грамматикализация начальных чередований в валлийском языке</title>
      <link>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/mscl2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anghyflawn.net/presentation/2006/mscl2006/</guid>
      <description>In this talk I suggest that some cases of the historical extension of initial mutation in Welsh to some contexts where they are not explainable with reference to sandhi in Proto-Brythonic, such as the &amp;lsquo;direct object mutation&amp;rsquo;, may have been driven by the interpretation of lenition (&amp;lsquo;soft mutation&amp;rsquo;) as a non-prototypicality marker.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>