<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Phonology Morphology Interface in Pavel Iosad </title>
	  <itunes:author>Pavel Iosad</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Pavel Iosad</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>pavel.iosad@ed.ac.uk</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Linguistics, phonology, historical linguistics, pdf</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="http://anghyflawn.github.io//img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/categories/phonology-morphology-interface/</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
    
    <updated>Thu, 28 May 2015 13:49:05 BST</updated>



<item>
<title>Preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic and its contribution to prosodic structure</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/preaspiration-in-north-argyll-gaelic-and-its-contribution-to-prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper reports the preliminary results of an acoustic study of
preaspiration in the Gaelic of North Argyll. Existing descriptions
identify this area as reflecting Old Irish and Old Norse &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo;
geminates as [xp xt xk] clusters (&amp;lsquo;pre-affricates&amp;rsquo;), but, to our
knowledge, no targeted acoustic study of these varieties had been
performed to date. Our results confirm that the preaspiration found in
other varieties corresponds to dorsal (velar or uvular) frication in
North Argyll, rather than other conceivable interpretations of the
impressionistic descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discuss the broader repercussions of these findings regarding the
nature of preaspiration in these varieties. In particular, we find only
very scant evidence of pre-frication after long vowels (in words like
&lt;em&gt;pàpa&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;Pope&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;bàta&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;boat&amp;rsquo;), which contrasts with regular
pre-frication after short vowels. This apparent neutralization of
laryngeal contrast outside the initial foot suggests that (at least
Argyll) Gaelic shows a weakly unconditioned reduction process (lenition;
Honeybone 2012) similar to languages such as English or
Icelandic. Further, if this analysis is correct, it suggests that
preaspiration in North Argyll Gaelic contributes a mora to the stressed
syllable (in parallel to South Argyll Gaelic, and in an echo of Ó Baoill
1980). We argue that the development from preaspiration to a moraic
segment is parallel to that hypothesized by Pétur Helgason (2002) for
Icelandic, and discuss the consequences of this analysis for the
question of internal vs external origin of preaspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Representation and variation in substance-free phonology: A case study in Celtic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/thesis/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/thesis/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here you will find some material related to my PhD thesis entitled &lt;em&gt;Representation and variation in substance-free phonology&lt;/em&gt;, which I submitted to the University of Tromsø on 3rd August 2012 and which I successfully defended in a &lt;em&gt;viva voce&lt;/em&gt; examination on 18th February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The official version of the thesis can be downloaded from &lt;a href=&#34;http://munin.uit.no&#34;&gt;Munin&lt;/a&gt;, the University of Tromsø&amp;rsquo;s institutional repository, &lt;a href=&#34;http://hdl.handle.net/10037/4794&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can download the LaTeX source code for the thesis &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.anghyflawn.net/phd-thesis&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an &lt;a href=&#34;http://uit.no/ansatte/organisasjon/nyhetsartikkel?p_document_id=325183&amp;amp;p_dimension_id=88147&amp;amp;p_menu=28723&amp;amp;p_lang=2&#34;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; I did for the faculty&amp;rsquo;s web site (it is in Norwegian).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/pdf/viva.presentation.pdf&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the handout for the short presentation of the thesis&amp;rsquo; main results that I had to do for the viva.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Norwegian doctoral defence is accompanied by a &amp;lsquo;trial lecture&amp;rsquo; (&lt;em&gt;prøveforelesning&lt;/em&gt;) on a topic of the committee&amp;rsquo;s choosing. &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/pdf/viva.lecture.pdf&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the handout for mine, entitled &lt;em&gt;Progress and problems in language revitalization: The Celtic languages&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>











<item>
<title>Humidity causes complex tones?</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/humidity-causes-complex-tones/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/blog/2015/humidity-causes-complex-tones/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.koensebregts.nl&#34;&gt;Koen Sebregts&lt;/a&gt;  points out that the title of my post is misleading, since the authors explicitly state they do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; predict humidity to cause complex tones. I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it unchanged as a warning to myself.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a new &amp;lsquo;geophonetics&amp;rsquo; paper out at PNAS this morning &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1417413112&#34;&gt;Climate, vocal folds, and tonal languages: Connecting the physiological and geographic dots&lt;/a&gt; by Caleb Everett, Damián Blasi, and Seán Roberts. In a nutshell, the claim, as I understand it, is that since low humidity is inimical to precise manipulation of vocal folds, languages with &amp;lsquo;complex tone&amp;rsquo; (understood as having a more than two-way pitch-based contrast) are unlikely to thrive in regions with low humidity (i.e. hot and arid, and all types of cold). This hypothesis appears to explain the areal patterns in the prevalence of tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phonetic component of the argument seems quite sound to me, and I&amp;rsquo;m not really qualified to judge the evolutionary part of this paper in any reasonable way. As a phonologist, there&amp;rsquo;s something that really bothers me though, and that is the almost total lack of critical discussion of what it means to be a tonal language. It&amp;rsquo;s noticeable that the phonological part of the bibliography is really sparse, especially compared to the phonetic part: there&amp;rsquo;s Moira Yip&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Tone&lt;/em&gt; textbook, several large-scale overviews like Maddieson (1978) and Hyman (2001), a couple of tonogenesis citations, and Jonathan Kaye&amp;rsquo;s (1990) textbook cited as an example of the consensus as disputed by the authors. No other work by Larry Hyman, who has published a lot on the typology of &amp;lsquo;tone languages&amp;rsquo;, no discussion of the whole idea of &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; and how it relates to tone: the only definition given (p. 2) is &amp;lsquo;phonemic tone, in which pitch is used to contrast lexical meaning&amp;rsquo;. The data sources are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wals.info&#34;&gt;WALS&lt;/a&gt; and especially the &lt;a href=&#34;http://phonotactics.anu.edu.au/&#34;&gt;ANU phonotactics database&lt;/a&gt;. Both of these sources, while extremely valuable, put a lot of emphasis on documenting &amp;lsquo;diversity&amp;rsquo; and quite a bit less on pinpointing what exactly it is they&amp;rsquo;re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to the ANU database to have a look at what it says about tone in languages I know about. Now I work on fairly &amp;lsquo;boring&amp;rsquo;, European languages, but recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been getting quite interested in the European &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; systems, plus I actually know a bit about these languages, so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d have a go at a selection. I have to say I wasn&amp;rsquo;t exactly happy with the results. The following list gives the number of tonal contrasts given for that language in the ANU database, and my comments if any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scots Gaelic: 0. This can&amp;rsquo;t be right; there is a &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; or glottalization system in most varieties as far as we know. As a shameless plug, &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/pdf/icngl.paper.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is a paper of mine with more references inside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Welsh: 0. (The pitch system of Welsh is non-trivial, but fair enough.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornish: 0. (Probably, but how do we know for sure?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manx: 0. (Probably true, but how did it end up somewhere in the Trossachs?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breton: 0. (Fair enough, although see the paper linked above for some discussion.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;North Germanic

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Danish: 0. Here&amp;rsquo;s a good example of the controversy. Danish has stød, a type of laryngealization. Does it count? Maybe not, but it has been analysed as being tonal (e.g. by Junko Itô &amp;amp; Armin Mester and Tomas Riad), although &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000354640&#34;&gt;reasonable people disagree&lt;/a&gt;. In any case, tonal dialects of Danish &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/03740463.1990.10411522&#34;&gt;definitely exist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lsquo;Jysk&amp;rsquo;: 0. (Why not Jutland Danish or the like? Anyway, it has both regular stød and so-called Western Jutland stød, how do we count?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Old Norse: 0. We don&amp;rsquo;t know that! Not zero according to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1075/dia.15.1.04ria&#34;&gt;Tomas Riad&lt;/a&gt;, anyway. Or see &lt;a href=&#34;http://uni.hi.is/haukurth/doktorsverkefni/&#34;&gt;Haukur Þorgeirsson&amp;rsquo;s dissertation&lt;/a&gt; – OK, it&amp;rsquo;s in Icelandic, but still&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nynorsk: 2. Nynorsk is a written standard&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aurland: 2. Why Aurland specifically? But fair enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trondheim: 2. Does this mean Standard Norwegian as spoken in Trondheim? Well then yes. But all around Trondheim you have dialects with so-called &amp;lsquo;circumflex accent&amp;rsquo;, where apocope creates a tonal contrast in monosyllables (usually absent in North Germanic). Does it count as 2 (after all, there is only ever a two-way contrast in monosyllables vs polysyllables) or 3 (the traditional way of looking at things)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;West Germanic

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limburgish [sic]: 2. OK, so we count pitch accents as tones. But many people have argued that it&amp;rsquo;s not a &lt;em&gt;lexical tone&lt;/em&gt; contrast but instead something else. How do we count? (Actually, the same question applies to much of North Germanic.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kölsch: 0. Unless I&amp;rsquo;m grossly mistaken, it does have a similar type of &amp;lsquo;tonal accent&amp;rsquo; system to Limburg. So either both have tones or neither.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baltic

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latvian: 2. That&amp;rsquo;s just incorrect, I think – at least in conservative varieties you have a three-way contrast in stressed syllables. OK, the third &amp;lsquo;accent&amp;rsquo; involves glottalization as well, but how do we decide to exclude that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lithuanian: 0. Definitely has a pitch accent system. If Latvian is treated as having two contrasts then surely Lithuanian should have (at least) two?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slavic

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serbian: 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Croatian: 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chakavian [sic]: 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bosnian: 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To me, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t really compute: there are certainly differences among these varieties but as far as I know they&amp;rsquo;re not quite as drastic. (That is off the top of my head, though, I&amp;rsquo;m willing to be corrected.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also note that Basque has 0 contrasts, while Japanese has 2 or 3; there are dialects of Basque that have been argued to have a similar pitch accent system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this is to say that the ANU database is bad and unusable, or that the paper is incorrect rubbish. This is a random, small selection of unrelated languages in a particular region. There is also much to be said for treating European tonal accents as a typologically unusual special case – Jakobson did that with Baltic tonal &lt;em&gt;Sprachbund&lt;/em&gt; in 1931 already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the authors are clear that their predictions should be particularly salient in relatively extreme environmental conditions, so it&amp;rsquo;s not entirely beside the point to look at northern Europe more closely. And it&amp;rsquo;s interesting that in the survey above the ANU database is consistently underreporting the number of tonal contrasts in this fairly cold, fairly dry region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does worry me. I&amp;rsquo;m sure the statistical models give the correct results for the data that&amp;rsquo;s fed into them. I&amp;rsquo;m willing to accept that the large amount of data might drown out this sort of noise. And yet, still, I&amp;rsquo;m finding it difficult to be convinced in matters I know little about when the things that I do know something about are a bit dodgy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this isn&amp;rsquo;t about bashing the munging of large-scale data. This paper is certainly quite explicit in its hypotheses and proposes a causal explanation based on more than correlations alone. But the data appears to have been collected without much regard to the theoretical underpinnings of what it is that we&amp;rsquo;re actually collecting here. And that means I&amp;rsquo;m not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>ICNGL paper</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/icngl11-paper/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/news/2015/icngl11-paper/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;My paper &lt;em&gt;‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic: Reassessing the role of contact&lt;/em&gt; has appeared in &lt;em&gt;New trends in Nordic and general linguistics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Martin Hilpert, Janet Duke, Christine Mertzlufft, Jan-Ola Östman, and Michael Rießler (Mouton de Gruyter). Read more and download a copy &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper considers the origin of &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic
with a view to evaluating the hypothesis that this feature was
borrowed from North Germanic varieties spoken by Norse settlers in
medieval Scotland. It is shown that the &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; system in
Gaelic is tightly bound with metrical structure (more precisely
syllable count), certainly diachronically, and probably (at least in
some varieties) synchronically. Gaelic &amp;lsquo;pitch accent&amp;rsquo; is argued to be
a plausible internal development, parallel to similar phenomena in
other branches of Celtic (specifically in Breton), as well as in
Germanic. This conclusion may appear to undermine the contact
hypothesis, especially in the absence of reliable written sources;
nevertheless, a certain role for Norse-Gaelic contact in the
appearance of the pitch accent system cannot be completely excluded&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>







<item>
<title>Brythonic ‘second lenition’ revisited</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2006/celto-slavica/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk I evaluate the arguments for two competing reconstructions regarding the laryngeal phonology of Proto-Brythonic. I defend the &amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo; interpretation which underplays the role of a &amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo; contrast and instead relies on two separate lenition processes (due to authors such as David Greene and Patrick Sims-Williams), against the &amp;lsquo;classical&amp;rsquo; one due to Kenneth Jackson and defended by John Koch and Graham Isaac, which emphasizes the rôle of aspiration in Proto-Brythonic &amp;lsquo;voiceless&amp;rsquo; stops. In many respects this talk does not really represent my current thinking, but some of the arguments seem to me to retain some value.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Too many levels, too few solutions</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/16mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/16mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk is largely of historic interest, superseded in particular by &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt;, also at the mfm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>‘Pitch accent’ and prosodic structure in Scottish Gaelic</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/pitch-accent-and-prosodic-structure-in-scottish-gaelic-historical-implications/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I consider the nature of the so-called &amp;lsquo;pitch accents&amp;rsquo; in Scottish Gaelic and argue that the contrast is one of metrical structure rather than lexical tone, at least diachronically, and probably also synchronically. This means that they can be reconstructed with an internal origin, and no recourse to contact with North Germanic is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to account for their appearance. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/icngl-proceedings/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; has the analysis in detail, and the historical argument is expounded in some detail in later talks &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/an-echoing-tone-pitch-accent-parallels-in-scandinavia-and-scotland/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2015/pitch-accent-and-preaspiration-in-gaelic-reconsidering-contact-origins/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Laryngeal realism revisited</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/20mfm/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk presents the near-final version of my analysis of Breton laryngeal phonology (largely superseding my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/&#34;&gt;Toronto presentation&lt;/a&gt; and to a certain extent my &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/&#34;&gt;talk from the 6th CLC&lt;/a&gt;). The detailed version of the analysis is in the thesis. I argue that in Breton voiceless obstruents are the marked members of the laryngeal opposition. If this is true, &amp;lsquo;laryngeal realism&amp;rsquo; is incorrect in assuming that languages which mark fortis obstruents with a feature will always realize that feature as aspiration. I argue that the tight connection between phonological contrast and phonetic representation proposed by laryngeal realism isn&amp;rsquo;t correct in any case, so this mismatch is not a major problem for the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Deconstructing mutation in Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/deconstructing-mutation-in-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer the analysis of Breton initial mutations found in my thesis. I argue that there is no such thing as a unified &amp;lsquo;mutation&amp;rsquo; mechanism: instead, this labels covers a variety of processes with different places in the overall grammar. The article-length version of the argument is &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-mutation/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A unified account of the behaviour of high vowels in Bothoa Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/a-unified-account-of-the-behaviour-of-high-vowels-in-bothoa-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I offer an analysis of gliding in Bothoa Breton, as presented in the thesis. I argue that high vowels (especially [i]) either become glides or coalesce with a preceding consonant, in order to avoid hiatus. However, this pattern is disrupted if the high vowel becomes a nucleus at an earlier stage in the cyclic derivation. This provides an argument for stratal models of phonology-morphology interactions, and a strong argument &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; Output-Output Correspondence, because some of the exceptional non-gliding cases cannot be explained by reference to a free-standing form with transparent non-gliding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Here, I propose an analysis of the interacting between final devoicing and vowel lengthening in Friulian (and other related varieties of northern Italy). Historically, stressed vowels lengthen before voiced obstruents, but this is opacified by final devoicing. I capitalize on phonetic studies showing final devoicing in the language to be incomplete and argue that the process is not in fact opaque: devoicing does not involve neutralization but instead the creation of a third, laryngealy unspecified class of obstruents. I also observe that the distribution of moraicity in Friulian presents a challenge to accepted theories of weight assignment, and propose an analysis that relies on language-specific featural representations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>In defence of Richness of the Base</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/in-defence-of-richness-of-the-base-context-free-weight-in-welsh/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I briefly present the analysis of mora assignment to consonants in South Welsh. The pattern can be analysed by appeal to the form of the inputs (i.e. with a massive number of accidental gaps, which is undesirable), or by positing a constraint schema with undesirable consequences for factorial typology. I suggest that the latter solution is preferable theoretically, although it may be premature to choose it for that reason alone.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Vowel reduction in Russian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose a substance-free analysis of vowel reduction in Standard Russian. I argue that the traditional distinction between &amp;lsquo;moderate&amp;rsquo; reduction (in pretonic syllables, producing less central vowels) and &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; reduction (producing central vowels) is not phonologically relevant. The phonological grammar is only responsible for the neutralization patterns and not for the exact phonetic properties of their outcome. In addition, I show that the necessary input-output mappings cannot be effected in a conventional featural system without some weakly supported assumptions: I argue that this demonstrates the viability of a substance-free, emergent-features approach to phonology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>The phonological endgame</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2012/the-phonological-endgame-welsh-svarabhakti-revisited/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I present an analysis of Welsh &amp;lsquo;svarabhakti&amp;rsquo;, whereby a copy of a preceding vowel is inserted to break up final clusters of rising sonority (&lt;em&gt;pwdr&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;rotten&amp;rsquo; is [pudur] rather than *[pudr]). This pattern is said to coexist with a pattern of deleting consonants in such clusters in polysyllables (&lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;danger&amp;rsquo; is [perɪɡ] rather than *[perɪɡl]). It has been argued that the two differing outcomes can be reconciled by appeal to a single constraint on the form of feet. I show that this analysis is not tenable for South Welsh, and propose that deletion (as in &lt;em&gt;perygl&lt;/em&gt;) is not part of the phonological grammar (at least in South Welsh).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Glottal stop insertion in Scottish Gaelic and contrastive syllabification</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Gaelic dialects, mostly in Argyll, show a process of glottal stop epenthesis in stressed light syllables. This has been analysed as a stress-to-weight effect, and I review the evidence to show that this analysis is likely correct, and also that glottal stop insertion is a live phonological process rather than a lexicalized artefact of history. If this is correct, Argyll Gaelic shows an example of lexical storage of syllable structure, sometimes argued to be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Non-contrastive epenthetic segments as surface prosodic structure</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/non-contrastive-epenthetic-segments-as-surface-prosodic-structure/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I analyse two cases where segment epenthesis must be phonological but involves segments that are otherwise non-phonemic in the relevant languages: Argyll Gaelic (see also the &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/glottal-stop-insertion-in-scottish-gaelic-and-contrastive-syllabification/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teangeolaoícht na Gaeilge&lt;/em&gt; talk&lt;/a&gt; to this effect) and Zealand Danish. Such involvement of non-contrastive information in phonological rules might be problematic for contrastivist approaches to phonology. I argue that this problem can be resolve if the epenthesis is analysed as not involving &lt;em&gt;segments&lt;/em&gt;, but instead &lt;em&gt;features&lt;/em&gt; attaching directly to suprasegmental nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Phonemicization vs. phonologization</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2013/phonemicization-vs-phonologization-voiced-fricatives-in-old-english-and-brythonic/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;We consider the status of &amp;lsquo;voiced&amp;rsquo; (really lenis) fricatives in Old English and in Brythonic Celtic. In the received view, they are not &amp;lsquo;phonemic&amp;rsquo; in Old English, yet their distribution is clearly sensitive to phonological structure. We propose that they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; distinct phonological symbols, coerced into predictable distributions by the phonological computation. We also offer a similar analysis for Brythonic Celtic. The situation is argued to result as a predictable consequence of the life cycle of phonological processes rather than from language contact, &lt;em&gt;contra&lt;/em&gt; previous suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Head-dependent asymmetries in Munster Irish prosody</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose an analysis of stress in Munster Irish which builds on two important premises. First, I argue for a distinction between the notion &amp;lsquo;head of a constituent&amp;rsquo; and the notion of &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo;: these are separate entities, and the typologically frequent isomorphic distribution of the two is just one possible outcome of the phonological computation. Second, I propose to employ a particular family of constraints requiring head-dependent asymmetries (Dresher and van der Hulst 1998) to account for the mismatch between the placement of foot heads and stress in Munster Irish. Overall, the paper is an argument for elaborate abstract structure as an explanatory factor in phonology, as opposed to relatively shallow, substance-based representations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Honours Foundation: Phonology and Phonetics</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2013/hfpp/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2013/hfpp/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course was an introduction to phonological theory and to laboratory phonology &amp;mdash; the use of phonetic evidence to answer theoretical phonological questions. I was responsible for the morphophonology portion of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course has now been discontinued. LEL Honours students interested in these topics may look at LASC10088 &lt;em&gt;Phonological Theory&lt;/em&gt; and/or LASC10090 &lt;em&gt;Phonetics and Laboratory Phonology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>







<item>
<title>LEL2E: Structure and History of European Languages</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2e/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2e/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is (optionally) a part of the pre-Honours sequence in the Linguistics undergraduate degree (but can of course be taken as an outside course). In &lt;sup&gt;2013&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2014&lt;/sub&gt;, I was responsible for the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celtic languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topics in the phonology of European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>LEL2D: Cross-linguistic variation: Limits and Theories</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2d/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/teaching/2014/lel2d/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This course is part of the pre-Honours sequence in all LEL single Honours degrees, as well as of some joint degrees (in addition to being available as an outside course). Its main aim is to familiarize students with the study of linguistic diversity and the relationship between language typology and theory-building. In &lt;sup&gt;2013&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2014&lt;/sub&gt;, I was responsible for most of the phonology block. We covered the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phonological typology and theory. Universals in phonology; descriptive and analytic universals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universals of inventory organization; feature theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syllable structure. Typology of syllable structures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimality Theory and its application to syllable structure typology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government Phonology; restrictiveness in theory-building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress; metrical typology; metrical typology in OT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Head-dependent asymmetries in Munster Irish prosody</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I propose an analysis of stress in Munster Irish which builds on two important premises. First, I argue for a distinction between the notion &amp;lsquo;head of a constituent&amp;rsquo; and the notion of &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo;: these are separate entities, and the typologically frequent isomorphic distribution of the two is just one possible outcome of the phonological computation. Second, I propose to employ a particular family of constraints requiring head-dependent asymmetries (Dresher and van der Hulst 1998) to account for the mismatch between the placement of foot heads and stress in Munster Irish. Overall, the paper is an argument for elaborate abstract structure as an explanatory factor in phonology, as opposed to relatively shallow, substance-based representations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Fonetikk versus fonologi</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2008/novemberseminaret-reduction/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Dette er det fyrste føredraget i prosjektet om russisk vokalreduksjon. Sluttversjonen kan ein finne i &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/jl-russian-vowel-reduction/&#34;&gt;denne artikkelen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>







<item>
<title>Sandhi, mutation, and contrast: laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This paper was presented at the Toronto-Tromsø Phonology Workshop in Toronto. It presents an analysis of laryngeal phonology in Plougrescant Breton, with an emphasis on the idea of a ternary contrast implemented through a distinction between the presence and absence of a bare geometric node. I later explored similar ideas in my work on Friulian (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/final-devoicing-and-vowel-lengthening-in-the-north-of-italy-a-representational-approach/&#34;&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;). A lot of the analysis eventually made it to my thesis, but the Plougrescant dialect is interesting because it combines the laryngeal phenomena found in Bothoa Breton with a prosodic system more similar to Welsh.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>











<item>
<title>Structure versus prominence</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I propose an analysis of the stress system of Munster Irish, which evinces a disruption of normal directionality only in words with two initial heavy syllables. The analysis relies on recursion of subsyllable constituents and on a formal distinction between &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;head status&amp;rsquo;. The full version of the analysis can be found in &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Russian palatalization</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk we argue that the traditional view of vowel-driven palatalization in Russian is inadequate, at least for two reasons. First, it relies on a six-vowel interpretation of the Russian inventory that is not adequate from a phonetic perspective. Second, and more importantly, it undergenerates the range of alternations found in Modern Standard Russian. Instead, we argue that palatalization must be driven by a floating feature attached to the left edge of suffixes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>





<item>
<title>Right at the left edge</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/rara/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/rara/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper I offer an overview of systems of initial consonant mutations found in the world&amp;rsquo;s languages and attempt to propose a preliminary typology. Many of these phenomena can probably be subsumed under a general theory of nonconcatenative morphology and phonology, but in some cases (notably some of the Celtic ones) the mutations&amp;rsquo; place in the grammar is less clear. For another, more detailed take on this architectural issue in the specific case of Breton, see also &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/breton-mutation/&#34;&gt;this later paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Feature geometry meets contrastive specification</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/feature-geometry-meets-contrastive-specification-incomplete-neutralization-reloaded/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I propose an analysis of the interaction between vowel lengthening before voiced obstruents and final devoicing in two languages: Friulian and Breton. I argue that such interactions are transparent and involve a three-way laryngeal contrast formalized geometrically, with true voiceless obstruents the most structurally complex and devoiced ones least. The Friulian analysis was later published &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/lingua-friulian/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and the Breton was largely incorporated into the thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>How good is the internal evidence for multiple-level phonological computation? A view from Russian</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/how-good-is-the-internal-evidence-for-multiple-level-phonological-computation-a-view-from-russian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Relying in part on the analysis of palatalization offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I argue that Russian does not provide strong &lt;em&gt;phonology-internal&lt;/em&gt; evidence for level ordering, contra suggestions by authors such as Morris Halle and Jerzy Rubach. A more focused argument to the same effect is offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>A bad case of excessive computation</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/a-bad-case-of-excessive-computation-the-role-of-morphology-in-palatalization-related-alternations-in-russian/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I use the analysis of palatalization in Modern Standard Russian offered &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/russian-palatalization-the-true-r-story/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to argue that these data do not provide a watertight argument for multilevel phonological computation, and that phonological analysis must be combined with a theory of ordering (such as Stratal OT) if the hypothesis of parallel computation is to be challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Incomplete neutralization and unorthodox markedness in Breton laryngeal phonology</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/incomplete-neutralization-and-unorthodox-markedness-in-breton-laryngeal-phonology/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;This talk represents a further iteration of the programme of research on Breton laryngeal phonology started &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2009/sandhi-mutation-and-contrast-laryngeal-phonology-in-plougrescant-breton/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here, I present both phonological and phonetic evidence for incomplete neutralization in final devoicing in Breton and for the greater markednesss of voiceless (&amp;lsquo;fortis&amp;rsquo;) stops. The analysis is largely retained in the thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>



<item>
<title>Structure versus prominence</title>
<link>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
<guid>http://anghyflawn.github.io/presentation/2010/ocp7-poster/</guid>
<description>&lt;p&gt;I propose an analysis of the stress system of Munster Irish, which evinces a disruption of normal directionality only in words with two initial heavy syllables. The analysis relies on recursion of subsyllable constituents and on a formal distinction between &amp;lsquo;stress&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;head status&amp;rsquo;. The full version of the analysis can be found in &lt;a href=&#34;http://anghyflawn.github.io/writing/munster-irish-stress/&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>


  </channel>
</rss>
